[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "How many bones does an adult human skeleton have?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 206",
            "b) 209",
            "c) 207",
            "d) 205"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the skeleton of the adult there are 206 distinct bones and the bifurcation is given below:-\nVertebral column – 26\nSkull – 22\nHyoid bone – 1\nRibs and sternum – 25\nUpper extremities – 64\nLower extremities – 62\nAuditory ossicles – 6. "
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Name the four classes of bones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long, short, regular, irregular",
            "b) Big, small, flat, bulged",
            "c) Long, Short, Flat, and Irregular",
            "d) Big, small, regular, irregular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bones are divisible into four classes: Long, Short, Flat, and Irregular. The long bones are found in the limbs, and each consists of a body or shaft and two extremities. Some of the irregular bones are vertebrae, sacrum, coccyx, temporal, sphenoid, maxilla, palatine, inferior nasal concha, mandible and hyoid. Flat bones are composed of two thin layers of compact tissue enclosing between them variable quantity of cancellous tissue. Where a part of the skeleton is intended for strength and compactness combined with limited movement, it is constructed of a number of short bones, as in the carpus and tarsus."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Name the two kinds of tissues present in the bone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cancellous tissue and non-compact tissue",
            "b) Compact tissue and non compact tissue",
            "c) Compact tissue and cancellous tissue",
            "d) Non compact tissue and cancellous tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On examining a section of any bone, it is seen to be composed of two kinds of tissue, one of which is dense in texture, like ivory, and is termed compact tissue; the other consists of slender fibers and lamellæ, which join to form a reticular structure; this, from its resemblance to lattice-work, is called cancellous tissue. The compact tissue is placed on the exterior of the bone and cancellous in the interior."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following connective tissue envelopes the bone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Periosteum",
            "b) Pericardium",
            "c) Myocardium",
            "d) Marrow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The periosteum is a membrane that covers the outer surface of all bones but not to cartilaginous extremities.  When strong tendons or ligaments are attached to a bone, the periosteum is incorporated with them."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which cell secretes the matrix for bone formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osteoclastoma",
            "b) Osteoclast",
            "c) Mesoblasts",
            "d) Osteoblasts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Compact bone tissue forms the outer layer of all bones while spongy or cancellous bone forms the inner layer of all bones. Spongy bone tissue does not contain osteons. it consists of trabeculae. "
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of the following are two types of bone marrow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red marrow and yellow marrow",
            "b) Red marrow and white marrow",
            "c) Yellow marrow and white marrow",
            "d) White marrow and blue marrow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Osteoblasts are cell which secrete the substance of bone. They are single nucleus cells. It helps in synthesis of bone."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the largest segment of the movable part of the vertebral column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coccygeal",
            "b) Cervical",
            "c) Lumbar vertebrae",
            "d) Thoracic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two types of bone marrows are red marrow and yellow marrow. Red marrow consists of hematopoietic tissue. The yellow marrow is made up of fat cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Choose the correct vertebral formula of vertebral column of human being.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C7 Th13 L4 S5 Co4",
            "b) C7 Th12 L5 S5 Co4",
            "c) C7 Th13 L5 S5 Co4",
            "d) C7 Th12 L5 S5 Co4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The vertebrae in the upper three regions of the column remain distinct throughout life. They are known as true or movable vertebrae. Those of the sacral and coccygeal regions, on the other hand, are termed false or fixed vertebrae, because they are united with one another in the adult to form two bones—five forming the upper bone or sacrum and four the terminal bone or coccyx."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which vertebra has odontoid process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atlas",
            "b) Axis",
            "c) Cervical",
            "d) Coccyx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lumbar vertebrae are the largest segments of the movable part of the vertebral column. They can be distinguished by the absence of a foramen in the transverse process and by the absence of facets on the sides of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the vestigial bony part of the human skeleton?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cervical",
            "b) Cranium",
            "c) Clavicle",
            "d) Coccyx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The vertebrae are thirty-three in number and are grouped under the names cervical, thoracic, lumbar, sacral, and coccygeal. According to the regions they occupy there are seven in the cervical region, twelve in the thoracic, five in the lumbar, five in the sacral and four in the coccygeal."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The joint between atlas and axis is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ball and socket joint",
            "b) Saddle joint",
            "c) Pivot joint",
            "d) Angular joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The odontoid process is known as the dens. It is an upward projectile of bone that arises from the front part of the center of the axis vertebra."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "The major function of intervertebral discs is to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorb shock",
            "b) String the vertebrae together",
            "c) Prevent injuries",
            "d) Prevent hypertension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vestigial structures are body parts that seemingly have no purpose or function. The coccyx is commonly called as tailbone and is the final segment of the vertebral column in humans."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "What is the number of true, false and floating ribs in man?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6, 2, 3",
            "b) 7, 2, 4",
            "c) 6, 3, 4",
            "d) 7, 3, 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: True ribs=7pairs, False ribs=3pairs, Floating ribs = 2 pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which ribs have “buckle handle” type of movements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rib no 1-2",
            "b) Rib no 3-5",
            "c) Rib no 6-10",
            "d) Rib no 11-12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bucket-handle is a movement of ribs that results in a change in transverse diameter of the thorax. It helps inspiration and expiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a breast bone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scapula",
            "b) Ribs",
            "c) Sternum",
            "d) Clavicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sternum or breastbone is a long flat bone shaped like a necktie located in the center of the chest. It helps to protect the heart, lungs and major blood vessels from injury."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Scapula is a large triangular flat bone situated in the dorsal part of the thorax between _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The second and fifth ribs",
            "b) The second and seventh ribs",
            "c) The third and seventh ribs",
            "d) The fourth and seventh ribs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scapula is a flat and triangular bone present at the back of shoulder as shoulder blade. Scapula is produced into scapular spine which ends into a triangular acromian process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Name the upper handle like part found in sternum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xiphoid cartilage",
            "b) Manubrium",
            "c) Body",
            "d) Facet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Manubrium is the upper handle like part found in sternum. Lower small cartilaginous plate is called Xiphoid cartilage."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is associated with ribs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synovitis",
            "b) Bursitis",
            "c) Rickets",
            "d) Berri Berri"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is caused due to deficiency of vitamin D and calcium in the bones. The ribs affected are the second to the eighth. In rickets, the ends of the ribs, where they join the costal cartilages, become enlarged, giving rise to the so-called “rickety rosary,” which in mild cases is only found on the internal surface of the thorax."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which part of human skeleton forms the helmet for the protection of human brain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temporal bone",
            "b) Hyoid",
            "c) Mandible",
            "d) Cranium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cranium (brain box). It is the large and hollow part of the skull which encloses and protects the brain in the cranial cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Human Cranium has ________ bones.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 8 bones that forms the cranium. The ethmoid bone, the sphenoid bone, the frontal bone, occipital bone, two parietal bone and two temporal bones."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Name of the tongue bone is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frontal bone",
            "b) Zygomatic bone",
            "c) Hyoid bone",
            "d) Mandible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is a horse shoe shaped which supports tongue. It also supports the throat and provides surface for attachment of tongue muscle."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Through which apparatus brain is continuous with spinal cord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Palatines",
            "b) Foramen magnam",
            "c) Cranial cavity",
            "d) Foramen maxilla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The skull which is attached to the body two articulatory condyles is known as dicondylic. In craniostylic jaw suspension upper jaw fuses throughout its length with the cranium. Hyomandibular forms the ear ossicles malleus and incus two dermal bones dentary of lower jaw and squamosal of skull provide the articulation between jaws."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "How many bones are present in a human skull?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 28",
            "c) 29",
            "d) 31"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Foramen magnam is the largest cranial foramen lying in occipital part of the skull. Brain continues the spinal cord through this foramen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Ear occicle incus is modified form of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jugal bone",
            "b) Quadrate bone",
            "c) Articular bone",
            "d) Hyomandibular bone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 29 bones. Cranium=8 Face=14 Ear ossicles=6 Hyoid=1. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following bone is called collar bone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetabulum",
            "b) Pelvic",
            "c) Scapula",
            "d) Clavicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Clavicle bone is a narrow rod like S shaped bone extending between sternum and acromion process of scapula bone. The clavicle forms the anterior portion of the shoulder girdle."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Glenoid cavity is found in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelvic girdle",
            "b) Pectoral girdle",
            "c) Sternum",
            "d) Humerous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pectoral girdle also known as shoulder girdles. At the junction of clavicle and scapula there is cup like depression called glenoid cavity, in which the head of the humerus fits in and forms shoulder joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Name of the shoulder bone is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetabulum",
            "b) Pelvic",
            "c) Scapula",
            "d) Clavicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The scapula forms the posterior part of the shoulder girdle. It is a flat, triangular bone, with two surfaces, three borders, and three angles."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Colle’s fracture is associated with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Femur",
            "b) Ulna",
            "c) Radius",
            "d) Humerus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Colle’s fracture s a type of fracture of the distal forearm in which the broken end radius is bent backward. Symptoms may include pain swelling deformity etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "The total number of bones found in right upper limb is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 26",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The upper arm is divided into 3 regions. These consist of arm located between shoulder and elbow joints the forearm which is between the elbow and wrist joints and the hand which is located distal to the wrist. There are 30 bones in each upper limb."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "An acromian process is characteristically found in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pelvic girdle of mammals",
            "b) Skull of frog",
            "c) Pectoral girdle of mammals",
            "d) Sperm of mammals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is seen in pectoral girdle. Scapula is produced into a scapular spine which ends into a triangular acromian process."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which cup lies at the junction of 3 bones of pelvic girdle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ilium",
            "b) Ischium",
            "c) Pubis",
            "d) Acetabulum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two pubis bones are joined by a cartilaginous slightly movable joint called pubic symphysis to enclose an arch like pelvis. At the junction of these bones there is a cup like depression the acetabulum in which the head of femur bone of thigh fits in."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as a knee cap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetabulum",
            "b) Scapula",
            "c) Patella",
            "d) Clavicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pelvic girdle are located in the lower part of trunk. It is formed of 3 bones ilium on upper side pubis on inner side and ischium below the pubis."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "How many bones does ankle has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Ankle also called as tarsus has seven bones called tarsal’s. It is arranged in three rows having gliding joints."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Thumb (great toe) of foot is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pollex",
            "b) Hallux",
            "c) Index",
            "d) Coracoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thumb of foot is called as hallux.T he first digit of the forearm is called pollex."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The toe bones are called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phalanges",
            "b) Tarsal",
            "c) Metatarsals",
            "d) Talus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Foot is formed of 3 parts. Ankle, sole and toes."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "What is sole bone known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Talus",
            "b) Metatarsals",
            "c) Tibia",
            "d) Fibula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Toes are with 14 bones called phalanges. Phalangel formula of foot of man is 2,3,3,3,3."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Joint of femur with pelvic girdle is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ball and socket",
            "b) Pivot",
            "c) Saddle",
            "d) Hinge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sole is with 5 metatarsals. it is called as metatarsus."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "_______ acts as a shock absorber to cushion when tibia and femur come together.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disc",
            "b) Tendon",
            "c) Ligament",
            "d) Cartilage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pelvic girdles of a female are more flexible broader and shallower than those of male. It is an adaption for pregnancy and parturition."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The total number of bones in lower extremity is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 62",
            "b) 63",
            "c) 61",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Femur is the longest bone of human body. It is differentiated into 3 parts head shaft and condyle.  It joins pelvic girdle by ball and socket joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The study of joints is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archaeology",
            "b) Osteology",
            "c) Syndesmology",
            "d) Arthrology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Study of joints is known as arthrology. Slightly movable joints are called amphiarthorses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The synovial joint are also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Megablast",
            "b) Periosteum",
            "c) Diarthrosis",
            "d) Arthrois"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Synovial joint is also known as diarthrosis. It joins bones with a fibrous joint capsule that is continuous with the periosteum of the joined bones, constitutes the outer boundary of the synovial cavity, and surrounds the bones articulating surfaces. The synovial cavity is filled with synovial fluid. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is associated with joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gout",
            "b) Osteoporosis",
            "c) Arthritis",
            "d) Tetany"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arthritis is inflammation and painful joints due to degradation of cartilages or synovial membrane or deposition of uric acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which cartilage is present at the joints of long bones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcified",
            "b) Elastic",
            "c) Hyaline",
            "d) Fibrous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hyaline is present at the joints of long bones."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The joints can be classified into ________ main types.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sutures are immovable joints. In sutures, skull bones are joined by strong bundles of white fibers."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which type of joint lies at the shoulder joint and hip joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pivot joint",
            "b) Angular joint",
            "c) Ball and socket joint",
            "d) Hinge joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The joints can be classified into three main types. Immovable or synarthrose joints, Slightly movable or amphiarthrose joints, and Freely movable or synovial joints. "
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Synovial joint is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pivot joint",
            "b) Fibrous joint",
            "c) Ball and socket joint",
            "d) Cartilaginous joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ball and socket joints have a ball like spherical end called head which fits into cup like depression. It is freely movable in all directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following pair is correctly matched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cartilaginous joint- skull bones",
            "b) Gliding joint- between zygapophyses of vertebrae",
            "c) Hinge joint- between vertebrae",
            "d) Fibrous joint- between phalanges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  In synovial joint one bone forms knob like swelling while other one forms a depression. The ends of both the bones are covered by smooth articular cartilages. Between two bones is synovial cavity filled with synovial fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Hinge joint is present between _______ and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Femur and ulna",
            "b) Humerus and ulna",
            "c) Femur and pectoral girdle",
            "d) Femur and pelvic girdle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Zygapophyses are projections of the vertebrae that serve the purpose of fitting with an adjacent vertebra, the actual region of contact is called articular facet."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Example of pivot joint is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hip joints",
            "b) Ankle joints",
            "c) Radio ulnar joints",
            "d) Metacarpophalangeal  joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hinge joints are formed between two or more bones where the bones can only move alone one axis to flex or extend."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which of the following connects margins of lateral masses of atlas with those of posterior articular surfaces of axis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Articular capsules",
            "b) Posterior atlantoaxial",
            "c) Anterior atlantoaxial",
            "d) The transverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Articular capsules are thin, loose and connect the axis. Each is strengthened at posterior and medial part by an accessory ligament which is attached below to the body of axis near base of odontoid process."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which of the following is covered by parotid gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Articular disc",
            "b) Sphenomandibular",
            "c) Temporomandibular ligament",
            "d) Stylomandibular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Temporomandibular ligament consists of two short narrow fascicule one in front of other attached above to the lateral surface of zygomatic arch and to tubercle on its lower border. It is covered by parotid gland and by integument."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Name the ligament that connects the anterior and posterior surface of 7th coastal cartilage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The costoxiphoid ligament",
            "b) The radiate sternocoastal",
            "c) The interarticular sternocoastal",
            "d) Articular capsules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The costoxiphoid ligament and sometimes the sixth to front and back of xiphoid process. They vary in length and breadth in different subjects; those on back of joint are less distinct than those in front."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Ligaments connecting bones of the pelvis with each other may be divided into ________ groups.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: They can be divided into 4 groups.\n1) Those connecting sacrum and ilium\n2) Those passing between sacrum and coccyx\n3) Those uniting the sacrum and coccyx\n4) Those between two public bones."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "The sternoclavicular articulation is a _________ arthrodial joint.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Double",
            "c) Triple",
            "d) 4 layered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pelvis girdle supports and protects contained viscera and affords surfaces for attachment of trunk and lower limb muscles. The most important mechanical function of pelvis is to transmit the weight of trunk and upper limbs to lower extremity."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The sternoclavicular joint is a type of __________ joint.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hinge joint",
            "b) Ball and socket",
            "c) Saddle type",
            "d) Pivot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sternoclavicular articulation is a double arthrodial joint. The parts entering into its formation are the sterna end of clavicle upper and lateral part of manubrium and cartilage of the first rib."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "How many ligaments are present in a wrist joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sternoclavicular joint is a type of saddle join. It allows movement of clavicle predominately in anterioposteior and vertical planes although some rotation occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of the wrist joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius",
            "b) Ulna",
            "c) Scaphoid",
            "d) Articular disc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acrominoclaviclular joint is located at the tip of the shoulder. It allows the joint to move."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Which of the following ligament is called y shaped ligament of Bigelow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Ischiocapsular",
            "b) The glenoidal labrum",
            "c) The Pubocapsular",
            "d) Illiofemoral ligament"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 4 ligaments are present in the wrist joint. They are Palmer radiocarpel, dorsal radiocarpel, ullnar collateral and radial collateral."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Ligamentous fibers that  provides stability to hip joint capsule is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral ligament",
            "b) Acetabular labrum",
            "c) Retinacular fibres",
            "d) Deltoid ligament"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ulna is not a part of the wrist joint. Ulna articulates with radius first proximal to wrist joint at distal radioulnar joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Joint with two articulations in one capsule medial side connects distal end of tibia and medial malleolus to talus. Lateral side connects malleolus of fibula with talus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Talocrural joint",
            "b) Lateral meniscus",
            "c) Lateral ligament",
            "d) Patellar ligament"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Illiofemoral ligament is a band of great strength which lies in front of joint. It is intimately connected with capsule and serves to strengthen it."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Diarthrosos and synovial articulation between condyles of femur and condyles of tibia is ______ joint.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metatarsophalangeal joints",
            "b) Tibiofemoral joints",
            "c) Tarsometatarsals joints",
            "d) Patellofemoral joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Knee joint consists of 3 joints within a single synovial cavity. They are medial condylar joint, lateral condylar joint and patellofemoral joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "The blood corpuscles are of _________ kinds.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The blood corpuscles are of 3 types. They are colored corpuscles- erythrocytes, Colorless corpuscles – Leucocytes and blood platelets.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Blood is stained with _________ stain.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylene blue",
            "b) Safranin",
            "c) Leishman stain",
            "d) Carbol fuchsine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Leishman stain is used in microscopy for staining blood smears. It is generally used to differentiate and identify leucocytes malaria parasites and trypanosomas."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Process of formation of blood corpuscles is called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Haemolysis",
            "b) Haemozoin",
            "c) Haemopoesis",
            "d) Haemoter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The Process of formation of blood corpuscles is called Haemopoesis. It occurs in the bone marrow."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Graveyard of RBC is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spleen",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Kidney",
            "d) Thymus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Old red blood cells are recycled in the spleen. Platelets and white blood cells are stored there. Spleen also helps fight certain kinds of bacteria that cause pneumonia and meningitis."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which leucocytes release heparin and histamine in blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neutrophil",
            "b) Basophil",
            "c) Eosinophil",
            "d) Monocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Basophil contains heparin which is an anticoagulant. It is a type of white blood cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which blood cells secrets antibody?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eosinophils",
            "b) Monocytes",
            "c) Lymphocytes",
            "d) Neutrophils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A Lymphocyte is a type of white blood cell that is a part of the immune system. There are 2 main types of Lymphocyte: B cells and T cells. The B cells produce antibodies that are used to attack invading bacteria, viruses and toxins.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Vitamin essential for blood clotting is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin K",
            "b) Vitamin A",
            "c) Vitamin B",
            "d) Vitamin C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vitamin K is used by the body to help blood clot. Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. By helping the blood clot vitamin k might decrease the effectiveness of warfarin."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Hemoglobin is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reproductive pigment",
            "b) Respiratory pigment",
            "c) Carbohydrate",
            "d) Fat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hemoglobin is a protein in RBC that carries oxygen throughout the body. Lower Hemoglobin counts indicate anemia."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Absence of which clotting factor leads to Hemophilia-A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factor VII",
            "b) Factor VIII",
            "c) Factor IX",
            "d) Factor X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hemophilia-A is also called factor VIII deficiency or classic hemophilia. It is a genetic disorder caused by missing or defective factor VIII a clotting protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "What prevents the clotting of blood inside blood vessels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heparin",
            "b) Serotonin",
            "c) Fibrinogen",
            "d) Fibrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heparin is an anticoagulant that prevents the formation of blood clots. It is used to treat blood clots in veins arteries or lung. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Red cell count is carried out by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrogram",
            "b) Sphygmomanometer",
            "c) Haemoglobinometer",
            "d) Haemocytometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Haemocytometer is a device designed and used for counting blood cells. It was invented by Louis Charles Malassez."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the thinnest blood vessel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Artery",
            "b) Arterioles",
            "c) Meta Arterioles",
            "d) Capillary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Capillary is the thinnest blood vessel order of 10µm in diameter. Each capillary is lined with simple layer of flat cells called endothelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "The arteries are composed of _________ coat.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The arteries are composed of 3 coats. They are as follows:-\n\n An internal or endothelial coat\n External or connective tissue coat\n A middle or muscular coat.\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "What is the study of blood vessels called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulmonology",
            "b) Electrophysiology",
            "c) Angiology",
            "d) Cardiology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Angiology is the medical specialty which studies the diseases in the circulatory system and blood vessels."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the thickest wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right ventricle",
            "b) Left ventricle",
            "c) Right auricle",
            "d) Left auricle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Left ventricle is one of the four chambers of the heart. The left ventricle has a thicker wall than right ventricles because the left ventricle has to pump blood all the way around the body but right ventricle only has to pump it to the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Pulmonary vein carries ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deoxygenated blood",
            "b) Mixed blood",
            "c) Oxygenated blood",
            "d) Pure blood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pulmonary vein carries Oxygenated blood from lungs to the heart. The largest pulmonary veins are the four main pulmonary veins two from each lung that drain into the left atrium of the heart."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "The artery is blood vessel which carries blood _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Away from the heart",
            "b) Towards the heart",
            "c) Has deoxygenated blood without exception",
            "d) Mixed blood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The arteries are the blood vessels that deliver oxygen rich blood from heart to other organs of the body. Artery is a muscular tube lined by smooth tissues and has three layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Frog heart: 3 chambered:: Human heart: ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Human heart is four chambered. It has two auricles and two ventricles.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Mention the organ which is present in thoracic cavity through which food passes from throat to stomach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trachea",
            "b) Lungs",
            "c) Bronchi",
            "d) Esophagus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Musculi pectinatis are parallel ridges in the walls of atria of the heart. They are so called because of their resemblance to the teeth comb as in pecten. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Accumulation of fluid in pleural cavity is called as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrothorax",
            "b) Hyperthorax",
            "c) Hypothorax",
            "d) Haemothroax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Esophagus is also known as food pipe. It is a muscular pipe about 8 inches long and is lined by tissue called mucosa."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "How many compartments does thoracic cavity have?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thoracic cavity is the second largest hollow space of the body. It is also called a chest cavity. The largest hollow space is abdominal cavity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which organ is present medial to the lungs and posterior to sternum in thoracic cavity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trachea",
            "b) Heart",
            "c) Food pipe",
            "d) Diaphragm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Accumulation of fluid in pleural cavity is called as Hydrothorax. If a fluid is bloody the condition is called hemothroax and if it contains pus it is called pythorax."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "What is the name of serous membrane that covers thoracic cavity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myocardium",
            "b) Pericardium",
            "c) Pleura",
            "d) Lining membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thoracic cavity has 3 compartments. It has mediastinum and 2 pleural cavities. Mediastinum is a home to heart trachea and vessels. Pleural cavity contains lungs and pleural linings."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "From where does the aorta originate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right ventricle",
            "b) Left auricle",
            "c) Right auricle",
            "d) Left ventricle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aorta is the largest artery in the body. The aorta begins at the top of the left ventricle. The heart pums blood from the left ventricle into the aorta through the aortic valve."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "How many aortic valves are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 4 aortic valves are present. They are ascending aorta, aortic arch, thoracic aorta and abdominal aorta."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "The aorta distributes _______ type blood.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygenated blood",
            "b) Deoxygenated blood",
            "c) Mixed blood",
            "d) Cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aorta distributes oxygenated blood to all parts of the body through the systemic circulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Name the valve which is associated with aorta?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitral valve",
            "b) Aortic valve",
            "c) Tricuspid valve",
            "d) Pulmonic valve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The aortic valve is located between the left ventricles and the aorta. Valves maintain one way blood flow through the heart."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which artery supplies oxygenated blood to liver, stomach and abdominal esophagus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Branchiocephalic artery",
            "b) Costacervical artery",
            "c) Mesenteric artery",
            "d) Celiac artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Celiac artery supplies oxygenated blood to liver, stomach abdominal esophagus, spleen and superior half of both the duodenum and pancreas. Structure of Celiac artery corresponds to embryonic foregut."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Name the artery which supplies blood to the diaphragm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal iliac artery",
            "b) Pancreatic coduodenal artery",
            "c) Inferior phrenic artery",
            "d) Carotid artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Cloud User or the cloud consumer or the self-service user decides which computing resources such as CPU, memory, storage etc. to use for their instances."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Name the major artery of head and neck.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thyrocerival artery",
            "b) Colic artery",
            "c) External carotid artery",
            "d) Suprarenal artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: External carotid artery is the major artery of head and neck. It arises from the common carotid artery when it splits into internal and external carotid artery."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the three major branches of the coeliac trunk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right gastric artery",
            "b) Left gastric artery",
            "c) Spleenic artery",
            "d) Common hepatic artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Right gastric artery arises above pylorus from the hepatic artery. It descends to the pyloric end of the stomach and passes from right to left along lesser curvature supplying it with branches and anastomosing with left gastric artery."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which is the only organ to receive arterial supply from all 3 branches of the coeliac trunk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Spleen",
            "c) Liver",
            "d) Pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coeliac trunk is a major visceral artery in the abdominal cavity. It supplies oxygenated blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which artery supplies to a tail of pancreas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Left gastric",
            "b) Right gastric",
            "c) Common hepatic",
            "d) Splenic artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Splenic artery is the blood vessel that supplies oxygenated blood to the spleen. It branches from celiac artery and follows the course superior to the pancreas."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The right subclavian artery arises from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subclavian artery",
            "b) Common carotid artery",
            "c) Arch of aorta",
            "d) Branchiocephalic trunk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The arterial supply to upper limb begins in the chest as subclavian artery. The right subclavian artery arises from Branchiocephalic trunk, while left subclavian branches directly off the arch of the aorta."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which artery is the main source of blood for the arm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ulnar artery",
            "b) Radial artery",
            "c) Brachial artery",
            "d) Profunda branchii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brachial artery is the main source of blood for arm. When axillary artery reaches the lower border of teres major it becomes brachial arteries."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which artery contributes mainly to supply of thumb and lateral side of index finger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial artery",
            "b) Ulnar artery",
            "c) Deep palmar arch",
            "d) Brachial artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radial artery contributes mainly to supply of thumb and lateral side of index finger. Radial artery enters hand dorsally crossing the floor of anatomical sniffbox."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "What muscle does axillary artery pass beneath?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pectoralis minor",
            "b) Pectoralis major",
            "c) Sub scapularis",
            "d) Biceps branchii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pectoralis minor is a thin, triangular muscle situated at upper part of chest and beneath the Pectoralis major. It originates from 3rd and 5th ribs and inserts on coracoids process of the scapula."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which clinical sign indicates ischaemia of forearm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volkmann’s Contracture",
            "b) Ulnar claw",
            "c) Hand of benediction",
            "d) Carpel tunnel syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Volkmann’s Contracture is a permanent flexion contracture of the hand at the wrist resulting in a claw like deformity of the hand and finger. Passive extension of fingers is restricted and painful."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "What is the name of the deep artery of the arm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial artery",
            "b) Profunda branchii",
            "c) Brachial artery",
            "d) Axillary artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Profunda branchii is the branch of brachial artery.  It is the deep artery of arm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following artery provides blood supply to head and neck of femur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Femoral",
            "b) Lateral femoral circumflex",
            "c) Medial femoral circumflex",
            "d) External Illiac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Femoral artery is second largest artery in the body. It is present in the thigh. It is the main arterial supply to the lower limbs. The first largest artery is aorta."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "From which artery does superior and inferior gluteal artery arise?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal Iliac",
            "b) Obturator",
            "c) Femoral",
            "d) External Illiac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Medial femoral circumflex arise from posterior aspect of profunda femoris artery. It is present in upper thigh that helps blood supply to neck and head of the femur."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is the name of a series of arteries which supply the blood to knee joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pariarticular",
            "b) Medial circumflex",
            "c) Dorsalis Pedis",
            "d) Genicular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Internal Iliac is the main artery of pelvis. It was formerly known as hypogastric artery."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which artery carries blood to posterior compartment of legs?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Dorsalis Pedis",
            "b) Posterior tibial artery",
            "c) Lateral femoral circumflex",
            "d) Internal Iliac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Genicular artery refers to one of six arteries in human leg most of which anastomoses in the knee region."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Portal system includes vein which drains blood from _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head and neck",
            "b) Lungs",
            "c) Abdominal part",
            "d) Kidneys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Portal system includes vein which drains blood from abdominal part of digestive tube, spleen, pancreas and gall bladder. The exception is a rectum. It is about 8cm long."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Portal circulation ends in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liver",
            "b) Heart",
            "c) Stomach",
            "d) Lungs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Portal circulation begins in capillary plexuses and ends in liver sinusoids."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Name the vein that drains blood from gall bladder directly into hepatic veins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastric vein",
            "b) Paraumbilical vein",
            "c) Pancreaticoduodenal vein",
            "d) Cystic vein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cystic vein drains the blood from the gall bladder and usually ends in the right branch of the portal vein. "
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "How many hepatic veins are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 3 main hepatic veins which drain the hepatic parenchyma into inferior venacava. They have named the right hepatic vein middle hepatic vein and left hepatic vein,"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Pulmonary vein carries ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygenated blood",
            "b) Deoxygenated blood",
            "c) Mixed Blood",
            "d) Blood with urea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: While veins usually carry deoxygenated blood from tissues to heart in case of pulmonary vein it carries oxygenated blood. Oxygenated blood is carried from the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Pulmonary vein carries blood to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right atrium",
            "b) Left atrium",
            "c) Aorta",
            "d) Lungs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pulmonary vein carries blood from lungs to heart. It drains into the left atrium. "
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What are the structures that keep blood flowing in unidirectional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bronchiole",
            "b) Neuron",
            "c) Septum",
            "d) Valves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Valve normally allows blood to flow in only one direction. There are 4 valves in the human heart. A heart valve opens or closes on differential blood pressure on each side."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "_______ circulation takes blood from heart to lungs and back.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Systemic",
            "b) Body",
            "c) Pulmonary",
            "d) Blood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pulmonary circulation is the process in which deoxygenated blood flows from the right ventricle to the lungs and returns oxygenated blood to the left atrium and ventricle of the heart. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "____________ returns blood from head, neck, thorax and upper limbs to right atrium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superior vena cava",
            "b) Inferior vena cava",
            "c) Pulmonary vein",
            "d) Pulmonary artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Superior vena cava return deoxygenated blood from systemic circulation to the right atrium of the heart. It has a diameter of about 24mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Major superficial veins that empty into axillary veins drain superficial upper limb structure is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vena cava",
            "b) Splenic vein",
            "c) Femoral vein",
            "d) Cephalic vein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cephalic vein is a superficial vein in the arm. It is also known as the antecubital vein."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Systemic venous system refers to the vein that drains into ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right ventricle",
            "b) Right atrium",
            "c) Left atrium",
            "d) Left ventricle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Vena cava is the largest vein. Vena cava can be classified into superior vena cava and inferior vena cava."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Compared to artery, veins ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Have thinner walls",
            "b) Hold their shape better when cut",
            "c) Have pleated endothelium",
            "d) Have smooth muscle in tunica media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Systemic venous system refers to the vein that drains into Right atrium without passing through two vascular beds."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "__________ circulation takes place from the heart to rest of the body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Systemic",
            "b) Full body",
            "c) Pulmonary",
            "d) Heart to lung"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  As blood flowing through vein doesn’t have much pressure as in that of artery their walls are thinner as compared to the artery walls."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "What is the structural and functional unit of the nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuron",
            "b) Dendron",
            "c) Axon",
            "d) Brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neuron is the nerve cell with all its branches. It is the structural and functional unit of the nervous system and is the longest sized (100cm) body cell of human. "
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Nerve cell does not divide because they do not have ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) Centrosome",
            "c) Golgi body",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Centrosome is responsible for cell division. Since it is absent in nerve cell they lack the ability to divide. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Node of Ranvier is found in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Muscle bundles",
            "b) Dendrites",
            "c) Right auricles",
            "d) Axon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Node of Ranvier is found in axons. Node of Ranvier is the microscopic gap between the glial cells if myelin sheath. "
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "How many types of neurons are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three types of neurons are present. They are sensory neurons, association neurons and motor neurons. "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Neurotransmission through a synapse is always from _________ to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axon, Dendron",
            "b) Dendron, Axon",
            "c) Brain, spinal cord",
            "d) Spinal cord, brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neurotransmission is the process by which signaling molecules are released by axon terminal. It is also called synaptic transmission. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Reflex action is controlled by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spinal cord",
            "b) ANS",
            "c) PNS",
            "d) Sympathetic nervous system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Reflex action is an involuntary and nearly instantaneous movement in response to the stimulus. A reflex is made possible by a neural pathway called reflex arc.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Connection between axon and dendrite is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synapsis",
            "b) Synapse",
            "c) Desmosome",
            "d) Tight junction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Synapse is a structure that permits a neuron to pass an electrical or chemical signal to another neuron. Synapse is essential for neuronal function."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "From where does the formation of a neural tube take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ectoderm",
            "b) Endoderm",
            "c) Mesoderm",
            "d) Spinal cord"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neuralation is a formation of neural tube from ectoderm of embryo. It follows gastrulation in all vertebrates."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "The anterior end of neural tube becomes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spinal cord",
            "b) Brain",
            "c) Axon",
            "d) Backbone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The anterior end of the neural tube becomes brain. The posterior end of the neural tube becomes spinal cord."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which is not true of glial cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuron support cells",
            "b) Retain ability to divide in adults",
            "c) Are not able to divide in adults",
            "d) Develop from glioblasts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neuronal migration is the method by which neurons travel from their origin or birth place to their final position in the brain. There are several ways like radial migration, axophilic migration, tangential migration etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "How many laminae are present in the grey matter of spinal cord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glial cells are also called neuroglial cells. Glial cells surround neurons and provide support and insulation between them."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The brain and spinal cord together make up ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CNS",
            "b) ANS",
            "c) PNS",
            "d) Reflux actions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Central nervous system consists of the brain and spinal cord. It integrates information it receives from and coordinates and influences the activity of all parts of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "_______ is protected by bony vertebrate, adipose tissue, and spinal meninges and cerebrospinal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spinal reflexes",
            "b) Central canal",
            "c) Spinal cord",
            "d) Epidural space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Spinal cord is a long thin tubular bundle of nervous tissue and support cells that extends from medulla oblongata in the brain. It is made up of 31 segments."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "________ layer of meninges that is thin and contains many blood vessels and nerves.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ependymal",
            "b) Dura mater",
            "c) Monosynaptic",
            "d) Pia mater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pia mater is the innermost layer of meninges and attaches directly to the brain and spinal cord. It is a delicate layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "________ connects right and left sides of the spinal cord.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cerebrospinal fluid barrier",
            "b) Spinal nerves",
            "c) Gray commissure",
            "d) Subarachnoid space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gray commissure is a thin strip of grey matter that surrounds the central canal of the spinal cord along with the anterior white commissure, connects the two halves of the cord."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Membranes that lie between bone and soft tissue ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ascending",
            "b) Descending",
            "c) Reflexes",
            "d) Meninges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Meninges are three layers are protective tissue that surrounds the neuraxis.  The three layers are dura mater, arachnoid mater and pia mater."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which part of the human brain has a center for controlling breathing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cerebrum",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Diencephalon",
            "d) Medulla oblongata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Medulla oblongata is cone-shaped neuronal mass responsible for autonomic functions. This part of brain is centre for respiration and circulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain controls intellectual ability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frontal lobe",
            "b) Parietal lobe",
            "c) Temporal lobe",
            "d) Occipital lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frontal lobe controls important cognitive skills such as emotional expression, problem solving, memory, language etc. it is the most common place for brain injury to occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain is concerned with the muscular movement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cerebellum",
            "b) Thalamus",
            "c) Temporal lobe of cerebrum",
            "d) Occipital lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cerebellum is located behind the top part of the brain stem. it is made of two hemispheres. It coordinates and regulates muscular activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "In human brain corpus callosum connects ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two optic lobes",
            "b) Bone and muscle",
            "c) Two cerebral hemisphere",
            "d) Two lobes of pituitary gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Corpus callosum is a part of the mind that allows communication between two hemispheres of the brain. It is responsible for transmitting neural messages between both right and left hemisphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Broca’s area of speech is present in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two optic lobes",
            "b) Frontal lobe",
            "c) Parietal lobe",
            "d) Temporal lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Broca’s area is important for putting words together to form complete sentences. It is present in Frontal lobe."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which nerve arises from the olfactory epithelium and functions solely by carrying different impulses for the sense of smell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) II optic",
            "b) IX glossopharyngeal",
            "c) IV trochlear",
            "d) I olfactory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Olfactory nerves the first cranial nerve. It conveys sensory information related to smell. It is the shortest cranial nerve."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "How many Cranial nerves are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 12 pairs of the nerve that can be seen on ventral surface of the brain. They are given roman numerals."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Which nerve is primarily a motor nerve that directs the eyeballs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trigeminal V",
            "b) Vestibulocochlear VIII",
            "c) Trochlear IV",
            "d) I olfactory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trochlear IV is the 4th cranial nerve. It emerges dorsally from the brain. It helps to direct the eyeballs."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following nerve innervates the muscles of facial expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VII Facial",
            "b) II Optic",
            "c) Vestibulocochlear VIII",
            "d) Trigeminal V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Facial nerve is the 7th cranial nerve. It emerges from brainstem between pons and medulla. It controls muscles of facial expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "How many pairs of the spinal nerve are found in human?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 13",
            "c) 31",
            "d) 33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spinal nerve arises from spinal cord. In humans, there are 31 pairs. They are 8cervical, 12 thoracis, 5 lumbar, 5 sacral, and 1 coccygeal. Each pair connects spinal cord with specific region of the body. "
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The spinal formula in man is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) C8 th12 L5 S5 Co1",
            "b) C7 th11 L5 S5 Co1",
            "c) C8 th12 L5 S4 Co2",
            "d) C8 th12 L5 S2 Co4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spinal nerve is divided into five groups. Cervical 8 pairs, thoracic 12pairs, Lumbar 5pairs, sacral 5pairs, coccygeal 1 pair. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Spinal nerve arises from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dorsal and ventral",
            "b) Anterior and ventral",
            "c) Ventral and posterior",
            "d) Posterior and dorsal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each spinal nerve arises from spinal cord by two roots. They are dorsal root and ventral root. Two roots join within the neural canal of vertebral column. "
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Post ganglionic nerve fibers of sympathetic nerve system are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Adrenergic",
            "b) Cholinergic",
            "c) Trigeminal",
            "d) Astrocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two roots the Dorsal and ventral join within the neural canal of vertebral column. So all spinal nerves are mixed in nature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "________ response sympathetic nervous system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rest and restore",
            "b) Fight or flight",
            "c) Decrease respiratory rate",
            "d) Increase respiratory rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Post ganglionic nerve fibers are long sized axons of neurons of chain ganglia. They have widespread effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Sympathetic nervous system is formed of ___________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sympathetic nervous system nerves emerge from thoracic and lumbar vertebral regions. Sympathetic nervous system “fight or flight” response."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The receptor absent in tongue is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermo receptors",
            "b) Gustato receptors",
            "c) Photo receptors",
            "d) Cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Photo receptors are sensitive to light. It is not seen in tongue. It is present in eyes."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which taste bud is present on the lateral sides of the tongue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salty",
            "b) Sweet",
            "c) Bitter",
            "d) Sour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  A man can perceive four basic modalities of taste i.e. sweet sour salty and bitter. Other tastes like pepper chocolate etc are experienced by a combination of two or more fundamental tastes."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "How many types of lingual papillae are found lingual papillae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 3 types of lingual papillae found on the tongue. They are circumvallate papillae, Funfiform papillae and filliform papillae."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which membrane connects tongue to the bottom of the mouth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frenulum",
            "b) Septum",
            "c) Lingual wall",
            "d) Barrier reff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frenulum is a small fold of mucous membrane extending from floor of the mouth to midline of the underside of the tongue."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Which receptor is present in the nose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photo receptors",
            "b) Telo receptors",
            "c) Olfacto receptors",
            "d) Phono receptors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Olfacto receptors are present in the nose. It is narrow and spindle shaped. Life span is about 2months and is replaced by basal cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What are the two holes on the nose called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Septum",
            "b) Blow holes",
            "c) Cartilage",
            "d) Nostrils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nostril is one of the two holes in the nose through which we breathe smell and sneeze."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Bowman’s glands are found in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Olfactory epithelium",
            "b) External auditory canal",
            "c) Cortical nephron",
            "d) Juxtamedullary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bowman’s glands are olfactory glands situated in the olfactory mucosa beneath the olfactory epithelium. It consists of an acinus in the lamina propria and secretory duct going out through the olfactory epithelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is behind the nose and connects with the back of the throat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bone",
            "b) Nasal cavity",
            "c) Nasal passage",
            "d) Hard palate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nasal cavity is a large air filled space above and behind the nose in the middle of the face. It filters air entering body before it reaches the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Made out of a thin piece of bone this wall separates nasal passages ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nostrils",
            "b) Cartilage",
            "c) Bridge",
            "d) Septum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The nasal septum is composed of five structures. It separates left and right airways in the nose."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Rods and cons are modified _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multipolar neurons",
            "b) Unipolar neurons",
            "c) Bipolar neurons",
            "d) Cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bipolar neurons are a type of neuron which has two extensions. They are specialized sensory neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Protein found in eye lens is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crystalline",
            "b) Opsin",
            "c) Collagen",
            "d) Rhodopsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rhodopsin is a biological pigment found in rods of the retina. It is a G-protein coupled receptor. It is extremely sensitive to light."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "What helps to see color?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rods",
            "b) Cons",
            "c) Lens",
            "d) Retina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rods and cones are two types of photoreceptors in human retina. Rods are responsible for vision at low light levels and cones helps to see color."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Fovea in the eye is a central depression in the yellowish pigment area called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macula lutea",
            "b) Cornea",
            "c) Retina",
            "d) Blind spot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Macula lutea is small yellowish area of retina. It provides central vision."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which part is a colorful part of the eye?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pupil",
            "b) Iris",
            "c) Eyeballs",
            "d) Cornea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iris is a thin circular structure of the eye. It is responsible for controlling the diameter and size of the pupil."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Aqueous humour and vitreous humor are divided by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lens",
            "b) Iris",
            "c) Retina",
            "d) Optic nerve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lens is a transparent biconvex structure in the eye. It helps to refract light to be focused on the retina. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Internal ear is filled with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perilymph",
            "b) Endolymph",
            "c) Lymph",
            "d) Mesolymph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Endolymph is the fluid contained in the membranous labyrinth of the inner ear. It is also called as Scarpa’s fluid. "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Eustachian tube is present between _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Middle ear and larynx",
            "b) Outer ear and pharynx",
            "c) Middle ear and pharynx",
            "d) Inner ear and larynx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Eustachian tube is also known as auditory tube. It is approx 35mm long and 3mm in diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Sequence of ear ossicles from outside to inside is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Malleus incus stapes",
            "b) Incus stapes Malleus",
            "c) Stapes incus malleus",
            "d) Malleus stapes incus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ear ossicles are three bones in middle ear. They are the smallest bones in humans. The term ossicle means tiny bones."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of the following is balancing organ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organ of corti",
            "b) Cochlea",
            "c) Vestibular region",
            "d) Eardrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vestibule is the central art of inner ear and is situated medial to eardrum behind cochlea. It contains organ of hearing (cochlea) and organ of balance (labyrinth)."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What separates the outer ear from the middle ear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auricle",
            "b) Ear wall",
            "c) Cochlea",
            "d) Ear drum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Eardrum is a thin cone-shaped membrane. It separates the external ear from the middle ear. It is also called a tympanic membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which part of the ear takes sound waves and turns them into vibrations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Middle war",
            "b) Ear wall",
            "c) Ear canal",
            "d) Inner ear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Middle war contains 3 bones. These 3 bones form a connection from the eardrum to the inner ear. As sound waves hit the eardrum, the eardrum moves back and forth causing the ossicles to move."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "During inspiration the diaphragm ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflexes to become dome shaped",
            "b) Contracts and flattens",
            "c) Expands",
            "d) Shows no change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Drawing of breath is called as inhalation. It is also known as inspiration. During this process the air is drawn inside the lungs and the diaphragm contracts and flattens."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Lungs are covered by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pleural membrane",
            "b) Peritoneum",
            "c) Pericardium",
            "d) Muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pleural membrane is the thin, moist and has two layers. Between two layers is the intrapleural space, which contains fluid secreted by the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Total number of alveoli in both the lungs is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3000",
            "b) 30000",
            "c) 500000000",
            "d) 700000000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Alveoli are tiny sacs within the lungs. It allows carbon dioxide and oxygen t move between lungs and bloodstream."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Lungs have large number of narrow tubes called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alveoli",
            "b) Bronchioles",
            "c) Bronchi",
            "d) Trachea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bronchioles are the smallest airways within the lungs. They are not encircled by any cartilage."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Alveoli of lungs are lines by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squamous epithelium",
            "b) Simple epithelium",
            "c) Cuboidal epithelium",
            "d) Columnar epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Squamous epithelium is a single layer of flat cells in contact with the basal lamina. It helps in easy movement of gas in the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "How many unpaired cartilage are present in larynx?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: There are 3 unpaired cartilages present in the larynx. They are cricoids, thyroid and epiglottis."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "The superior horn of thyroid cartilage is connected to which bone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertebra",
            "b) Ribs",
            "c) Hyoid",
            "d) Epiglottis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The posterior border of each lamina is prolonged upward and downward to form 2 projections, the superior horn and the inferior horn.  The superior horns point upwards and backwards, the inferior horn points downwards."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Larynx is found at what vertebral level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CV3-CV6",
            "b) CV6-CV3",
            "c) CV2-CV5",
            "d) CV5-CV2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hyoid bone is horse shoe shaped bone situated in anterior midline of the neck. It lies at base of the mandible."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Where does the arterial blood come from those supplies to visceral pleura?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bronchial veins",
            "b) Intercostal nerves",
            "c) Bronchial arteries",
            "d) The costodiaphragmatic recesses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bronchial arteries supply lungs with nutrition and oxygenated blood. There are usually two bronchial arteries that run to the left lung and one to right lung."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "What is the dry form of inflammation without a significant collection of fluid in the pleural cavity called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intercostal nerves",
            "b) Pleura",
            "c) Pleurisy",
            "d) Pneumothorax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pleurisy is also called as pleuritis. It is the inflammation of membranes that surround lungs and lines the chest cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "What are the innervations to the costal and peripheral parts of the diaphragmatic pleura?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydropneumothorax",
            "b) Intercostal nerves",
            "c) Bronchial arteries",
            "d) Empyema thoracis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Intercostal nerves arise from somatic nervous system. This enables them to control the contraction of muscles as well as provide specific sensory information regarding the skin and parietal pleura."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What does the pulmonary ligament contain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The inner surface of the thoracic wall",
            "b) Interpleural space/ Pleural cavity",
            "c) A thin layer of areolar tissue with a few lymphatics",
            "d) The pulmonary veins to expand during the increased venous return, such as during exercise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pulmonary ligament serves to hold the lower part of lungs in position. It contains a thin layer of areolar tissue with a few lymphatics."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "What part of the parietal pleura covers the superior surface of the diaphragm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mediastinal pleura",
            "b) Diaphragmatic pleura",
            "c) Intercostal nerves",
            "d) Pneumothorax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diaphragmatic pleura is a layer of parietal peritoneum overlaying the thoracic surface of the diaphragm and the lung. "
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The respiratory system is made up of trachea, the lungs and the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diaphragm",
            "b) Pancreas",
            "c) Esophagus",
            "d) Liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diaphragm is a dome shaped sheet of muscles and tendon that serves as the main muscles of respiration and plays vital role in breathing process. It separates the thorax, or chest from the abdomen."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "___________ delivers deoxygenated blood to the lungs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulmonary vein",
            "b) Aorta",
            "c) Left ventricle",
            "d) Pulmonary artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two are not of the same size. The left lung is approximately 10%smaller than right one. This is due to the position of the heart."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "The inner layer that surrounds the lung itself is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parietal Pleura",
            "b) Lobar bronchi",
            "c) Pleuracardium",
            "d) Visceral Pleura"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pulmonary artery carries deoxygenated blood from right ventricle to the lungs. The blood passes through capillaries adjacent to alveoli and becomes oxygenated as a part of respiration process."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Gas exchange in lungs occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alveolar sacs",
            "b) Segmental Bronchi",
            "c) Bronchioles",
            "d) Alveolar sinus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Visceral Pleura is a delicate membrane that covers the surface of each lung and dips into fissures between the lobes. It also separates the pleural cavity from the mediastinum."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "How many secondary bronchi are there in the right lung?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Alveoli are tiny sacs in our lungs. It allows oxygen and carbon dioxide to move between the lungs and bloodstream. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which of the following supports epiglottis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cricoid cartilage",
            "b) Thyroid",
            "c) Ribs",
            "d) Lungs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 3 secondary bronchi in right lung. It delivers oxygen to three lobes of the right lung. The lobes are superior middle and inferior lobe."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Point where bronchial enters lung is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manus briosternal",
            "b) Hilus",
            "c) Bronchi",
            "d) Carina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cricoid cartilage is located slightly below the thyroid cartilage. This cartilage consists of strong connective tissue consisting the dorsal part of larynx."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Place where trachea bifurcates into right and left bronchus is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trachea",
            "b) Bronchi",
            "c) Hilus",
            "d) Carina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is also known as hilum.  They consist of major bronchi and pulmonary arteries and veins. It is found in medial aspect of each lung."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "How many types of teeth are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Permanent teeth of man are 4 types. They are incisors, canines premolars and molars."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which structure closes the internal nares during swallowing of food bolus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uvula",
            "b) Tongue",
            "c) Palate",
            "d) Larynx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During solling the soft palate and the uvula moves up close off the nasopharynx preventing food from entering nasal cavity. When this process fails it results in nasal regurgitation."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Crown of teeth is covered by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dentine",
            "b) Enamel",
            "c) Pinocytic",
            "d) Muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Enamel is the hardest and most highly mineralized substance of the body. It covers the outer layer of each tooth. Enamel is made up of minerals primarily hydroxyapatite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The dental formula of man is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) i 2/2 c 1/1 pm 2/2 m 3/3",
            "b) i 1/2 c 2/1 pm 2/2 m 3/3",
            "c) i 1/1 c 1/2 pm 1/2 m 4/4",
            "d) i 2/2 c 1/1 pm 3/2 m 2/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dental formula indicates 2 incisors 1 canine 2 premolars and 3 molars on one side of upper mouth. "
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "ph of saliva is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 6.8",
            "c) 7.5",
            "d) 9.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ph of saliva is slightly alkaline range. The ph of saliva is around 6.8 to 7.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Salivary amylase is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastrin",
            "b) Glyoxylase",
            "c) Pepsin",
            "d) Ptyalin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: Digestion of carbohydrates begins from the mouth itself. It breaks starch into maltose and dextrin."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The esophagus connects _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mouth to throat",
            "b) Throat to stomach",
            "c) Mouth to stomach",
            "d) Stomach to large intestine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: The esophagus is a muscular tube connecting the throat with a stomach. It is about 8 inches long."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "The esophagus is also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Food pipe",
            "b) Wind pipe",
            "c) Stomach",
            "d) Voice box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is also known as gullet. It is an organ through which food passes. It is aided by peristaltic contractions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The esophagus is ____________ to the trachea.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Posterior",
            "b) Anterior",
            "c) Lateral",
            "d) Dorsal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Esophagus is located posterior to trachea in neck and thoracic regions of the body and passes through the esophageal hiatus of diaphragm on its way to the stomach."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "An opening in the diaphragm called __________ hiatus allows the esophagus to pss through and connects to the stomach.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Esophageal",
            "b) Diaphragmatic",
            "c) Mediastinal",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Esophageal hiatus is an opening in the diaphragm through esophagus and the vagus nerve pass. It connects diaphragm to the spine."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "The stomach is formed of __________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stomach is formed of 3 parts. They are the cardiac stomach, phyloric antrum and fundic part."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Inner mucosa of the stomach is raised into large number of folds called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Villi",
            "b) Cilia",
            "c) Rugae",
            "d) Capillaries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inner mucosa of the stomach is raised into large number longitudinal of folds called as gastric rugae. These rugae dilate the stomach to store food and also increase the surface area of digestion."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Enzyme rennin used in digestion is secreted from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Intestine",
            "d) Mouth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Stomach is a muscular organ located on the left side of the upper abdomen. It receives food from e esophagus. Rennin is found in the stomach. It is an enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone helps in secretion of HCL from stomach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Renin",
            "b) Gastrin",
            "c) Secretin",
            "d) Pepsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gastrin is a hormone that is produced by g cells in the lining of the stomach and upper small intestine. Gastrin stimulates the stomach to release gastric acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Gastric juice has a ph of about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The ph of gastric juice is acidic. They range between 1.5 to 2.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "___________ sphincter prevents regurgitation of food from the stomach.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cardiac",
            "b) Sphincter of oddi",
            "c) Bimitral valve",
            "d) Villi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cardiac sphincter prevents acidic content of the stomach from moving upward into the food pipe. It is found at the lower end of the esophagus."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the longest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Esophagus",
            "c) Small intestine",
            "d) Large intestine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Small intestine is the longest part of the alimentary canal. It is about 20ft or 6metres long. It is narrow and tubular part occupying the central and lower parts of abdominal cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Small intestine is divided into __________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Small intestine is divided into 3 parts. They are duodenum, jejunum and ileum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The opening of Ileum is guarded by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ileo caecal valve",
            "b) Mitral valve",
            "c) Sphincter",
            "d) Villi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The opening of Ileum is guarded by Ileo caecal valve. It prevents regurgitation of food from caecum. Ileum is highly coiled."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Secretin and cholecystokinin are digestive hormones. These are secreted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Esophagus",
            "b) Stomach",
            "c) Ileum",
            "d) Duodenum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Duodenum is the widest shortest and most flexible part of small intestine. It forms a c shaped curve. It receives bile-pancreatic duct."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "“Crypts of Lieberkuhn” are found in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gall bladder",
            "b) Intestine",
            "c) Liver",
            "d) Kidney"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cells of Crypts of Lieberkuhn secret intestinal juice as they gradually migrate along the side of the crypt and the villus. The glands are named after German anatomist J.N Lieberkuhn."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The food that enters the intestine from stomach is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chyme",
            "b) Fundus",
            "c) Chyle",
            "d) Bolus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chyme is a semi fluid mass of partly digested food that is expelled from stomach through pyloric valve into duodenum."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "In which of the following putrefying bacteria are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colon",
            "b) Intestine",
            "c) Liver",
            "d) Kidney"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Colon is found in large intestine. It is a long sized sacculated structure which is differentiated into4 regions. They are ascending colon, transverse colon, descending colon and sigmoid colon."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which among the following is vestigial in function?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duodenum",
            "b) Vermiform appendix",
            "c) Peyer’s patch",
            "d) Plicae circulares"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vermiform appendix and Caecum are vestigial function. Since these are not involved in cellulose digestion."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "__________ stores the temporary faeces.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colon",
            "b) Caecum",
            "c) Rectum",
            "d) Kidney"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: Rectum is a slightly dilated part and concerned with the temporary storage of faeces. It leads into anal canal which opens out by the anus."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Large intestine is divided into _________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Large intestine is about 5feet long, shorter but it is wider. It forms an arc around small intestine. It is formed of 3 parts. They are caecum, colon and rectum."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "____________ is present in the posterior concavity of the diaphragm in the right upper part of the abdomen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreas",
            "b) Stomach",
            "c) Liver",
            "d) Kidneys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Liver is an exocrine gland of the body. It weighs about 1.5kgs. It is attached to diaphragm by suspensory ligament."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "How many lobes are present in the liver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liver is a multilobulated gland. It is formed of two main and two small lobes. Two main lobes are larger right and smaller left lobe. While two small lobes are quadrate and caudate lobe."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Glisson’s capsule is found in which organ of mammals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Kidney",
            "c) Testis",
            "d) Liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hepatic lobules are structural and functional units of the liver.  Each liver lobe is formed of hexagonal lobules surrounded by a connective tissue sheath called as Glisson’s capsule."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "In humans, sphincter of oddi is associated with the opening of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hepatopancreatic ampulla",
            "b) Pyloric stomach",
            "c) Esophagus",
            "d) Common hepatic duct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The opening of Hepatopancreatic ampulla in the duodenum is guarded by a sphincter of oddi. Daily secretion of bile is about 600-1200ml."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Cholecystokinin stimulates ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreas",
            "b) Gall bladder",
            "c) Secrete bile",
            "d) Kidneys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:   Present on lower surface of right liver lobe, there is a thin walled pear shaped sac called gall bladder. It concentrates and stores the bile secreted by liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Pancreas is a _________ gland.",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Heterocrine",
            "b) Endocrine",
            "c) Exocrine",
            "d) Hormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pancreas is a Heterocrine gland. Its exocrine part is formed of a large number of lobules or acini."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Where is Pancreas located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Below stomach",
            "b) In-between stomach and liver",
            "c) Behind the stomach",
            "d) Above the stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pancreas are about 6 inches long. It is a 2nd largest gland. It is dived into the head body and tail. It sits in the abdomen behind the stomach and in front of the sine."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Which cells in the pancreas make insulin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Germ cells",
            "b) Islet cells",
            "c) Epithelial cells",
            "d) Hepatic cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Islets are tiny clusters of cells in the pancreas. These make insulin which controls blood sugar levels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "What does pancreas make?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzymes",
            "b) Carbohydrates",
            "c) Fats",
            "d) Muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Enzymes are proteins that boost the rate of reaction. Enzymes in pancreas combine with bile to break down the food."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Average PH of urine is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is possible to live without a pancreas. Pancreas secretes insulin. By depending on insulin shots it’s possible to live. It’s hard to mange as pancreas makes other hormones that control blood sugar."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Henle’s loop is found in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liver",
            "b) Kidney",
            "c) Pancreas",
            "d) Stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Urine consists of urea. The ph is slightly acidic."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which among the following is structural and functional unit of a kidney?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nephron",
            "b) Neuron",
            "c) Urethra",
            "d) Henle’s loop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Henle’s loop is a long U-shaped tube that conducts urine within each nephron. Its function is to recover water and sodium chloride from urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The liquid which collects in Bowman’s capsule is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentrated urine",
            "b) Blood plasma minus proteins",
            "c) Glycogen and water",
            "d) Urea, glycogen and water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nephron is a structural and functional unit of kidney. Its chief function is to regulate the concentration of water and soluble substances like sodium salts by filtering blood, reabsorbing what is needed and excreting the rest as urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "In which of the following region f nephron does maximum reabsorption of useful materials occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loop of Henle",
            "b) Glomerulus",
            "c) DCT",
            "d) PCT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bowman’s capsule is a cuplike sack at the beginning of the tubular component of a nephron, it performs the first step in the filtration."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "__________ is located at the junction with the bladder made of smooth involuntary muscle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urethra",
            "b) Internal Urethral sphincters",
            "c) External Urethral Sphincters",
            "d) Bladder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Internal Urethral sphincters are a muscle which constricts the internal urethral orifice. It is made of smooth muscle so it is involuntary. "
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Just posterior to the symphysis pubis; hollow, collapsible sac empty=deflated balloon; full=pear shape. Name this part.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bladder",
            "b) Urters",
            "c) External Urethral Sphincters",
            "d) Urethra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  It is External Urethral Sphincters. External Urethral Sphincters surrounds whole length of the membranous portion of the urethra. It is enclosed in urogenital diaphragm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "How many ureters are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Urine is made in kidneys and flows from them to the bladder. From the bladder, urine flows through the urethra to the outside of the body. "
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The bladder is lined with _________ epithelium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple columnar",
            "b) Transitional",
            "c) Stratified squamous",
            "d) Simple cuboidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 2 ureters present. One from each kidney. The upper half is located in the abdomen and lower half is located in pelvic area. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Urine that has glucose in it usually an indicator of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diabetes",
            "b) Bacterial infection",
            "c) Kidney stones",
            "d) Muscle atropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike mucosa of other hollow organs, urinary bladder is lined with transitional epithelium, it is able to stretch significantly to accommodate large volume of urine, it also provides protection to underlying tissues from acidic or alkaline urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "The trigone is an area located within the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urethra",
            "b) Urinary bladder",
            "c) Renal Pelvis area",
            "d) Kidneys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diabetes is a disease in which blood glucose level is very high. Insulin is a hormone that helps glucose to get into the cells and give them energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Urinary bladder is divided into ________ regions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trigone is a smooth triangular region of an internal urinary bladder formed by two ureteric orifices and internal urethral orifice, the area is very sensitive to expansion and once stretched to a certain degree the urinary bladder signals brain of its need to empty."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Anatomically male urethra can be divided into _________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In males, the urethra travels the length of the penis and serves a dual purpose. It is a conduit for both urine and semen ejaculation."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Male urethra is lined with _______ epithelium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stratified columnar",
            "b) Simple squamous",
            "c) Stratified squamous",
            "d) Simple columnar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anatomically male urethra can be divided into four parts. They are pre prostatic, prostatic, membranous and spongy."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Male urethra is approximately _______ long.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30cm-35cm",
            "b) 15cm-20cm",
            "c) 10cm-15cm",
            "d) 5cm-10cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Male urethra is lined with Stratified columnar epithelium.  It is protected from the corrosive urine by mucus secreting glands."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "In female the urethra is _______ long.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4cm",
            "b) 2cm",
            "c) 6cm",
            "d) 10cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The male urethra is approximately 15cm to 20cm long. The anatomical course of urethra is different in males and females."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The female urethra develops from _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ectoderm",
            "b) Endoderm",
            "c) Mesoderm",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Female urethra is comparatively shorter than male urethra. It is approximately 4cm long. This predisposes women to urinary tract infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The female urethra is lined with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stratified squamous epithelium",
            "b) Simple columnar epithelium",
            "c) Squamous epithelium",
            "d) Simple epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The female urethra develops from Endoderm and the surrounding splanchnic mesoderm of urogenital sinus. The female urethra develops by the 12th gestational week."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "If for some reason, the vasa efferentia in the human reproductive system gets blocked, the gametes will not be transported from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Testes to epididymis",
            "b) Epididymis to vas deferens",
            "c) Ovary to uterus",
            "d) Vagina to uterus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Epididymis is a narrow tightly coiled tube connecting the rear of the testis to the deferent duct. It stores sperms for maturation."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Vasa efferentia are the ductules leading from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rete testis to vas deferens",
            "b) Epididymis to urethra",
            "c) Vas deferens to epididymis",
            "d) Placenta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rete testis is an anatomizing network of delicate tubules located in the hilum of the testicle that carries sperm from somniferous tubules to the efferent ducts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Spermatogenesis is promoted by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estrogen",
            "b) Progesterone",
            "c) Testosterone",
            "d) Oxytocin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Testosterone is the primary make sex hormone and an anabolic steroid. In male it lays a key role in development of male reproductive tissues. It also promotes secondary sexual character."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The ductus deferens is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urethrea",
            "b) Penis",
            "c) Testis",
            "d) Vas deferens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is a part of the male reproductive system. Vas deferens transport sperm from the epididymis to the ejaculatory ducts for the ejaculation."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "In most mammals testes are located in scrotal sacs for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Sex differentiation",
            "b) Sperm development in cooler condition",
            "c) Independent functioning of kidney",
            "d) More space to visceral organs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Testes are located outside the body because the sperm develop best at temperature several degree cooler than normal internal body temperature. They are located behind the penis in a pouch of skin called scrotum."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "The head of epididymis at the head of testis is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cauda epididymis",
            "b) Vas deferens",
            "c) Caput epididymis",
            "d) Gubernaculum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The head of epididymis receives spermatozoa via efferent ducts of mediastinum of the testis. It is characterized historically by a thin myoepithelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Testes are protected in scrotum because they _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Produce heat",
            "b) Produce sperms",
            "c) Help in micturition",
            "d) Control homeostasis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sperm is the male reproductive cell. It has a limited life span. Human sperm cell is haploid."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Tunica alburginea is the covering of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Testes",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Spleen",
            "d) Lungs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tunica alburginea is a fibrous envelope. It consists of 5% elastin that is made up of amino acids glycine, valine, alanine and proline."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": " Nutritive cells found in seminiferous tubules are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sertoli cells",
            "b) Leydig cells",
            "c) Chromaffin cells",
            "d) Spermatogonical cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sertoli cells are somaticcells of testis that are essential for testis formation and spermatogenesis.  It is also called a nurse cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Cauda epididymis leads to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Rete testis",
            "b) Vas deferens",
            "c) Vas efferens",
            "d) Ejaculatory duct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The epididymis consists of three parts head, body and tail. Spermatozoa formed in testis enter caput epididymis progress to corpus and finally reach cauda region where they are stored."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "How many pairs of seminal vesicles are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One pair of seminal vesicles is present. They are elongated muscular and sacculated glands present in the pelvis between bladder and rectum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Sperm is nourished by a sugary fluid from the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cowper’s gland",
            "b) Prostate gland",
            "c) Seminal vesicle",
            "d) Vas deferens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Seminal vesicle is a pair of simple tubular glands posteroinferior to the urinary bladder of some male mammals. It is located within the semen. They secrete a fluid that partly composes the semen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Seminal vesicle produce ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sperm cells",
            "b) Testosterone",
            "c) Fructose rich fluid",
            "d) Estrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The seminal vesicle secretes a significant proportion of the fluid that ultimately becomes semen. It is very rich in fructose content. "
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The function of fructose in semen is to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Provide an energy source for ATP production by sperm",
            "b) Promote coagulation of semen in the female reproductive tract",
            "c) Buffer acids in female reproductive tract",
            "d) Inhibit the growth of bacterial in semen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Semen contains up to 11mmol/L of free fructose. It is the major energy source for the sperm cells in their ace for ovum. Hence the sperm contains fructose as the primary energy source and not glucose. "
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "The seminal vesicles are located at ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inferior to the prostate within urogenital tract",
            "b) In kidneys",
            "c) Within spermatic cord",
            "d) Posterior and inferior to the urinary bladder in front of rectum"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation:  It is a part of male reproductive system. It helps in making of sperms. "
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "______ adds fluid to sperm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seminal vesicle",
            "b) Prostate gland",
            "c) Bulbourethral gland",
            "d) Ejaculatory duct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ejaculatory duct is about 2cm in length and is created with the duct of the seminal vesicle merges with vas deferens. They transport spermatozoa and fluids."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following structures makes up the most of the male urethral length?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Membranous urethra",
            "b) Prostatic urethra",
            "c) Ejaculatory duct",
            "d) Spongy urethra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spongy urethra is the longest part of male urethra, and is contained in a penis. It is about 15cm long. "
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The sperms acrosome ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Contains nutrients",
            "b) Contains enzymes",
            "c) Provide blood-testis barrier",
            "d) Beats so that sperm can swim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sperm’s acrosome contains digestive enzymes. These enzymes break down the outer membrane of the ovum."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "In response to parasympathetic stimulation _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spermiogenesis is encouraged",
            "b) Ejaculation occurs",
            "c) Blood flow increases to the penis",
            "d) Vessels in the penis constrict."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Omega 3 fatty acids increase blood flow. Brain sends nerve impulses that increase blood flow to the penis."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Choose the correct order for the path of sperm from testes to outside the body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ductus deferens- Epididymis- Ejaculatory duct- Penis",
            "b) Epididymis- Ductus deferens- Ejaculatory duct- Penis",
            "c) Ejaculatory duct-Ductus deferens-Epididymis -Penis",
            "d) Penis- Ductus deferens –Epididymis- Ejaculatory duct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sperm travels from epididymis to penis. Penis is external male organ and serves as urinal duct."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "During sexual arousal ________ impulses cause vasodilation of the arterioles of the penis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parasympathetic",
            "b) Sympathetic",
            "c) Somatic",
            "d) Brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Penile erection is the result of a complex interaction of physiological neural and vascular factor. Physiological erection is triggered by parasympathetic impulses, the arteries dilate and blood flow increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which male structure is homologous to the female clitoris?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scrotum",
            "b) Penis",
            "c) Pubis",
            "d) Testis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Penis is the male sex organ. It also acts as urinal duct."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "All except which of the following about vasectomy is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a highly effective birth control method",
            "b) The part of ductus deferens is cut",
            "c) It is 10% recoverable",
            "d) It is a minor surgery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vasectomy is the surgical process for male sterilization. The male vas deferens are severed and then tied or sealed to prevent sperm from entering into urethra and prevent fertilization."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "The urethra passes through the _______________ of the penis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corpora cavernosa",
            "b) Corpora spongiosum",
            "c) Tunica alburginea",
            "d) Prepuce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Corpora spongiosum is the mass of spongy tissue surrounding the male urethra within penis. Also called as corpus cavernous urethrae."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "The main function of prostate is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spermatogenesis",
            "b) Maturation of sperm cells",
            "c) Secretion of alkaline muscus",
            "d) Production of glycogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Prostate gland main function is to secrete prostate fluid. It surrounds urethra just beneath the bladder."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Testosterone is converted to ___________ in the prostate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dihydrotestosterone",
            "b) Cholestrol",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Progesterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dihydrotestosterone is also known as stanolone. It is an endogenous androgen sex steroid and hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following is unpaired gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulbourethral glands",
            "b) Prostate gland",
            "c) Seminal vesicle",
            "d) Testis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bulbourethral glands produce some amount of PSA (prostate-specific antigen). The increased quantity of which is an indicator of prostatic cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Bulbourethral gland is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cowper’s gland",
            "b) Prostate gland",
            "c) Seminal vesicles",
            "d) Bartholin’s gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a walnut sized gland. It is unpaired. It secrets fluid that nourishes and protects sperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Bulbourethral gland is a _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endocrine gland",
            "b) Exocrine gland",
            "c) Hormone",
            "d) Heterocrine gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is a pea shaped gland located at posterolateral to the membranous urethra. They are in pair. It is named after English surgeon William Cowper."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Bulbourethral gland is homologous to _____________ present in female body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovary",
            "b) Mammary gland",
            "c) Bartholin’s gland",
            "d) Vagina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Exocrine glands are glands that produce and secrete substances onto an epithelial surface. It secrets hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The outside layer of the oocyte is the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zona pellucida",
            "b) Theca interna",
            "c) Theca externa",
            "d) Antrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zona pellucid is the glycoprotein layer surrounding plasma membrane of mammalian oocyte. It is a vital part of the oocyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The mature follicle is also called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary follicle",
            "b) Graafian follicle",
            "c) Granulosa cell",
            "d) Primary follicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Graafian follicle is present inside an ovary and is a minute cyst within an egg or ovum."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Name the primary sex organ of a female.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Testis",
            "b) Mammary glands",
            "c) Ovaries",
            "d) Fallopian tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ovaries are the part of the female reproductive tract. They produce eggs as well as hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Antrum is the cavity of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastrula",
            "b) Blastula",
            "c) Graafian follicle",
            "d) Ovary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Antrum is the cavity present in graafian follicle. It is filledwith follicular fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Capacitation of sperm occurs in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Female genital tract",
            "b) Vas deferentia",
            "c) Vagina",
            "d) Penis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Capacitation is the maturation of the spermatozoon. Glycoprotein coat and seminal proteins are removed from the surface of sperms acrosome. This takes place inside female reproductive tract."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "The Mullerion duct in the female amniotes develops into __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uterus",
            "b) Ureters",
            "c) Oviduct",
            "d) Vagina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mullerion duct are primordial anlage of female reproductive tract. They differentiate to form fallopian tube, uterus, cervix and vagina."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Polyspermy is prevented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fertilization cone",
            "b) Fertilization membrane",
            "c) Jelly coat",
            "d) Tertiary membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polyspermy is the condition in which an egg is fertilized by more than one sperm. This is not seen in humans. After the fusion of one sperm into the egg, the fertilization membrane is formed to prevent the entry of other sperms thus preventing polyspermy."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Fertilization of egg by sperm occurs in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oviduct",
            "b) Ovary",
            "c) Uterus",
            "d) Vagina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oviduct is also known as fallopian tube or uterine tube. The fertilization of the egg by sperm occurs in fallopian tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "If mammalian ovum fails to get fertilized which one of the following is unlikely?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corpus luteum will degenerate",
            "b) Estrogen secretion decreases",
            "c) Primary follicle starts developing",
            "d) Progesterone level declines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Progesterone is a naturally occurring steroid hormone. It is released by ovaries. It is necessary for implantation of fertilized egg. If fertilization fails to take place the Progesterone levels declines."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Fallopian tube is differentiated into ____________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fallopian tube is differentiated into 3 parts. They are ampulla, isthmus and uterine part."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Uterus is made up of ______ layers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Uterus is made up of 3 layers. 3 layers are endometrium (inner lining),Myometrium (middle layer) and perimetrium (outer layer)."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "_________ lies between external opening to vagina and internal opening to uterus.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral cervical ligaments",
            "b) Round ligaments",
            "c) Cervical canal",
            "d) Mesometrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It should me lateral cervical ligaments. It is the major ligament of uterus. It is located at the base of uterus. It provides support to uterus."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": " Where does implantation of the blastocyst occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fallopian tube",
            "b) Endometrium",
            "c) Ovary",
            "d) Cervix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cervical canal is sindle shaped flattened canal of the cervix. It is seen in neck of uterus. It is also called as canal of the cervix."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which hormones thicken the lining of the uterus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) Estrogen",
            "c) LH",
            "d) Progesterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Implantation is the attachment of fertilized egg to the wall of the uterus. It occurs about week after ovulation.  Implantation occurs in endometrium part of uterus."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The contraction of the myoepithelial breast cells is stimulated by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estrogen",
            "b) Progesterone",
            "c) Oxytocin",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Estrogen is the primary female sex hormone. It is responsible for development of female reproductive system and regulation of secondary sex characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Nipple has 15-25 openings called ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactiferous ducts",
            "b) Somniferous duct",
            "c) Milk duct",
            "d) Pores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Prolactin is luteotrophic hormone. It helps to produce milk after childbirth. It is important for female reproductive health."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of mammary gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are many plasma cells in the connective tissue surrounding epithelial units",
            "b) There is apocrine secretion of lipids in Brest milk",
            "c) Mammary gland is responsive for both hormones and steroids.",
            "d) There are striated ducts that are active in transport of ions and water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lactiferous ducts converge and form a branched system connecting nipple to the lobules of the mammary gland. Each breast has about 15-20 Lactiferous ducts."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "A non lactating mammary gland in adult female cannot produce ilk because of the lack of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lobules",
            "b) Lactiferous sinuses",
            "c) Intraovular ducts",
            "d) Alveoli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The base of the nipple is termed as areola. Milk comes out of nipple after child birth."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Grave’s disease is due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypoactivity of Islets of Langerhans",
            "b) Hyperactivity of adrenal cortex",
            "c) Hyperactivity of thyroid gland",
            "d) Hyperactivity of adrenal medulla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grave’s disease is an immune system disorder. It results in the overproduction of thyroid hormones. The thyroid gets enlarged."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Hypothyroidism in adult causes _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myxoedema",
            "b) Cretinism",
            "c) Diabetes",
            "d) Obesity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Myxoedema is loss of brain function as a result of severe low level of thyroid hormone in the blood. It is life threatening."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "An autoimmune disease where body’s own antibodies attack cells of thyroid is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hoshimoto’s disease",
            "b) Grave’s disease",
            "c) Turner’s syndrome",
            "d) Hyperthyroidism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is an autoimmune disorder. Immune system attacks the thyroid gland. Thyroid are damaged and can’t make enough hormone."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which type of epithelium is found in thyroid follicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squamous",
            "b) Cuboidal",
            "c) Transitional",
            "d) Columnar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thyroid follicles are reasonable for the production and secretion of thyroid hormone. They are made up of Cuboidal epithelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The hormone that controls the level of calcium and phosphorus in blood is secreted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thyroid gland",
            "b) Parathyroid gland",
            "c) Pituitary gland",
            "d) Thymus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Parathyroid gland is tiny glands. It controls the body’s calcium level.  Each gland is about the size of a grain of rice."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "What hormone does the parathyroid produce?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcitonin",
            "b) PTH",
            "c) PFH",
            "d) Insulin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PTH is known as parathyroid hormone. It is secreted by parathyroid gland. It is important in bone remodeling."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "How many parathyroid glands are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are four tiny parathyroid gland present. It weighs about 30mg and3-4 mm in diameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "What are the types of cells found in parathyroid gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha and beta cells",
            "b) Chiefcells and oxyphil",
            "c) Parafollicular and follicle cells",
            "d) Pituicytes and basophil cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxyphil cell is present. Along with that chief cells are also present. Oxyphilcellsappear at the onset of puberty."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Where are parathyroid glands present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Posterior surface of lateral lobes of thyroid",
            "b) Posterior to stomach",
            "c) On top of kidneys",
            "d) Upper chest under breastbone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Parathyroid glands are endocrine glands in the neck of humans. It is located on the back of the thyroid gland. They are four in numbers."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "The Thymus is located in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neck",
            "b) Along intestinal walls",
            "c) Along trachea",
            "d) In abdominal cavity above diaphragm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Thymus is located along the trachea behind the sternum. It is located between lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Thymus secrets ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymosin",
            "b) Macrophages",
            "c) Antibodies",
            "d) Lymph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thymus secrets Thymosin. It stimulates the development of disease fighting Tcells."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "T lymphocytes mature in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spleen",
            "b) Thymus",
            "c) Red bone marrow",
            "d) Thyroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After puberty thymus starts to slowly shrink.  It becomes replaced by fat."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Endocrine gland thought to be involved in setting the biological clock and influencing the reproductive function of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary gland",
            "b) Thymus gland",
            "c) Adrenal gland",
            "d) Pineal gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: T lymphocytes play a central role in cell mediated immunity, it has a receptor on the cell surface. T lymphocytes mature in Thymus."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Pineal gland of human brain secretes melatonin concerned with ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anger",
            "b) Body temperature",
            "c) Smell",
            "d) Coloration of the skin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pineal gland is the small endocrine gland. It secrets the hormone that affects the modulation of sleep/wake patterns and photoperiodic functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The pineal gland secrets _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melatonin",
            "b) Vasopressin",
            "c) MSH",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Melatonin is a hormone secreted by Pineal gland. It is also known as N-acetyl-5-methoxy tryptamine."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Where is Pineal gland located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Just below Adam’s apple",
            "b) Hanging down from hypothalamus",
            "c) Between the right and left hemisphere of the brain",
            "d) In the frontal lobe of brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pineal gland secrets Melatonin. It regulates sleep and wakefulness. Melatonin supplement is used to treat jet lags or sleep problems."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Changes in blood concentration of glucose, oxygen and hydrogen ions are detected by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Baroreceptors",
            "b) Chemoreceptors",
            "c) Nociceptors",
            "d) Proprioceptors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pineal gland is located in the epithalamus near the centre of the brain between the two hemisphere tucked in a groove where the two halves of the thalamus join. The function of this gland was discovered last."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of these receptors detects stretching or lengthening of a muscle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nociceptors",
            "b) Muscle spindle",
            "c) Golgi tendon organ",
            "d) Meissner’s coruscle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemoreceptors are stimulated by a change in concentration of chemicals such as glucose, oxygen, carbon dioxide and hydrogen ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "The sensation of temperature, touch, pressure and pain occurs in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temporal lobe",
            "b) Occipital lobe",
            "c) Parietal lobe",
            "d) Frontal lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Muscle spindle and Golgi tendon organs both transmit proprioceptive information. The muscle spindles are located within muscles while Golgi tendon organs are located within the tendons."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The occipital lobe contains which of the following primary sensory areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visual",
            "b) Taste",
            "c) Auditory",
            "d) Olfactory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sensation of temperature, touch, pressure and pain occur in postcentral gyrus of each parietal lobe. The Parietal lobe contains primary somatic sensory cortex. The thalamus projects general somatic sensory information to this part of the cerebrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an effect of aging on the nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in the number of free nerve ending",
            "b) Decreased awareness of tactile stimulation",
            "c) Identify objects by touch more easily",
            "d) An increases sense of two pint discrimination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The cerebrum is divided into lobes. The visual cortex where the visual images are processed is located in occipital lobe."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The spleen’s sinuses are filled with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blood",
            "b) Lymph",
            "c) Salts",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spleen is located in the upper left region of abdominal cavity beneath the diaphragm."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Nodule of spleen contains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red pulp and white pulp",
            "b) Hormone producing cells",
            "c) Glucose stored as glycogen",
            "d) Cells producing platelets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sinusoids is a small blood vessel that is a type of capillary. It is found in liver, bone marrow, spleen etc. It is filled with blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "White pulp contains mostly ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lymphocytes",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Macrophages",
            "d) Red blood cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spleen contains red pulp and white pulps. Red pulp is composed of connective tissue known as cords of Billroth."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "The length of the spleen is approximately ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12-14cm",
            "b) 5-10cm",
            "c) 20-25cm",
            "d) 30-35cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: White pulp is the histological region of the spleen. White pulp is lymphatic tissue mainly made u of white blood cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "__________ is the venous compartment of spleen and is important to break down RBC’s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) White pulp",
            "b) Red pulp",
            "c) Antigens",
            "d) Lymphocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Old red blood cells are recycled in the spleen. The platelets and white blood cells are stored in the spleen."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Polycythemia is _____________ RBC’s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreased",
            "b) Death",
            "c) Increased",
            "d) Birth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of the spleen is approximately 12-14cm. It is a bean shaped structure. It weighs about 150 grams."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Centromere is required for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transcription",
            "b) Crossing over",
            "c) Movement of chromosomes towards poles",
            "d) Cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Centromere is a special region of a chromosome. It helps in the movement of chromosomes towards poles."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Polytene chromosomes are formed due to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endomitosis",
            "b) Meiosis",
            "c) Mitosis",
            "d) Endomixis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polytene chromosomes are oversized chromosomes. It is formed due to endomitosis (without cell division)."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Racker’s particles occur in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria",
            "b) Nucleus",
            "c) Chromosome",
            "d) Golgi complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Racker’s particles occur in Mitochondria. They are also known as F1 particles. They help in production of ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Cell membrane is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semi permeable",
            "b) Permeable",
            "c) Selectively permeable",
            "d) Impermeable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell membrane is also known as plasma membrane. It is semi permeable membrane surrounding the cytoplasm of a cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not have a membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Mitochondria",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) Chloroplast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ribosome are the protein builders or the protein synthesizer of the cell. They consist of two major components: the small subunit and the large subunit."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Cell theory was proposed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virchow",
            "b) Robert Hooke",
            "c) McClintock",
            "d) Schleiden and Schwann"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cell theory was proposed by Schleiden and Schwann. It states that\nAll living things are composed of cells.\nAll the cells are produced from other cells\nCells are the basic units of structure and function in living things."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "There is no DNA in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An enucleated ovum",
            "b) Mature RBC",
            "c) Hair root",
            "d) Mature spermatozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mature RBC is flexible and oval biconcave discs. They lack a nucleus and most organelles in order to accommodate maximum space for hemoglobin."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Cell theory is not applicable to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virus",
            "b) Bacteria",
            "c) Fungi",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell theory is not applicable to the Virus. Viruses can be considered alive depending upon the host. They are much smaller than cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Histones octamer contains _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eight types of histones",
            "b) Five types of histones",
            "c) Eight histones of four different types",
            "d) Six types of histones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Histones octamer is an 8 protein complex found at the center of nucleosome core particles. it consists of two copies of each f four core histone proteins (H2A, H2B, H3 and H4)."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Hormone inhibin is secreted by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theca cells",
            "b) Zona pellucida",
            "c) Granulosa cells",
            "d) Corpus luteum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hormone inhibin is secreted by Corpus luteum. It inhibits the production of FSG by pituitary gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "The follicle that ruptures at the time of ovulation promptly fills with blood forming is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corpus albicans",
            "b) Corpus luteum",
            "c) Corpus haemorrhagium",
            "d) Corpus callosum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Corpus haemorrhagium is a temporary structure formed by immediately after ovulation from the ovarian follicle as it collapses and is filled with blood that quickly clots."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Cessation of menstrual cycle is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovulation",
            "b) Menopause",
            "c) Parturition",
            "d) Menarche"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Menopause is the natural decline in reproductive hormones when a woman reaches 40s or 50s. It is absence of a menstrual cycle. It is a gradual process."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "During oogenesis each diploid primary oocyte produces ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four functional sperms",
            "b) Four functional polar bodies",
            "c) Two functional eggs and two polar bodies",
            "d) One functional egg and three polar bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oogenesis occurs within embryo sac and leads to formation of single egg cell. During oogenesis each diploid primary oocyte produces One functional egg and three polar bodies."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Graafian follicle is maintained by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) Prolactin",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Androgens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FSH stands for follicle stimulating hormone. It is synthesized by pituitary gland. It controls menstrual cycle and production of eggs by the ovaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "The lytic enzyme released by sperm is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Hyaluronidase",
            "b) Acrosome",
            "c) Ligase",
            "d) Androgamone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hyaluronidase is a type of enzyme which catalyses degradation of hyaluronic acid. It is released to help the sperm to penetrate into the ovum."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The cytoplasm surrounding the mitochondria found in the middle piece of sperm is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manchette",
            "b) Microsome",
            "c) Acrosome",
            "d) Centrosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Manchette is an array of microtubules that invests in the nucleus of a spermatid. It is believed to play a role in shaping the nucleus during spermiogenesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Secondary spermatocytes are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diploids",
            "b) Haploids",
            "c) Tetraploids",
            "d) Triploids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main function of spermatocytes is to divide and produce spermatids. They undergo meiosis to form haploid Secondary spermatocytes each receiving half set of DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Acrosome of spermatozoa is formed by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Mitochondria",
            "c) Lysosomes",
            "d) Golgi complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acrosome contains digestive enzymes. They break down outer membrane of ovum. Acrosome of spermatozoa is formed by Golgi complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Nebenkern is the part of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovary",
            "b) Sperm",
            "c) Fetus",
            "d) Testis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nebenkern is the mitochondrial formation in the sperm. The Nebenkern proceeds to elongate into double stranded helical structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Middle piece of sperm contains ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria and Golgi body",
            "b) Centriole and Golgi body",
            "c) Mitochondria and axial filament",
            "d) Axial filament and Golgi body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The middle piece of sperm has a central filamentous core with many mitochondria spiraled around.  It is used for ATP production for the journey into female oviduct."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What occurs when egg and sperm fuse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differentiation",
            "b) Development",
            "c) Fertilization",
            "d) Cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fertilization occurs when egg and sperm fuse. Fertilization is the process of fusion of male and female gametes."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the cell division without growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleavage",
            "b) Conjugation",
            "c) Fertilization",
            "d) Development"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cleavage is the cell division without growth. It occurs after fertilization."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "___________ is a term for milk production.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactation",
            "b) Parturition",
            "c) Menstruation",
            "d) Ovulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lactation is called milk production. Oxytocin hormone is responsible for this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Hormones that cause uterus to contact are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH LH",
            "b) Prolactin and progesterone",
            "c) Estrogen and progesterone",
            "d) Oxytocin and prostaglandins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hormones that cause uterus to contact are Oxytocin and prostaglandin. There are peristaltic movements seen in the uterus."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which hormone is the basis for pregnancy test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCG",
            "b) Prolactin",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Prostaglandins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HCG (Human chorionic gonadotropic hormone) is the basis for pregnancy test. It is seen in the urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "The lining of uterus to which the embryo implants is called as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coccyx",
            "b) Trohoblast",
            "c) Yolk plug",
            "d) Endometrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Implantation is a process of attachment of the fetus to the wall of uterus. It is seen in 3rd week of the gestation period."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "The initial step during fertilization is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetration of sperm into egg",
            "b) Fertilizin and antifertilizin reaction",
            "c) Formation of fertilization membrane",
            "d) Formation of fertilization cone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The lining of uterus to which the embryo implants is called as Endometrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Fertilization of sperm and ovum takes place in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ampulla of oviduct",
            "b) Isthmus of oviduct",
            "c) Fimbriae of oviduct",
            "d) Uterus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The initial step during fertilization is Fertilizin and antifertilizin reaction. It reduces polyspermy."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The extra embryonic structure that provides nutrition to the embryo is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chorion",
            "b) Placenta",
            "c) Amnion",
            "d) Umblicus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fertilization of sperm and ovum takes place in Ampulla of oviduct. Ampulla is the 3rd portion of oviduct. The word ampulla is from Latin fro flask."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Beginning of menstruation is known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Menopause",
            "b) Ovulation",
            "c) Oogenesis",
            "d) Menarche"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Placenta is an organ that develops in uterus during pregnancy. It attaches to the wall of uterus and baby’s umbilical cord arises from it."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "The main function if fimbriae of oviduct are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Help in collection of ovum after ovulation",
            "b) Make necessary changes in endometrium for implantation",
            "c) Release ovum from Graafian follicle",
            "d) Help in devilment of embryo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Menarche is the first occurrence of menstruation in females. It is the central event of puberty as it signals the possibility of fertility."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The process of delivery of fetus is known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactation",
            "b) Implantation",
            "c) Parturition",
            "d) Fertilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The fimbriae of uterine tube are small fingerlike projections at the end of fallopian tube. Fimbriae are connected to the ovary. It helps in collection of ovum."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "In the absence of acrosome the sperm cannot ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetrate into egg",
            "b) Get energy",
            "c) Get food",
            "d) Swim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Parturition is the process of child birth. The fetus is taken out from the womb."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which type of tissue gives rise to notochord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mesoderm",
            "b) Endoderm",
            "c) Ectoderm",
            "d) Ovum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mesoderm gives rise to the notochord. Mesoderm is one of the primary germ layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The segmented blocks of tissue that develop on each side of notochord are called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Somites",
            "b) Neural tube",
            "c) Neural crest",
            "d) Adrenal medulla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Somites are bilaterally paired blocks of paraxial mesoderm that forms along the head to tail axis of the developing embryo in segmented animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The first truly vertebrate development is marked by the formation of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Notochord",
            "b) Neural crest",
            "c) Primitive streak",
            "d) Coccyx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Neural crest cells are temporary group of cells unique to vertebrates that arise from embryonic ectoderm cell layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "When does neuralation occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st week",
            "b) 2nd week",
            "c) 3rd week",
            "d) 4th week"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neuralation is a process of transformation of neural late into the neural tube. The embryo at this stage is termed as neurula. It occurs during 3rd week of gestation period.\t"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Where does the development of the notochord begin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the middle between two layer of bilaminar disc",
            "b) From endodermal layer",
            "c) At prechordal plate",
            "d) At cranial end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The development of the notochord begins in the middle between two layers of bilaminar disc."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Formation of primitive streak marks the beginning of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) neuraltion",
            "b) gastrulation",
            "c) folding",
            "d) notochord formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Primitive streak is the structure that forms in blastula during the early stages of embryonic development. It forms on the dorsal face of the developing embryo towards the posterior end."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "The notochord is essential for all except ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) to develop into mesoderm",
            "b) to establish axis of the body",
            "c) to establish nervous tissue in ectoderm",
            "d) influence embryonic folding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Notochord is a flexible rod made out of a material similar to cartilage. It serves as a source of midline signals that pattern surrounding tissues and as a major skeletal element of the developing embryo."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "The signals for parturition arises from___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) placenta",
            "b) oxytocin",
            "c) fetus",
            "d) placenta and fully developed fetus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The signals for parturition arise from Placenta and fully developed fetus. It is followed by uterine contraction."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "The anterior end of neural tube forms ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Notochord",
            "b) Gonads",
            "c) Brain",
            "d) Gut"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mesoderm cells become the skeletal system and muscular system. Ectoderm becomes epidermis, epithelial lining of mouth and rectum."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "How many stages does parturition have?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The anterior end of neural tube forms brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Ectodermal cells thicken into placodes that develop into ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the spinal cord",
            "b) peripheral nerves",
            "c) sensory organs",
            "d) skeletal muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Placenta is delivered during the 3rd stage. 3rd stage is the shortest stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Organogenesis in the embryo is completed by the end of which stage of the pregnancy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3rd trimester",
            "b) 1st month",
            "c) 2nd trimester",
            "d) 1st trimester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Parturition is considered to have 3 stages. Parturition is labor and expulsion of the fetus."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "In meroblastic cleavage the cleavage occurs in the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) placodes",
            "b) blastodisc",
            "c) trophoblast",
            "d) yolk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ectodermal cells thicken into placodes that develop into Sensory organs of the head. Placode is an area of thickening of the epithelium in the embryonic head ectoderm layer that gives rise to neurons and other sensory nervous system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "The embryo developed from somatic cells is called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) embryoid",
            "b) cybrid",
            "c) callus",
            "d) hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Organogenesis is a process by which the three germ layers develop into the organs. It is completed by the end of 1st trimester that is 3months."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "The ____________ is the primitive digestive tract or gut.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ectoderm",
            "b) Endoderm",
            "c) Mesoderm",
            "d) Archenteron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Archenteron is the rudimentary alimentary cavity of an embryo at the gastrula stage. It develops into endoderm and mesoderm."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Umbilical arteries carry __________ blood to the placenta.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygenated",
            "b) deoxygenated",
            "c) mixed  maternal and fetal",
            "d) no"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Umbilical arteries carry Deoxygenated blood to placenta. The artery is named for the fetus side and the placental veins therefore, it returns oxygenated blood to the fetus."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Placenta produces __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prolactin",
            "b) Oxytocin",
            "c) FSH",
            "d) Estrogen and progesterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Placenta produces Estrogen and progesterone. It also produces HCG and HPL hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": " When does the development of heart begin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st week",
            "b) 12th week",
            "c) 5th week",
            "d) 3rd week"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Placenta has two distinct separate compartments. The fetal side consisting of the trophoblast and chorionic villi and maternal side consisting of the deciduas basalis."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Embryonic development includes first ___________ of development.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Week",
            "b) 2 weeks",
            "c) 2 Month",
            "d) 9 months"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The heart and other organs start developing during 3rd week after conception. The baby’s brain and spinal cord will develop from neural tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Development requires _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastrulation and neuralation",
            "b) Cellular cleavage and fusion",
            "c) Growth cellular differentiation and morphogenesis",
            "d) Neurulation and induction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Embryogenesis is the process by which the embryo forms and develops. It starts with fertilization of egg cell by a sperm cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "During which stage do the three primary layers first appear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blastulation",
            "b) Neurulation",
            "c) Fertilization",
            "d) Gastrulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Development requires Growth cellular differentiation and morphogenesis. Morphogenesis is a process that causes an organism to develop its shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "A newborn infant obtains maternal antibodies from _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lanugo",
            "b) rubella",
            "c) colostrum",
            "d) afterbirth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gastrulation is a phase in embryonic development during which single layered blastula is reorganized into multilayered structure known as gastrula."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Human placenta is derived from _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chorion",
            "b) allantois",
            "c) amnion",
            "d) allantois and chorion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Colostrum is a form of milk produced by mammary gland of mammals during pregnancy. It contains antibodies to protect newborns from disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "The first movement of fetus and the appearance of hair on head occurs during?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5th month",
            "b) 7th month",
            "c) 2nd month",
            "d) 9th month"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Human placenta is derived from Chorion. The chorion and amnion together forms amniotic sac."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not a placental hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progesterone",
            "b) HCS",
            "c) HCG",
            "d) Melatonin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first movement of fetus is seen between 16 and 25 weeks of pregnancy. It is called as quickening."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Mother’s milk during lactation is rich in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IgA",
            "b) IgG",
            "c) IgM",
            "d) IgE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Melatonin is not a placental hormone. It is secreted by the Pineal gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "The zygote undergoes cleavage forming a solid ball of cells of the uniform size called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morula",
            "b) Blastula",
            "c) Gastrula",
            "d) Neurula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Morula is an early stage embryo consisting of cells in solid balls contained within zona pellucida."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "The third layer to form in gastrulation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archenteron",
            "b) Ectoderm",
            "c) Endoderm",
            "d) Mesoderm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mesoderm is one of the three primary germ layers in the early embryo. It is formed during gastrulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The trophoblast gives rise to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chorion",
            "b) Neurula",
            "c) Allantois",
            "d) Placenta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Development of all organs can be traced in single germ layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Cleavage begins at ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vagina",
            "b) Ovary",
            "c) Uterus",
            "d) Oviduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Trophoblast are cells forming the outer layer of blastocyst which provide nutrients to the embryo and develop into large part of placenta. "
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "The cavity inside the blastula is called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blastocoel",
            "b) Blastomere",
            "c) Gastrula",
            "d) Animal pore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Transformation of blastula into gastrula is gastrulation. It occurs during 2nd week of development."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The vertebrate embryo develops into hollow ball called as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fistula",
            "b) Blastula",
            "c) Gastrula",
            "d) Morula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cleavage begins at oviduct. In humans cleavage begins while fertilized egg is still passing down the oviduct."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The embryo at 16 celled stage is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morula",
            "b) Gastrula",
            "c) Blastula",
            "d) Blastomere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cavity inside the blastula is called as Blastocoel. It is a fluid filled cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Blastopore is the opening of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blastomere",
            "b) Blastula",
            "c) Gastrula",
            "d) Archenteron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blastula is a hollow sphere of cells surrounding an inner fluid filled cavity. The cells of blastula is referred as blastomere."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "At the time of implantation the embryo is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blastocyst",
            "b) Zygote",
            "c) Fetus",
            "d) Morula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Morula is the solid ball of cells resulting from the division of a fertilized ovum from which a blastula is formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "How many types of circulatory pathways are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two major types of circulatory pathway present. They are closed type and open type circulatory system."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Cockroach and other insects have blood which __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) circulates in open system",
            "b) has RBC’s",
            "c) resembles human blood color",
            "d) circulates through arteries and veins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Cockroach and other insects have open type circulatory system. In this type of system the blood does not flow inside the vessels."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Blood vascular system of earthworm is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) closed type with Hb in plasma",
            "b) open type with Hb in plasma",
            "c) open type with Hbin RBC’s",
            "d) closed type with Hb in RBC’s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Closed circulatory system has blood closed at all time within the vessels. Blood is pumped by a heart through vessels and does not normally fill body cavities."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "In which of the following animals hemoglobin is found dissolved in plasma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthworm",
            "b) Cockroach",
            "c) Sepia",
            "d) Planaria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxygen is carried in the blood in two forms. 1) Dissolved in plasma and RBC water and 2) Reversible bound to hemoglobin. In earthworm hemoglobin is found dissolved in the plasma."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What is heart made up of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skin",
            "b) Bone",
            "c) Muscle",
            "d) Tissues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Heart is made up of muscles. It is an involuntary organ. Heart is made up of muscle called as myocardium."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "What is a circulatory system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) System that helps body to move",
            "b) System that helps body to respire",
            "c) System that helps in transportation of blood",
            "d) System that deals with nerves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Circulatory system is an organ system that permits blood to circulate and transport nutrients, oxygen, carbon dioxide, hormones and blood cells. It is also known as vascular system or cardiovascular system."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "What makes blood clotting possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platelets",
            "b) Hemoglobin",
            "c) Lymphocytes",
            "d) Plasma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Platelets help in blood clotting. It is also known as thrombocytes. It is a component of blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of WBC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They fight against bacteria",
            "b) They guard against infection",
            "c) They carry oxygen",
            "d) They attack pathogens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: WBCs are white blood cells. It is also known as leukocytes. They are cells of immune system and helps in fighting infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Which of the following has closed circulatory system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arthropods",
            "b) Mollusks",
            "c) Platyhelminthes",
            "d) Annelids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Annelids are a large phylum. They are also known as ringed worms or segmented worms. Closed circulatory system is found in annelids."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which of the following component cause coagulation if introduced to the blood stream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fibrinogen",
            "b) Prothrombin",
            "c) Heparin",
            "d) Thromboplastin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thromboplastin is a plasma protein aiding blood coagulation. It catalyzes the conversion of prothrombin to thrombin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Process of formation of blood corpuscles is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) haemolysis",
            "b) haemopoeisis",
            "c) haemozoin",
            "d) haemolytic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Haemopoeisis is the production of blood cells and platelets. It occurs in bone marrow."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "The normal blood pressure of an adult is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100/80 mm Hg",
            "b) 100/60 mm Hg",
            "c) 120/80 mm Hg",
            "d) 80/120 mm Hg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blood pressure is the pressure of circulating blood on the walls of blood vessels. The normal blood pressure of an adult is 120/80 mm Hg."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "What is Pernicious anemia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low RBC count",
            "b) Destruction of RBC maturation",
            "c) Death of WBC",
            "d) Low WBC count"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pernicious anemia is decreased in red blood cells when body can’t absorb enough vitamin B12. There are more than 1 million cases in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Graveyard of RBC is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) spleen",
            "b) liver",
            "c) stomach",
            "d) pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Spleen is known as Graveyard of RBC. For every 120 days new RBCs are formed. Old blood cells are recycled in spleen."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which leucocytes release heparin and histamine into the blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basophils",
            "b) Neutrophils",
            "c) Monocytes",
            "d) Lymphocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basophils contain heparin. This is the naturally occurring blood thinning substance. It is seen in WBCs."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which among the following is true regarding leucocytes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are enucleated",
            "b) Produced in thymus",
            "c) Sudden fall in number indicate cancer",
            "d) They can squeeze through capillary walls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Leucocytes are involved in protecting body against infectious disease. They are produced in bone marrow. Leucocytes can squeeze through capillary walls and this is called as diapedesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Largest sized RBC is seen in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) elephant",
            "b) whale",
            "c) man",
            "d) amphiuma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Largest RBC is seen in amphiuma. RBCs are an important part of blood. They help in the transportation of oxygen throughout the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Irregular nuclei are seen in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) basophiles",
            "b) eosinphil",
            "c) monocytes",
            "d) neutrophil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Neutrophil is a type of immune cell. They fight infection by ingesting microorganisms and releasing the enzymes that kill the microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Hemoglobin is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) respiratory pigment",
            "b) reproductive pigment",
            "c) fat",
            "d) carbohydrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hemoglobin is the iron containing oxygen transport metalloprotein in RBCs. It is abbreviated as Hb."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Hemophilia is due to absence of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) factor VI",
            "b) factor VII",
            "c) factor VIII",
            "d) factor X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hemophilia is a disorder in which blot doesn’t clot normally. There are different types of Hemophilia. It is due to the absence of Factor VIII."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the cellular element of blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T cells",
            "b) B cells",
            "c) Plasma",
            "d) Monocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasma is not the cellular elements of blood. Blood plasma is yellowish colored liquid. It makes up 55% of the body’s total blood volume. It contains water and dissolved proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Red cell count is carried out using _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) electrocardiogram",
            "b) sphygmomanometer",
            "c) haemocytometer",
            "d) haemoglobinometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Haemocytometer is a specialized slide that has a counting chamber with a known volume of liquid. It is used to count RBC."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "How many types of blood groups are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are four types of blood group present. They are A, B, O and AB type."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following blood group is considered a universal donor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) AB",
            "d) O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Blood group O is considered are universal donor. The Rh negative blood is given to Rh negative patients and Rh positive blood or Rh negative blood are given to Rh positive patients. O negative is considered as universal donor."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "The antigens for ABO and Rh blood groups are present on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plasma",
            "b) white blood cells",
            "c) red blood cells",
            "d) platelets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Red blood cells are the most common type of blood cells and principle means of delivering oxygen. The antigens for blood groups are present on RBCs."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of the following blood group is referred as a universal recipient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) AB",
            "d) O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blood group AB is referred as a universal recipient. They can receive donated blood of any ABO blood group."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "What are the two blood tests?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rh and ABB",
            "b) ABO and Rh",
            "c) ABO and Rn",
            "d) ABC and Rh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two blood tests are ABO and Rh type. ABO test determines the blood group. Rh test determines if it is positive or negative."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "What is the process of transfer of human blood known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfusion",
            "b) Processing",
            "c) Transporting",
            "d) Transferring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blood transfusion is the process of receiving blood or blood products into ones circulation intravenously. It is used in various medical conditions to replace the lost component of blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which is the rarest blood group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AB negative",
            "b) AB positive",
            "c) O negative",
            "d) O positive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  AB negative is the rarest blood group. It is seen only in 1% of the US population."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Who discovered blood groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thomas Cooley",
            "b) Karl Landsteiner",
            "c) Camillo Golgi",
            "d) Ernst Haecker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Karl Landsteiner discovered ABO blood group system. He is an Austrian scientist. It was discovered in 1900."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Rh group was discovered in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1930s",
            "b) 1940s",
            "c) 1950s",
            "d) 1960s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The Rh factor was discovered in 1940 by Karl Landsteiner and A.S. Wiener. It is known as the rhesus factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "If the blood group of an individual is A then the antibody present is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti B antibodies",
            "b) Anti A antibodies",
            "c) Anti O antibodies",
            "d) Anti OA antibodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the blood group of an individual is A then the antibody present is Anti B antibodies. It is present on RBCs."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which blood type can be transfused to the individual whose blood type is unknown?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AB positive",
            "b) AB negative",
            "c) O positive",
            "d) O negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: O negative blood type can be transfused to individual whose blood type is unknown since it is a universal donor blood group.  Only6.6% of population has O negative blood group."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "In determining phenotype of ABO system ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) O is dominant over A",
            "b) B is dominant over A",
            "c) O is recessive",
            "d) A is dominant over O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In determining the phenotype of ABO system O is recessive. A and B are dominant over O."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Tissue plasmin activator _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) helps in wound healing",
            "b) allergy response",
            "c) immunity",
            "d) dissolves clot in blood vessels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmin is an important enzyme present in blood that degrades fibrin clot. Plasmin protein is encoded by the PLG gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following will not coagulate when placed separately on four slides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blood serum",
            "b) Blood plasma",
            "c) Blood from pulmonary vein",
            "d) Blood from lymphatic tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blood serum is a component that is neither a blood cell nor a clotting factor. It is the blood plasma not including the fibrinogens."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "The vitamin essential for blood clotting is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) vitamin A",
            "b) vitamin B",
            "c) vitamin C",
            "d) vitamin K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vitamin K is an essential nutrient necessary for responding to injuries. It regulates normal blood clotting. It also helps for bone health."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "What prevents clotting of blood in blood vessels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serotonin",
            "b) Fibrinogen",
            "c) Heparin",
            "d) Fibrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Heparin is used as an anticoagulant. It inhibits reactions that lead to the clotting of blood and the formation of fibrin clots both in vitro and in vivo."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Clumping of cells is known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) clotting",
            "b) mutation",
            "c) agglutination",
            "d) glutathione"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Agglutination is a process that occurs if an antigen is mixed with its corresponding antibody called isoagglutinin. This is used during blood grouping."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lymph = Plasma + WBC’s + RBC’s",
            "b) Plasma = Blood – Lymphocytes",
            "c) Neuron = Cyton + Dendron + Axon + Synapse",
            "d) Blood = Plasma + RBC’s + WBC’s + Platelets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Blood is essential for life. Blood consists of plasma, rbcs, wbcs, and platelets."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Antibiotics are useful against __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) virus",
            "b) bacteria",
            "c) autoimmune disease",
            "d) fungi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Antibiotics are strong medicines that treat bacterial infections. Antibiotics won’t treat viral infections because they can’t kill viruses. "
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Antigen presenting cells are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) T cells",
            "b) B cells",
            "c) Macrophages",
            "d) Mast cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  T cells are a type of lymphocyte that lays central role in cell mediated immunity. It has the presence of receptor on the cell surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of the following plasma protein is involved in coagulation of blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Albumin",
            "b) Globulin",
            "c) Fibrinogen",
            "d) Amylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fibrinogen is a glycoprotein, during tissue injury it is converted by thrombin to fibrin and subsequently to a fibrin based blood clot."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "In the clotting mechanism pathway, thrombin activates factors ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) XI VIII V",
            "b) XI IX X",
            "c) VIII X V",
            "d) IX VIII X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thrombin is encoded by F2 gene. There are 12 clotting factors. Thrombin activates XI, VIII and V factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "“Heart of heart” is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SA node",
            "b) AV node",
            "c) Bundle of HIS",
            "d) Purkinji fibers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: “Heart of heart” is SA node."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the thickest wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right ventricle",
            "b) Left ventricle",
            "c) Right atrium",
            "d) Left atrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Left ventricle has the thickest wall in the human heart. "
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Pacemaker is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AV node",
            "b) SA node",
            "c) Bundle of HIS",
            "d) Ventricle muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pacemaker is SA node. SA node is located in upper lateral wall of right atrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "SA node is located in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) upper lateral wall of right atrium",
            "b) lower lateral wall of left atrium",
            "c) lower lateral wall of right atrium",
            "d) upper lateral wall of left atrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SA node is located in upper lateral wall of right atrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "“Bundle of HIS” is made up of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nervous tissue supplied to ventricles",
            "b) nervous tissue supplied to heart",
            "c) muscular tissue supplied to heart",
            "d) muscular tissue supplied to ventricles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bundle of HIS is made up of muscular tissue supplied to ventricles."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Blood enters into the heart because of muscles of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) atria relax",
            "b) ventricles contract",
            "c) ventricles relax",
            "d) atria contract"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blood enters the heart through large veins called as vena cava. Blood enters the heart when the muscles of atria relax and it is pumped out when it is contracted."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The opening of right atrium into right ventricle is guarded by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mitral valve",
            "b) tricuspid valve",
            "c) bicuspid valve",
            "d) aortic semilunar valve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tricuspid valve is on the right dorsal side of the mammalian heart between the right atrium and right ventricle. The function of the valve is to prevent back flow of blood into right atrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Mitral valve is present between __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) right atrium and left ventricle",
            "b) right and left ventricle",
            "c) left ventricle and aorta",
            "d) left atrium and left ventricle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mitral valve is a valve that lets blood flow from one chamber of the heart, the left atrium to another called the left ventricle. In mitral valve prolapsed part of mitral valve slips backward loosely into the chamber called the left atrium."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Cardiac output is determined by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) heart rate",
            "b) stroke volume",
            "c) blood flow",
            "d) heart rate and stroke volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stroke volume is an amount of blood pumped by the left ventricle of the heart in one contraction. The heart rate for adults ranges from 60-100 beats per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "In human being the duration of cardiac cycle is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.008 sec",
            "b) 0.5 sec",
            "c) 0.8 sec",
            "d) 8 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The duration of the cardiac cycle is reciprocal of heart rate. Assuming a heart rate of 75 beats per minute, each cycle takes 0.8sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "The volume of blood each ventricle pumps out during a cardiac cycle is about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70 ml",
            "b) 5000 ml",
            "c) 7 L",
            "d) 1200 ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cardiac output is a volume of blood pumped by the heart in a minute. It is equal to the heart rate multiplied by the heart stroke, so if there are 70 beats per minute and 70ml blood is ejected with each beat of the heart, the cardiac output is 4900ml per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "What is the definition of the cardiac cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The contraction of the atria",
            "b) Circulation of the blood in the heart",
            "c) The contraction and relaxation of the ventricles",
            "d) It is a sequence of event that occurs during one complete  heartbeat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cardiac cycle refers to the sequence of mechanical and electrical events that repeats with every heartbeat. It includes diastole and systole."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Name the three phases of cardiac cycle in the order ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) early diastole, mid-to-late diastole, ventricular systole",
            "b) ventricular systole, mid-to-late diastole, Early diastole",
            "c) mid-to-late diastole, Ventricular systole, Early diastole",
            "d) early diastole, Ventricular systole, mid-to-late diastole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Every beat of the heart involves 3 major stages. They are mid-to-late diastole, Ventricular systole, Early diastole."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "An electrocardiogram is a graphic illustration of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cardiac conduction system",
            "b) cardiac cycle",
            "c) cardiac output",
            "d) systemic and pulmonary circuits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrocardiogram is a test which measures the electrical activity of the heart. It records the heart’s rhythm and activity on a moving strip of paper or a line on the screen."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "The P wave of the ECG represents _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ventricular depolarization",
            "b) atrial depolarization",
            "c) ventricular repolarization",
            "d) atrial systole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: P wave is the first wave. It represents atrial depolarization. P wave is followed by QRS complex and T wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for ventricular systole?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ventricles relax",
            "b) The ventricles contract",
            "c) The semi lunar valves close",
            "d) The atrioventricular valves open"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Systole is the last stage of the heartbeat. It happens right after the diastole. "
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Heart beat initiates from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purkinji fibers",
            "b) SA node",
            "c) Bundle of HIS",
            "d) Auriculo ventricular node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SA node is heart’s natural pacemaker. Heart beat initiates from SA node."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "An artificial pace maker is implanted and connected to the heart in patients ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) suffering from arteriosclerosis",
            "b) having high blood pressure",
            "c) with irregularity in heart rhythm",
            "d) having 90% blockage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  A pace maker is a medical device which uses electrical impulses, delivered by the electrodes contacting the heart muscles to regulate the beating of the heart."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "A heat murmurs indicates a defective ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heart valves",
            "b) Bundle of HIS",
            "c) SA node",
            "d) AV node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  A heart murmur can be a symptom of serious heart diseases. A heart murmur indicates defective heart valve."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Choose the correct pathway of the transmission of impulses in heart beat.",
        "Options": [
            "a) AV node- SA node- Bundle of HIS- Purkinji fibres",
            "b) SA node- AV node- Bundle of HIS- Purkinji fibres",
            "c) SA node- Bundle of HIS- AV node- Purkinji fibres",
            "d) SA node Purkinji fibres- Bundle of HIS- AV node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The heart impulse starts from SA node and ends in Purkinji fibres."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "In ECG the depolarization of atria is indicated by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P wave",
            "b) Q wave",
            "c) R wave",
            "d) S wave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ECG the depolarization of atria is indicated by P wave. This happens right before the atria contracts and push blood into the ventricles."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following pair is correctly matched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dup- Sudden opening of semilunar valves at the beginning of ventricle diastole",
            "b) Lubb- Sharp closing of AV valves at the beginning of ventricular systole",
            "c) Pulsation of radial artery valves in blood vessels",
            "d) Initiation of heart beat- Purkinji fibers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lub is the first heart sound and is caused by the closure of mitral valve and tricuspid valves at the startup systole. The second sound dub is caused by the closer of aortic and pulmonic valve marking the end of systole."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which instrument is used to listen to the internal sounds of the human body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stethoscope",
            "b) Sphygmomanometer",
            "c) Reflex hammer",
            "d) Suction device"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stethoscope is an acoustic medical device for auscultation. It has a small disc shaped resonator that is placed against the chest and two tubes connected to earpieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 130/90 mm Hg is considered high and require treatment",
            "b) 100/55 mm Hg is considered an ideal blood pressure",
            "c) 105/50 mm Hg makes one active",
            "d) 190/110 mm Hg may harm vital organs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The high blood pressure may harm vital organs of the body.  It is the condition in which the force of blood against the artery valve is very high."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Blood pressure is the pressure exerted by blood against ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) kidneys",
            "b) artery walls",
            "c) brain",
            "d) stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blood pressure exerted by circulating blood on the walls of blood vessels."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Blood pressure is measured in terms of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm Hg",
            "b) mm",
            "c) cm Hg",
            "d) Hg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Blood pressure values are generally measured in terms of millimeters of mercury. It is measured using an instrument called as sphygmomanometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "A normal heart rate in an adult at rest is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 110",
            "b) 125",
            "c) 60",
            "d) 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Low blood pressure is when the systolic and diastolic blood pressure is below for the age of the person. High BP is when blood pressure is high than 120/80 mm Hg. "
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": " Unhealthy growth of tissue due to higher pressures on the walls of the artery is termed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) atheroma",
            "b) aroma",
            "c) adenoma",
            "d) aroma and adenoma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  A normal resting heart rate for an adult ranges from 70-85 beats a minute. Generally, a lower heart rate at rest implies more efficient heart function and better cardiovascular fitness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Any mechanism that increases heart rate is said to have a positive ________ effect.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cholinergic",
            "b) inotropic",
            "c) chronotrophic",
            "d) feedback"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atheroma is the growth of tissues due to higher pressure on walls of artery. High pressures increases heart work load."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "The colloid osmotic pressure of blood plasma is due to high concentration of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) albumin",
            "b) hemoglobin",
            "c) sodium",
            "d) glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Chronotrophic are those that change the heart rate. It changes the heart rate by affecting the electrical conduction system of the heart."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "The sinoatrial node depolarizes more frequently under the influence of  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) medulla oblongata",
            "b) vagus nerve",
            "c) norepinephrine",
            "d) acetylcholine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Albumin is a family of globular protein. The most important function is maintaining intra vascular colloid osmotic pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "_________ is the enzyme that converts Angiotensinogen to Angiotensin I.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rennin",
            "b) ACE",
            "c) ANP",
            "d) ADH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Norepinephrine is similar to adrenaline. It is used to treat life threatening low BP that can occur with certain medical conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Crown of teeth is covered by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) enamel",
            "b) dentine",
            "c) skin",
            "d) sone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crown of teeth is covered by enamel. It is the highly mineralized substance of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Alimentary canal is absent in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fasciola hepatica",
            "b) Taenia solium",
            "c) Ascaris suum",
            "d) Ancylostoma caninum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taenia solium is a pork tapeworm. It is a parasite causing disease. It lacks the alimentary canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "How many teeth appear twice during the life span of an individual?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16",
            "b) 17",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 20 teeth appear twice during the life span of an individual. The first set is called milk teeth and the second set is called permanent teeth."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "The pH of saliva is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.5",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 7.5",
            "d) 6.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pH of saliva is 6.8.it is basic in nature. It has enzymes to digest carbohydrates."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Alimentary canal of herbivores differs from carnivore in having _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short alimentary canal",
            "b) Long alimentary canal",
            "c) Thin alimentary canal",
            "d) Fat alimentary canal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Herbivores as grass eating animals. To digest the cellulose present in it the herbivores have long alimentary canal comparing to carnivores."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Diastema is associated with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absence of teeth",
            "b) Organ of corti",
            "c) Retinal cells",
            "d) Presence of extra teeth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diastema is associated with an absence of teeth. It is very common in human beings."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The involuntary muscular movement of alimentary canal is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amoeboid movement",
            "b) Peristalsis movement",
            "c) Smooth movement",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peristalsis movement is an involuntary muscular movement. It occurs in esophagus, stomach and intestines."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the chisel shaped teeth use for biting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incisors",
            "b) Canines",
            "c) Molars",
            "d) Pre molars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Incisors are four in numbers in a human being. They are located in the premaxilla above and on the mandible below."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not release any enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salivary glands",
            "b) Esophagus",
            "c) Stomach",
            "d) Pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Esophagus does not release any enzyme. It connects throat from stomach and food passes through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which of the following vitamin is water soluble and antioxidant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin B1",
            "b) Vitamin A",
            "c) Vitamin D",
            "d) Vitamin C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Vitamin C is water soluble and antioxidant. The disease scurvy is prevented and treated using vitamin C rich supplements."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Enzymes, vitamins and hormones can be classified into single category on biological chemicals because they __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) enhance oxidative metabolisms",
            "b) help in regulating metabolism",
            "c) are conjugated proteins",
            "d) are exclusively synthesized inside the body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enzymes, vitamins and hormones can be classified into single category on biological chemicals because of all of these help in regulating metabolism. They play a major role in the functioning of human body."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Microphagial nutrition occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) paramecium",
            "b) insects",
            "c) euglena",
            "d) hydra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microphagial nutrition occurs in Paramecium. Paramecium is a tiny unicellular organism found in water."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Kwashiorkor disease occurs due to deficiency of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipids",
            "b) sugars",
            "c) hormones",
            "d) proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Kwashiorkor disease occurs due to a deficiency of proteins. It is a form of malnutrition."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Osteomalacia occurs due to deficiency of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin D",
            "b) Vitamin A",
            "c) Vitamin B",
            "d) Vitamin E"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Osteomalacia is the softening of bones caused by impaired bone metabolism. It is caused due to inadequate levels of vitamin D calcium and phosphate."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Biotrophic nutrition is shown by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) humans",
            "b) insectivorous plants",
            "c) invertebrates",
            "d) saprophytic plants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Biotrophic pathogens derive nutrients from living cells by maintaining host viability. They don’t kill host plant rapidly."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which of the following cells produces HCL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beta cells",
            "b) Oxyntic cells",
            "c) Chief cells",
            "d) Alpha cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxyntic cells are also known as parietal cells. They are located in the gastric glands found in the lining of the fundus and in the body of the stomach."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "The gastric juice contains _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trypsin, pepsin, lipase",
            "b) Pepsin, lipase, rennin",
            "c) Pepsin, amylase, trypsin",
            "d) Trypsin, pepsin, rennin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gastric juice contains Pepsin, lipase, rennin. They are the enzymes which help in breaking down of food."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Digestion of protein is completed in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Ileum",
            "c) Duodenum",
            "d) Duodenum and Ileum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Digestion of protein is completed in Duodenum. Duodenum is the part of small intestine. Different enzymes act on food so that it gets digested."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Enzyme rennin is secreted by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stomach",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Kidney",
            "d) Pancreas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rennin is the enzyme secreted by stomach. It helps in the digestion of milk."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Jaundice is the disorder of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excretory system",
            "b) Digestive system",
            "c) Circulatory system",
            "d) Skin and eyes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Jaundice is the disorder of the digestive system. Jaundice occurs when there is too much bilirubin in the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Which of the following converts pepsinogen to the active form of pepsin in the stomach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mucus",
            "b) Gastrin",
            "c) HCL",
            "d) Chef cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hcl present in the stomach converts inactive pepsinogen into active pepsin. It helps in the digestion of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Secretion of Gastric juice is stimulated by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastrin",
            "b) Cholecystokinin",
            "c) Enterogastrin",
            "d) Pepsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Gastrin stimulates secretion of gastric juice. It is a peptide hormone. It is released by G cells in pyloric antrum of the stomach."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the largest gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liver",
            "b) Thymus",
            "c) Pancreases",
            "d) Thymus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liver is the largest gland of human body. It is present on the right side of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Part of bile juice useful in digestion is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bile pigments",
            "b) Bile salts",
            "c) Bile matrix",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bile salts help in the absorption and digestion of fats. Many waste products are eliminated from the body by secretion into bile and elimination in feces."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Bile helps in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Digestion of proteins",
            "b) Breaking down of nucleic acids",
            "c) Emulsification of fats",
            "d) Phagocytosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bile is produced by liver. It helps in breaking down of large molecule of fats into smaller parts and this process is known as emulsification."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Name the digestive juice that lacks enzyme but helps in digestion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bile juice",
            "b) Pancreatic juice",
            "c) Ptyalin",
            "d) Pepsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bile juice doesn’t contain any enzyme. It helps in digestion of fats."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Stores liver’s digestive juice until they are needed by the intestines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreas",
            "b) Gall bladder",
            "c) Villi",
            "d) Stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gall bladder stores the livers digestive juice. It is present under the liver. Gall bladder delivers bile into the small intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "RBC’s are broken down in abnormally large amounts in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cirrhosis",
            "b) Viral hepatitis",
            "c) Hemolytic jaundice",
            "d) Obstructive jaundice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hemolytic jaundice is caused due to increase in hemolysis.  Unconjugated bIllirubin comes from the breakdown of the heme pigment found in RBC."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "When starch is broken down by pancreatic amylase ______ is formed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose",
            "b) Maltose",
            "c) Peptides",
            "d) Amino acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maltose is a disaccharide formed from two units of glucose. When starch is broken down maltose is formed in the pancreas."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which is the readily available source of energy in the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein",
            "b) Carbohydrates",
            "c) Lipids",
            "d) Vitamins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbohydrates is the readily available source of energy in the body. The simplest carbohydrate is glucose. It undergoes glycolysis to give energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Where is the liver situated in the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beside the pancreas",
            "b) Beside heart",
            "c) Above kidney",
            "d) Above stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Liver is located in the upper right hand portion of the abdominal cavity beneath the diaphragm and top of the stomach. It is a dark reddish brown organ."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Bile salts acts as activator of which enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lipase",
            "b) Pepsinogen",
            "c) Pancreatic lipase",
            "d) Trypsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lipase is an enzyme which catalyses the hydrolysis of fats.  Lipase performs essential role in digestion."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "“Glisson capsule” is seen in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kidneys",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Pancreas",
            "d) Stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bile salts help in emulsification of fats. It takes place in the liver. Fats are broken down into smaller molecules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following vitamin can be produced by the liver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin A",
            "b) Vitamin B",
            "c) Vitamin C",
            "d) Vitamin D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glisson capsule is a layer of connective tissue surrounding the hepatic artery. It is seen in the liver. It is named after a scientist who discovered it."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following forms of viral hepatitis is caused by a defective single stranded RNA virus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hepatitis A",
            "b) Hepatitis B",
            "c) Hepatitis C",
            "d) Hepatitis D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vitamin A can be produced by the liver. It is fat soluble and antioxidant."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Approximately how much bile is produced by the liver every 24hours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36 ounces",
            "b) 30 ounces",
            "c) 18 ounces",
            "d) 24 ounces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: Hepatitis D is a serious liver disease. It is transmitted from an infected individual through blood contamination or sexual contact."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "What is the approximate weight of the liver in a healthy adult?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.4kg",
            "b) 2.3kg",
            "c) 0.9kg",
            "d) 1.8kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Approximately 24 ounces bile is produced by the liver in every 24hours."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which part of pancreas produce and secrete insulin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glomerulus",
            "b) Bowman’s capsule",
            "c) Islets of Langerhans",
            "d) Loop of Henle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Islets of Langerhans are present in pancreas. It contains many types of cells that produces insulin hormone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Alpha cells are found in _________ of the islet while beta cells are usually found in the __________ of the islet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Periphery, center",
            "b) Center, periphery",
            "c) Equally in both regions, periphery",
            "d) Periphery, Equally in both regions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alpha cells are found in the Periphery of the islet while beta cells are usually found in the center of the islet. It secretes hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Secretion of pancreatic juice is stimulated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gastrin",
            "b) Secretin",
            "c) Enterokinase",
            "d) Enterogastron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pancreatic juice is produced by the pancreas. It is alkaline in nature. Secretin helps to stimulate pancreas to produce pancreatic juice which helps in digestion."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the common passage for bile and pancreatic juice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duct of oddi",
            "b) Ampulla",
            "c) Stomach",
            "d) Duct of Wirsung"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ampulla is the common passage for bile and pancreatic juice. It then moves into the small intestine for the digestion process."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The pancreatic juice which aids digestion is secreted into?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liver",
            "b) Duodenum",
            "c) Stomach",
            "d) Ileum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pancreatic juice helps in digestion of fat. It contains enzymes. It also helps in digestion of proteins and carbohydrates."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which cells produce insulin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha cells",
            "b) Beta cells",
            "c) Delta cells",
            "d) F cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Duodenum is the initial part of the intestine and is a vital organ for digestion. The pancreatic juice is drained into the duodenum via pancreatic duct."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Pellagra is caused due to deficiency of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Niacin",
            "b) Pantothenic acid",
            "c) Tocopherol",
            "d) Cyanocobalamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pellagra is caused due to deficiency of Niacin. It is characterized by diarrhea and dementia. If it is untreated it may result in death of that person."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "A patient is advised to include more meat, lentils, milk and eggs in diet only when he suffers from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maramus",
            "b) Thyroid",
            "c) Osteomalacia",
            "d) Kwashiorkar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Kwashiorkar is caused due to deficiency of proteins. It is characterized by edema, enlarged liver, ulcerating dermatoses."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Continued consumption of a diet rich in butter, red meat and eggs for long period may cause?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toxicity",
            "b) Kidney stones",
            "c) Hypercholesterolemia",
            "d) Urine with ketone bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: Hypercholesterolemia is caused due to high cholesterol in the blood. It may further lead to heart disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "An obstruction in bile duct causes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jaundice",
            "b) Malaria",
            "c) Cholera",
            "d) Acidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An obstruction in bile duct causes Jaundice. It is caused due to the accumulation of bilirubin in the system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Gall stones or alcohol abuse can lead to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreatitis",
            "b) Cystitis",
            "c) Pancreatic cancer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Pancreatitis is the inflammation of the pancreas. It is very painful. Gall stones are the leading cause. The stones get trapped in the bile duct leading to inflammation."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "How many types of viral hepatitis is present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 5 types of viral hepatitis. They are Hepatitis A, Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, Hepatitis D, and Hepatitis E."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Diarrhea takes out too much of water and minerals which causes _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lack of energy",
            "b) Dryness",
            "c) Hunger",
            "d) Dehydration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Diarrhea is a condition of having at least three loose or liquid bowl movements each day. It may lead to dehydration. "
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of the following cause a hiatal hernia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased intrathorasic pressure",
            "b) Weakness of diaphragm muscle",
            "c) Increased esophageal muscle pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is caused due to Weakness of diaphragm muscle and increased intra abdominal pressure. This makes the stomach slide into the esophagus. "
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "In gastric acid perforates, which of the following actions should not be included in the immediate management?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antacid administration",
            "b) Fluid and electrolyte replacement",
            "c) Blood replacement",
            "d) Nasogastric tube suction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Antacids aren’t helpful in perforation. The patient should be treated with antibiotics as well as fluid, electrolytes and blood replacement."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of the following test is used to diagnose ulcers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EGD",
            "b) Barium swallow",
            "c) CT scan",
            "d) X ray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EGD is used to visualize the entire upper GI tract, EGD stands for Esophagogastroduodenoscopy. The barium swallow is used to locate a gastric ulcer."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for aerobic respiration in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose + water = carbon dioxide + water",
            "b) Glucose + oxygen = Carbon dioxide + water",
            "c) Glucose = Carbon dioxide + water",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aerobic respiration is the process of producing cellular energy involving oxygen. The first step is glycolysis. Glucose and oxygen react to produce carbon dioxide and water."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Respiration results in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Release of oxygen",
            "b) Anabolism",
            "c) Release of carbon dioxide",
            "d) Transfer of carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Respiration is the movement of oxygen from outside environment to cells and transport of carbon dioxide in the opposite direction. Respiration results in release of carbon dioxide from the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "During hibernation frogs respire through ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gills",
            "b) Lungs",
            "c) Tympanum",
            "d) Integument"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Frogs hibernate to escape freezing temperatures. During hibernation frogs respire through integument."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "In which of the following animal respiration occur without any respiration organs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frog",
            "b) Fish",
            "c) Cockroach",
            "d) Earthworm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Earthworm is a tube shaped segmented worm. It is classified into annelid. It lacks respiration organs. Respiration occurs through skin."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The product of glycolysis is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyruvate",
            "b) Lactic acid",
            "c) NADH",
            "d) Acetyl coA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fishes do not respire through skin. They have gills which help them in breathing."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Where in the cell most of the aerobic respiration takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria",
            "b) Nucleus",
            "c) Ribosome",
            "d) Cytoplasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The end product of glycolysis is pyruvate.  It is made from glucose."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following occurs both in photosynthesis and respiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Krebs cycle",
            "b) Glycolysis",
            "c) Calvin cycle",
            "d) Chemiosmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mitochondria is the power house of the cell. Most of the aerobic respiration occurs in mitochondria. It is double layered organelle."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for anaerobic respiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose + lactic acid = carbon dioxide + water",
            "b) Glucose= Lactic acid + carbon dioxide",
            "c) Glucose gives lactic acid",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Krebs cycle is a series of chemical reactions to release stored energy. It is also known as citric acid cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Catabolic processes ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Make complex molecules",
            "b) Break complex molecules",
            "c) Occur in autotrophs",
            "d) Occur in heterotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anaerobic respiration occurs during a lack of oxygen. It is used when there is not enough oxygen present."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Respiration is controlled by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cerebrum",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Medulla oblongata",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Respiration is controlled by Medulla oblongata. Medulla oblongata is located in brainstem. It also controls circulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The majority of carbon dioxide produced by the body is transported to lungs _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dissolved in blood",
            "b) As carbonates",
            "c) As bicarbonates",
            "d) Attached to hemoglobin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The majority of carbon dioxide produced by the body is transported to lungs in the form of bicarbonates. It is then expelled out from lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which one of the following mammalian cells are not capable of metabolizing glucose to carbon dioxide aerobically?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RBC",
            "b) WBC",
            "c) Liver cells",
            "d) Unstraited muscle cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Red blood cells are not capable of metabolizing glucose to carbon dioxide aerobically. They contain hemoglobin pigment."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "During inspiration the diaphragm _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expands",
            "b) Contracts",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Relaxes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of breathing is divided into inspiration and expiration. The process of inhalation is called as inspiration. During this process the diaphragm contacts and the air gets filled into the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Cramps during exercise are caused due to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemiosmosis",
            "b) Glycolysis inhibition",
            "c) Lactic acid fermentation",
            "d) Alcohol fermentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Respiration depends partly on the principle of diffusion and facilitated diffusion. Diffusion is flow of substance from higher concentration to lower concentration region."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the product of the Krebs cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP",
            "b) NADH",
            "c) FADH",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cramps during exercise are caused due to lactic acid fermentation."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Which of the following Produces maximum ATP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Krebs cycle",
            "b) Glycolysis",
            "c) Fermentation",
            "d) Oxidative Phosphorylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A person cannot expel all the air from lungs. A small amount of air will be present in the lungs."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "RQ is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio of CO2 produced to substrate consumed",
            "b) Ratio of CO2 produced to O2 consumed",
            "c) Ratio of oxygen consumed to CO2 produced",
            "d) Ratio of oxygen consumed to water produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The end products of the Krebs cycle consist of 6 NADH, 2 FADH, 4 carbon dioxide and 2 ATPs."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "The epithelial tissues present on the inner surface of bronchioles and fallopian tubules are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squamous",
            "b) Ciliated",
            "c) Glandular",
            "d) Cuboidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ciliated epithelial tissues are present on inner surface of bronchioles and fallopian tubes. These hairs called cilia move back and forth to help move particles out of the body. They contain goblet cells which secrete mucous."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "The site of respiration inside the lungs are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alveoli",
            "b) Diaphragm",
            "c) Bronchi",
            "d) Bronchioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alveoli is tiny air sacs of lungs which allow for rapid gaseous exchange. It is located at the very end of conducting zone and beginning of the respiratory zone in the respiratory system."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The number of gills present in Osteichthyes is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 Pairs",
            "b) 12 pairs",
            "c) 5 pairs",
            "d) 10 pairs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Osteichthyes are referred as bony fish.  They respire through gills. They have 12 pairs of gills present."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "_________ acts as air conditioners.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nasal chambers",
            "b) Larynx",
            "c) Pharynx",
            "d) Lungs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nasal chambers are internal nose.  Each cavity is the continuation of one of the two nostrils. They act as air conditioners."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "What is the function of trachea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filters air we breathe",
            "b) Releases air out of the body",
            "c) Carries air to lungs",
            "d) Exchange of gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Bronchioles are the minute branches into which a bronchus divides. It helps in respiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "The trachea leads to the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulmonary vessels",
            "b) Esophagus",
            "c) Bronchi",
            "d) Bronchioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trachea is also known as windpipe. It is a cartilaginous tube that connects the pharynx and larynx to lungs.  It filters the air. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Hyaline cartilage has a primary function of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protect thyroid",
            "b) Increase the surface area",
            "c) Support trachea",
            "d) Connect conchae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The trachea leads to the bronchi. Trachea extends from larynx and branches into two primary bronchi."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not belong to conducting portion of the respiratory system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nose",
            "b) Pharynx",
            "c) Alveoli",
            "d) Bronchioles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hyaline cartilage is a glass like but translucent cartilage. It contains no nerves or blood vessels and simple in structure. It supports trachea."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "The structure which closes of larynx is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epiglottis",
            "b) Vocal cords",
            "c) Adam’s apple",
            "d) Glottis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Respiratory system is divided into conducting zone and respiration zone. Alveoli belong to respiration zone and not conducting zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Oxygen is carried by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platelets",
            "b) Leucocytes",
            "c) Erythrocytes",
            "d) Monocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During respiration, the oxygen is carried by erythrocytes. It is also known as RBC’s."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "In glycolysis during oxidation electrons are removed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NAD+",
            "b) ATP",
            "c) Molecular oxygen",
            "d) Glyceraldehyde-3-phoshate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glycolysis is a metabolic pathway that converts glucose into pyruvate. During oxidation electrons are removed by NAD+. The energy released in this process is used to form ATP and NADH."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "RQ of fat is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) more than one",
            "c) less than one",
            "d) infinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RQ of fat is less than one. Fats require extra oxygen for the formation of H2O. It is around 0.7. For carbohydrate RQ is one."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "How much percent of CO2 is expired?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7%",
            "b) 32%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During respiration CO2 is exhaled out from the body. 32% of CO2 is expired out."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "When CO2 concentration in blood increased breathing becomes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) shallower and deeper",
            "b) slow and deep",
            "c) faster and deeper",
            "d) no effect on breathing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When CO2 concentration in the blood increased breathing becomes faster and deeper. This happens due to the increase of carbon dioxide and breathing rate becomes faster."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "The oxygen toxicity is related to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blood poisoning",
            "b) Failure of ventilation of lungs",
            "c) Collapsing of the alveolar wall",
            "d) Improper functioning of alveoli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The result of breathing increased partial pressure of oxygen is hyperoxia an excess of oxygen in body tissues. Oxygen toxicity is concern for underwater divers."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "After deep inspiration maximum expiration of lungs is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vital capacity",
            "b) Total lung capacity",
            "c) Inspiratory capacity",
            "d) Functional residual capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hemoglobin carries some of body’s respiratory carbon dioxide as carbaminohemoglobin, in which CO2 is bound to globin protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Pulmonary ventilation movements are due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Costal muscles and diaphragm",
            "b) Diaphragm",
            "c) Wall of lungs",
            "d) Costal muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vital capacity is the maximum amount of air a person can expel from the lungs after a maximum inhalation. A person’s vital capacity can be measured by a wet or regular spirometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "If RQ is 0.6 in a respiratory metabolism it would mean that _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbohydrate is used as respiratory substrate",
            "b) Organic acids are used as respiratory substrate",
            "c) Oxidation of respiratory substrate consumed more O2 than CO2 produced",
            "d) Reaction is anaerobic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Pulmonary ventilation is commonly referred to as breathing. Air flows because of the pressure difference between the atmosphere and the gases inside the lungs. Costal muscles and diaphragm helps pulmonary ventilation."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Partial pressure of oxygen in lungs is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 mm Hg",
            "b) 40 mm Hg",
            "c) 110 mm Hg",
            "d) 100 mm Hg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RQ is respiratory quotient. If RQ is 0.6 then Oxidation of respiratory substrate consumed more O2 than CO2 produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Vital capacity of lung is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TV+IRV+ERV",
            "b) TV+IRV+RV",
            "c) TV+ERV",
            "d) IRV+ERV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a mixture of gases partial pressure is a pressure of that gas if it alone occupied the entire volume of the original mixture at the same temperature. Partial pressure of oxygen in lungs is 100 mm Hg."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Hamburger shift is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bicarbonate shift",
            "b) Chloride shift",
            "c) Potassium shift",
            "d) Sodium shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vital capacity of lung is the sum of tidal volume, inspiratory reserve and expiratory reserve volume. IRV is about 1900-3300ml and ERV is700-1200ml."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Amount of CO2 in expired air is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.04%",
            "b) 0.03%",
            "c) 3.6%",
            "d) 21%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hamburger shift is a process which offers in a cardiovascular system and refers to the exchange of bicarbonate and chloride across the membrane of RBC. It is also known as the chloride shift."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Dead space air in man is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500ml",
            "b) 150ml",
            "c) 250ml",
            "d) 1.5l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average human excels about2.3 pounds of carbon dioxide on a average day. Nearly  4% of carbon dioxide is present in exhaled  air. "
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Total lung capacity is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5000-6000ml",
            "b) 2500-5000ml",
            "c) 4000-5500ml",
            "d) 3000-6000ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dead space is the volume of air that is inhaled that does not take part in gas exchange because it remains in the conducting airways or it reaches alveoli that are not perfused or poorly perfused."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which is true for carbon dioxide concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More in alveolar air than in expired air",
            "b) More in inspired air than in alveolar air",
            "c) More in expired air than in alveolar air",
            "d) More in alveolar air than in inspired air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carbon dioxide concentration is more in alveolar air than in expired air. Carbon dioxide is expelled out from the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "One molecule of hemoglobin carries ___________ molecules of oxygen.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hemoglobin is a protein molecule found in RBC. It is made u of 4 sub units. They are 2 alpha subunits and 2 beta subunits. 1 molecule of hemoglobin can bind to 4oxygen molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Maximum amount of oxygen is exchanged from blood in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arteries of the body",
            "b) Capillaries surrounding the alveoli",
            "c) Left auricle of the heart",
            "d) Arteries of the body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum amount of oxygen is exchanged from blood in Capillaries surrounding the alveoli."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Residual volume is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lesser than tidal volume",
            "b) Greater than vital capacity",
            "c) Greater than inspiratory volume",
            "d) Greater than tidal volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The volume of air still remaining in the lungs after the most forcible expiration possible is called residual air. It is about60-100cubic inches."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Oxygen dissociation curve is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parabolic",
            "b) Hyperbolic",
            "c) Sigmoid",
            "d) Straight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Oxygen dissociation curve is a curve that plots the proportion of hemoglobin in its saturated form in vertical axis against the prevailing oxygen tension on the horizontal axis. Oxygen dissociation curve is sigmoid."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "RQ is one in case of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fatty acids",
            "b) Nucleic acids",
            "c) Organic acids",
            "d) Carbohydrates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RQ of carbohydrate is one. Carbohydrate has the same 2:1 ratio of hydrogen to oxygen as water. Therefore its RQ is one."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Oxygen is mainly transported as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxyhemoglobin",
            "b) Hemo-oxyglobin",
            "c) Hemoglobin",
            "d) Oxynoglobin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Oxyhemoglobin is a bright red substance formed by the combination of hemoglobin with oxygen present in oxygenated blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "____________ ml of oxygen is transported per deciliter of blood.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20ml",
            "b) 40ml",
            "c) 10ml",
            "d) 50ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: About 20ml of oxygen is transported per deciliter of blood. It is transported as Oxyhemoglobin."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the following binds stronger to hemoglobin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Carbon dioxide",
            "c) Carbon monoxide",
            "d) Carbon disulphide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carbon monoxide has high affinity to hemoglobin. It is then followed by carbon dioxide and oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The factor which does not affect the rate of alveolar diffusion is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solubility of gas",
            "b) Reactivity of gas",
            "c) Thickness of membrane",
            "d) Concentration gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  In the alveolar capillaries the diffusion of gases occurs. Oxygen diffuses from alveoli into blood and carbon dioxide from blood to alveoli. Alveolar diffusion does not depend on the reactivity of gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "A large proportion of oxygen is left unused in the human blood even after its uptake by the body tissues. This oxygen ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) helps in releasing more oxygen to tissues",
            "b) raises the pCO2 of blood to 75mm of Hg",
            "c) acts as a reserve during muscular exercise",
            "d) is enough to keep oxyhemoglobin saturation at 96%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some amount of oxygen is left unused in human blood and it acts as a reserve during muscular exercise and preventing muscle cramps.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The urge to inhale in humans results from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rising Pco2",
            "b) Rising O2",
            "c) Falling PCO2",
            "d) Falling PO2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The urge to inhale in humans results from rising of pco2. PcO2 refers to the partial pressure of carbon dioxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Blood analysis of a patient reveals an unusually high quantity of carboxyhemoglobin content. Which of the following conclusion is most likely to be correct? The patient has inhaled polluted air containing high amount of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide",
            "b) Chloroform",
            "c) Carbon monoxide",
            "d) Carbon disulphide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carbon monoxide is colorless odorless and tasteless gas. It is toxic in nature. When blood is associated with carbon monoxide the carboxyhemoglobin content increases in the blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about hemoglobin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present in dissolved state in blood plasma in scorpion",
            "b) Present in dissolved state in blood plasma in earthworm",
            "c) It is a dipeptide and present in RBCs in blood worm",
            "d) It is a dipeptide in mammals and present in RBCs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation:  Earthworm has closed circulatory system. It breaths through moist skin. Their blood contains red hemoglobin which is dissolved in blood plasma to transport oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "RBCs and adipose tissue cells respire anaerobically because they ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) posses very few mitochondria",
            "b) posses carbonic anhydrase",
            "c) posses large amount of energy",
            "d) posses less energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RBCs and adipose tissue cells respire anaerobically. They do not need oxygen to respire as they have very few mitochondria present in them."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Lack of oxygen to the brain can make the person feel ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hyperactive",
            "b) sleepy",
            "c) depressed",
            "d) gasping for air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reduced supply of oxygen to the brain is called cerebral hypoxia. Prolonged hypoxia induces neurons cell death via apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Oxygen diffuses out of blood into tissues because __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen concentration of tissue fluid is lower",
            "b) Oxygen concentration of blood is lower",
            "c) Carbon dioxide concentration of tissue fluid is lower",
            "d) Carbon dioxide concentration of tissue fluid is higher"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxygen diffuses out of the blood into tissues because the concentration of oxygen in tissue fluid is lower. The principle of osmosis is followed here."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Pneumotaxic centre which can moderate the functions of the respiratory rhythm centre is present at ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pons",
            "b) Spinal cord",
            "c) Left hemisphere",
            "d) Thalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pneumotaxic centre is present at pons which is situated in the brain. It helps in the control of respiraton."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the cofactor of carbonic anhydrase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zn",
            "b) Fe",
            "c) Mg",
            "d) Cu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Zinc acts as a cofactor of carbonic anhydrase. Carbonic anhydrase catalyze rapid interconversion of carbon dioxide and water to bicarbonate and protons."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Breathing rate in human is controlled by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medulla oblongata",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Hypothalamus",
            "d) Thalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Breathing rate in human is controlled by Medulla oblongata. It is present in the brainstem. It is an important part of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The primary stimulus for respiratory centre is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide and hydrogen ions",
            "b) Oxygen gas level in blood",
            "c) Oxygen gas level in hemoglobin",
            "d) Conscious feeling for need of oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Humans breathe by negative pressure.T he relative lower pressure compared to the atmosphere is called as negative pressure breathing."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "The respiratory centre sends out nerve impulses to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control center in brain",
            "b) Diaphragm and rib cage",
            "c) Carotid and aortic bodies",
            "d) Muscles of the body that regulate the use of oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The primary stimulus for respiratory centre is Carbon dioxide and hydrogen ions. It stimulates further respiration process."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Emphysema is a ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neural disease",
            "b) Digestive disorder",
            "c) Pulmonary disease",
            "d) Renal disease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The respiratory centre sends out nerve impulses to Diaphragm and rib cage. The diaphragm then expands and relaxes to facilitate breathing."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Congestion of lungs in one of the main symptoms in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heart failure",
            "b) Angina",
            "c) Hypotension",
            "d) Atherosclerosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Emphysema is a chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. It causes shortness of breath."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "SARS is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An acute form of asthma",
            "b) Caused by variant of Corona virus",
            "c) Caused by a variant of Pneumococcus pneumoniae",
            "d) Affects non vegetarians faster"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atherosclerosis is also called as atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. Atherosclerosis is a disease in which the inside of artery narrows due to the buildup of a plaque."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": " Alveoli become enlarged and damaged with reduced surface area in heavy smokers. This condition is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emphysema",
            "b) Silicosis",
            "c) Asthma",
            "d) Bronchitis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SARS stands for Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome. It is caused due to corona virus."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Ascent of high mountains may cause altitude sickness in men. Prime cause for this is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreased proportion of oxygen in the air",
            "b) Decreased partial pressure of oxygen",
            "c) Decreased efficiency of hemoglobin",
            "d) Excess CO2 in blood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: in Emphysema alveoli at the end of the airways in the lungs are damaged.  The sacs become larger and move less oxygen into the blood. Emphysema can be due to genetics also."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Increased asthmatic attacks in certain seasons are related to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low temperatures",
            "b) Inhalation of seasonal pollens",
            "c) Eating fruits preserved in containers",
            "d) Hot and humid environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Altitude sickness is caused due to low availability of oxygen at high altitude. The symptoms are headache, dizziness, nausea, muscle aches."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disorder in which cell division takes place without any control and causes tumor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bronchi cancer",
            "b) Bronchioles cancer",
            "c) Lung cancer",
            "d) Emphysema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Asthma is a condition in which a person’s airways become inflamed narrow and swell and produce extra mucus which makes difficult to breathe. Due to inhaling seasonal pollens the asthma attack may increase."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Uricotelism is found in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Birds reptiles and insects",
            "b) Frogs and toads",
            "c) Mammals and birds",
            "d) Fishes and fresh water protozoans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Elimination of uric acid as main nitrogenous waste material is called uricotelism. It is fond in mammals and birds."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "A terrestrial animal must be able to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excrete large amount of water",
            "b) Actively pump salts through skin",
            "c) Excrete large amount of salts in urine",
            "d) Conserve water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A terrestrial animal must be able to conserve water as it is very necessary to the body. Less amount of water in the body will lead to dehydration."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Animals which excrete urea are known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aminotelism",
            "b) Ureotelism",
            "c) Uricotelism",
            "d) Ammonotelism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Animals which excrete urea are known as Uricotelism. It is seen in birds and diapsids, insects, lizards and snakes. Uric acid is less toxic than ammonia or urea."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Which of the following nephridia are not found in earthworm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Septal nephridia",
            "b) Macronephric nephridia",
            "c) Pharyngeal nephridia",
            "d) Integumentary nephridia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nephridia are a tubule open to the exterior which acts as an organ of excretion or osmoregulation. It removes metabolic wastes from animal’s body. Macronephric nephridia are not found in the earthworm."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Excretory waste of birds and reptiles are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea",
            "b) Uric acid and urea",
            "c) Uric acid",
            "d) Ammonia and uric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Excretory waste of birds and reptiles are ammonia and uric acid. They are Uricotelism animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the only vertebrate osmoconformer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bird",
            "b) Hag fish",
            "c) Rabbit",
            "d) Dog"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Osmoconformers are marine organisms that maintain an internal environment that is osmotic to their external environment. This is seen in hag fish."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Sea gulls excrete salts from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nasal chamber",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Lungs",
            "d) Kidneys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sea gulls excrete salts from the nasal chamber. They have the presence of salt gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Simultaneous movement of two molecules across a membrane in the same direction is known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antiport",
            "b) Symport",
            "c) Uniport",
            "d) Biport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A symporter is an integral membrane protein that is involved in the transport of many different molecules across the cell membrane. There is a simultaneous movement of two molecules across the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "A condition in which body’s internal environment remains nearly constant is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homeostasis",
            "b) Hematoma",
            "c) Hemostasis",
            "d) Hemopoeisis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Homeostasis can be defined as the stable condition of an organism and of its internal environment or as the maintenance or regulation of the stable condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "The presence of arginase confirms that ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea cycle is operating",
            "b) Arginine is being converted to ornithine",
            "c) Urea cycle maybe operating",
            "d) Arginine is being converted to citrulline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Arginine is an alpha amino acid. Arginase is a manganese containing an enzyme, it is the final enzyme of urea cycle. Arginine and water forms ornithine and urea."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Removal of amino group to transform into keto acid is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transamination",
            "b) Deamination",
            "c) Ammonofication",
            "d) Amination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deamination is the removal of an amino group from a molecule. In human deamination takes place in liver however glutamate is deaminated in kidneys."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "In the ornithine cycle which of the following waste is removed from the blood?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea and urine",
            "b) Carbon dioxide and urea",
            "c) Ammonia and carbon dioxide",
            "d) Ammonia and urea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Urea cycle is also known as Ornithine cycle. It converts highly toxic ammonia to urea for excretion. It takes place in the Liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The function of flame cell is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excretion",
            "b) Digestion",
            "c) Respiration",
            "d) Reproduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flame cell is a specialized excretory cell found in freshwater invertebrates. Flame cells function like kidney removing waste materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Urea is directly produced in mammals from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breakdown of arginine",
            "b) Oxidative deamination of proteins",
            "c) Breakdown of ornithine",
            "d) Ammonia released by oxidative deamination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Urea is directly produced in mammals from ammonia released by oxidative deamination. During oxidative deamination amino acid is converted into corresponding keto acid by removal of amine functional group as ammonia and amine functional group."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which blood vessel carries the least amount of urea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulmonary vein",
            "b) Renal artery",
            "c) Renal vein",
            "d) Hepatic portal vein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Renal veins are veins that drain the kidney. They connect the kidney to the inferior vena cava. They carry blood filtered by the kidney. Renal vein carries the least amount of urea."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The amino acid that acts as carrier of ammonia from skeletal muscle to the liver is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alanine",
            "b) Glutamine",
            "c) Methionine",
            "d) Arginine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glutamine is an alpha amino acid used for the biosynthesis of protein. It carries ammonia from skeletal muscle to the liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Which of the following facilitates reabsorption of water by nephron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medulla",
            "b) Cortex",
            "c) Pelvis",
            "d) Loop of nephron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Primary excretory organs are kidneys while the accessory excretory organs are skin lungs and liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Main function of Henle’s loop is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passage of urine",
            "b) Filtration of blood",
            "c) Formation of urine",
            "d) Conservation of urine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Loop of Henle conducts urine within each nephron. It helps in the recovery of water and sodium chloride from the urine. It helps in the conservation of urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "What is the function of ADH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controls sugar level in blood",
            "b) Increases water absorption",
            "c) Decreases water absorption",
            "d) Synthesis of salt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ADH stands for antidieurtic hormone. It tells kidney how much water to conserve and it helps in increase of water absorption. It is secreted by the hypothalamus in the brain and stored in the pituitary gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Glucose is mainly reabsorbed in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Henle’s loop",
            "b) DCT",
            "c) PCT",
            "d) Nephron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glucose is a simple sugar molecule made up of 6 carbon atoms. It circulates in the blood as blood sugar. It is reabsorbed in Henle’s loop which is present in nephron."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Part of nephron impermeable to salt is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DCT",
            "b) Collecting ducts",
            "c) Ascending limb of loop of Henle",
            "d) Descending limb of loop of Henle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Henle’s loop is made up of the descending loop and an ascending loop. Descending limb of loop of Henle is impermeable to salt and doesn’t allow any salt to pass through it."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Podocytes are found in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cortex of nephron",
            "b) Outer wall of Bowman’s capsule",
            "c) Inner wall of Bowman’s capsule",
            "d) Wall of glomerular capillaries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Podocytes are cells in Bowman’s capsule in the kidney that wrap around capillaries of the glomerulus. The Bowman’s capsule filters blood. "
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "PCT is lined with ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cuboidal epithelium",
            "b) Columnar epithelium",
            "c) Simple brush border epithelium",
            "d) Simple Cuboidal epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCT stands for proximal convoluted tubule. Fluid entering the PCT is reabsorbed into peritubular capillaries. PCT is lined with simple cuboidal epithelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the urinary bladder of embryo?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allantois",
            "b) Amnion",
            "c) Chorion",
            "d) Yolk sac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Allantois is a part of placenta. It helps the embryo exchange gases and handles liquid wastes."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Longest loop of Henle is found in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opposum",
            "b) Rhesus monkey",
            "c) Kangaroo rat",
            "d) Cockroach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Longest loop of Henle is found in Kangaroo rat.  It is a small rodent and is native to western North America."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Yellow color of urine is due to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urochrome",
            "b) Urea",
            "c) Bilirubin",
            "d) Uric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Yellow color of urine is due to Urochrome. It is a linear tetrapyrrole compound is degradation products of the cyclic tetrapyrrole heme."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Vasopressin is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synovial fluid",
            "b) Neurotransmitter",
            "c) Antidiuretic hormone",
            "d) Growth regulating substance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vasopressin is called an Antidiuretic hormone (ADH). Vasopressin stimulates reabsorption of water and reduction of urine output."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Juxta glomerular cells of renal cortex synthesize a hormone called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADH",
            "b) Renin",
            "c) Oxytocin",
            "d) Urochrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Juxta glomerular cells are cells in a kidney that synthesize the store and secrete the enzyme rennin. They are smooth muscle cells mainly in the wall of afferent arterioles and some in efferent arterioles that deliver blood to glomerulus."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Liquid which collects in Bowman’s capsule is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water and sulphates",
            "b) Water and glycogen",
            "c) Plasma minus blood proteins",
            "d) Concentrated urine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bowman’s capsule is a cup like a sac at the beginning of tubular component of nephron, it performs first step in filtration of blood to form urine. Liquid which collects in Bowman’s capsule is plasma minus blood proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of renal pyramid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collecting ducts",
            "b) Peritubular capillaries",
            "c) Convoluted tubules",
            "d) Loops of Henle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Renal Pyramid is cone shaped tissues of the kidneys. In human renal medulla is made up of 18-20 of these conical subdivisions. It consists of tubules that transport urine from cortical to calyces in which urine is collected before it passes through the ureter."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Urea synthesis takes place in liver because __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzyme arginase is present in liver only",
            "b) Kidney is smaller than liver",
            "c) ADH is found in liver",
            "d) Urea is present only in liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Urea synthesis takes place in liver because Enzyme arginase is present in liver. Urea cycle takes place to form urea."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Mark the mismatch pair.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Henle’s loop – concentration of urine",
            "b) DCT – Absorption of glucose",
            "c) PCT – Absorption of sodium and potassium ions",
            "d) Bowman’s capsule – Glomerular filtration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DCT is distal convoluted tubule. It is the portion of kidney nephron between the loop of Henle and collecting tubule."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Urea synthesis occurs in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kidney",
            "b) Liver",
            "c) Pancreas",
            "d) Muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Urea synthesis occurs in the liver. Since there is an arginase enzyme present in the liver the synthesis of urea occurs in liver."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Maximum absorption of Na+ and K+ occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loop of Henle",
            "b) Bowman’s capsule",
            "c) DCT",
            "d) PCT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCT is proximal convoluted tubule. It is the convoluted portion of the vertebrate nephron that lies between Bowman’s capsule and the loop of Henle and functions in resorption of sugar, sodium and chloride ions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "In micturition ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urethra relaxes",
            "b) Ureters relax",
            "c) Ureters contract",
            "d) Urethra contracts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Act of passing the urine is called as micturition. During micturition, Urethra relaxes and urine is passed out. "
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Glomerular hydrostatic pressure is present in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubule of kidney",
            "b) Bowman’s capsule",
            "c) Malpighian tubule",
            "d) Glomerulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glomerulus is a tuft of small blood vessels called capillaries located within Bowman’s capsule within the kidney. Blood enters Glomerulus by single arteriole called an afferent arteriole and leaves by an efferent arteriole. "
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Glomerular filtrate contains _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasma without sugars",
            "b) Blood without blood cells and proteins",
            "c) Blood with proteins but without cells",
            "d) Blood without urea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glomerular filtrate contains Blood without blood cells and proteins. It then filtered later. "
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which one is an important constituent of rennin angiotensinogen aldosterone system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macular cells",
            "b) Plasma cells",
            "c) JGA cells",
            "d) Erythropoietin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: JGA cells contain three cell types. They secrete rennin enzyme. "
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Haematuria means _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RBCs in urine",
            "b) WBCs in urine",
            "c) Fats in urine",
            "d) Urea in urine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Haematuria is the presence of red blood cells in the urine. It is detected using a dipstick test. "
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a nitrogenous waste?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Citrulin",
            "b) Allantoin",
            "c) Purines",
            "d) Creatinine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Citrulin is an alpha amino acid. They are important to heart and blood vessel health. They also boost the immune system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Volume of urine is regulated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADH",
            "b) Aldosterone",
            "c) ADH and Aldosterone",
            "d) Aldosterone and testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ADH and Aldosterone are hormones that tell the kidney to put water back in the blood. ADH is also known as vasopressin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "The condition where urea accumulates in blood is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anemia",
            "b) Glycosuria",
            "c) Uremia",
            "d) Acidosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The condition where urea accumulates in blood is Uremia. It is a very rare disorder. It is fewer than 1 million cases per year."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Name the condition when the concentration of ketone increases in urine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turners syndrome",
            "b) Diabetes mellitus",
            "c) Sickle cell anemia",
            "d) Acromegaly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diabetes mellitus is lifelong condition they affect body’s ability to use the energy found in food. Diabetes can cause many complications if left untreated."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "What is glycosuria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low amount of sugar in urine",
            "b) Average amount of sugar in urine",
            "c) Low amount of fat in urine",
            "d) High amount of sugar in urine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glycosuria is a condition characterized by an excess amount of sugar in the urine. It is associated with diabetes or kidney disease. "
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Hemodialysis is done when the person is suffering from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Goiter",
            "b) Diabetes insipidus",
            "c) Diabetes mellitus",
            "d) Uremia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hemodialysis is a process of purifying the blood of a person whose kidneys are not working normally. It is done to treat uremia."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Inflammation of joint due to accumulation of uric acid crystals is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gout",
            "b) Osteoporosis",
            "c) Osteomalacia",
            "d) Myasthenia gravis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Gout is also known as gouty arthritis. It is chracterie3zed by severe pain, redness and tenderness in joints."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "About 90% of kidney stones can pass out through urinary system by drinking _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Juice",
            "c) Sugar drinks",
            "d) Milk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Kidney stones are also known as nephrolothiasis.  A small hard deposit that forms in the kidneys and is often painful when passed."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Which drug is indicated for pain related to acute renal calculi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salicylates",
            "b) NSAIDS",
            "c) Narcotic analgesics",
            "d) Muscle relaxants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Narcotic analgesics are usually needed to relieve the severe pain in renal calculi. NSAIDS are used for anti inflammatory and to treat less severe pain."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Polystyrene sulfonate is used in renal failure to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prevent constipation",
            "b) Reduce serum level",
            "c) Correct acidosis",
            "d) Exchange potassium ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In renal failure, patient becomes hyperkalemic because they can’t excrete potassium in the urine. Polystyrene sulfonate acts to excrete potassium by pulling potassium into the bowls and exchanging it for sodium."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a structural and functional unit of the nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neurons",
            "b) Nephron",
            "c) Brain",
            "d) Spinal cord"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nephron is the microscopic structural and functional unit of kidney. It is made up of a renal corpuscle and renal tubule. "
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Neurons are absent in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat worms",
            "b) Prawns",
            "c) Sponges",
            "d) Leech"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sponges are the member of phylum Porifera. They lack neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Which type of nervous system is present in flatworms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diffused nervous system",
            "b) Ladder type nervous system",
            "c) Circum pharyngeal nervous system",
            "d) Central nervous system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In flat worm nervous system is ladder type. It is formed of primitive nerve rings and nerve cords. The latter is connected by transverse connectives."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "In which of the following can be see diffused nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydra",
            "b) Earthworms",
            "c) Millipedes",
            "d) Frogs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In coelenterates (hydra) diffused nervous system is present. It is formed of epidermal nerve nets in which neuritis of neurons are not differentiated into Dendron and axons."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Alzheimer’s disease is associated with deficiency of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetlycholine",
            "b) Dopamine",
            "c) Glutamic acid",
            "d) Gamma aminobutyric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acetlycholine is an organic chemical that functions in the brain and body of many types of animals as a neurotransmitter. Alzheimer’s disease is a progressive disease that destroys memory and other important mental function. Alzheimer’s disease is associated with deficiency of Acetlycholine."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Nervous system is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An external communication system",
            "b) A slow communication system",
            "c) A rapid communication system",
            "d) A moderate communication system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Nervous system is the network of cells and fibers which transmits nerve impulses between parts of the body. Nervous system is rapid communication system."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Nervous system is divided into _________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nervous system is divided into 2 parts. They are Central nervous system and peripheral nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "_______ controls the voluntary functions of the body.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PNS",
            "b) CNS",
            "c) Neurons",
            "d) ANS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peripheral nervous system controls the voluntary functions of the body. It is formed of long thin whitish threads called nerves which extends between CNS and body parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "How many types of peripheral nerves are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 2 types of peripheral nerves are present. They are afferent nerve fibers and efferent nerve fibers."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Neuroglial cells support and provide nutrition for the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nephron",
            "b) Muscles",
            "c) Glands",
            "d) Neurons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Neuroglial cells form myelin. They protect support and maintain equilibrium in the nervous system. Neuroglia is cells that are not neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Sympathetic nervous system is associated with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fight and flight",
            "b) Fear and rage",
            "c) Hormonal secretions",
            "d) Skeletal muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sympathetic nervous system is a part of the autonomic nervous system. It activates fight or flight response."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Somatic nervous system is made up of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relay neurons",
            "b) Associate neurons",
            "c) Sensory neurons",
            "d) Motor neurons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Somatic nervous system is a part of the peripheral nervous system. The Somatic nervous system consists of afferent nerves and efferent nerves."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "What type of signals are used by the nervous system to communicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical and chemical",
            "b) Electrical and mechanical",
            "c) Mechanical and chemical",
            "d) Only chemical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nervous system communicates using Electrical and chemical. Electrical signals are in the form of pulses and chemical signals are through some hormones or chemicals."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Gaps in myelin sheath are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synapse",
            "b) Myeliniods",
            "c) Nodes of ranvier",
            "d) Myelinoids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Myelin is a fatty white substance that surrounds the axon of some nerve cells. It forms an electrically insulating layer, it is essential for the proper functioning of the nervous system. Gaps in myelin sheath are called as Nodes of ranvier."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Nissl’s granules are present in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RBC",
            "b) WBC",
            "c) Nerve cells",
            "d) Platelets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  A neuron is formed of 2 parts. Neuron is made up of cyton and nerve processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Nodes of Ranvier are found in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myelinated nerve fibers",
            "b) Non myelinated nerve fibers",
            "c) RBC",
            "d) WBC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nissl’s granules are of rough endoplasmic reticulum with rosettes of a free ribosome and are site of protein synthesis. Nissl’s granules are present in nerve cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Myelin sheath is derived from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nerve cells",
            "b) Schwann cells",
            "c) Neuroglial cells",
            "d) Microglia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nodes of Ranvier are found in myelinated nerve fibers. It is a gap in the myelin sheath of a nerve between adjacent Schwann cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the parts of neurons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sympathetic and parasympathetic",
            "b) Dendrite axon and cell body",
            "c) Cortex medulla and sheath",
            "d) Brain spinal cord and vertebral column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Schwann cell is also called a neurilemma cell. It is the cells in peripheral nervous system that produce the myelin sheath around neuronal axons. It was discovered in the 19th century."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding interneuron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has long dendrites and a long axon",
            "b) It has long dendrites and a short axon",
            "c) It has short dendrites and a long or short axon",
            "d) It has short dendrites and a long axon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Neurons are made up of dendrite axon and cell body. It helps in conducting the nerve impulse to different body parts."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disease of myelin sheath?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leprosy",
            "b) Polio",
            "c) Alzheimer",
            "d) Multiple sclerosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Interneuron is relays signals between a sensory neuron and motor neurons. Interneuron has short dendrites and a long or short axon."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Axoplasm is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytoplasm of axon",
            "b) Cytoplasm of dendrite",
            "c) Blood plasma",
            "d) External fluid to axon but inside myelin sheath"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Multiple sclerosis is a disease in which the immune system eats away at the protective coverings of the nerves, It is also called as MS. MS is the disease of myelin sheath."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Which of the following neurotransmitter is not a biogenic amine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dopamine",
            "b) Serotonin",
            "c) Neuropeptides",
            "d) Norepinephrine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Axoplasm is a cytoplasm of the axon. Axoplasm has a different composition of organelles and other materials than that found in the neurons cell body r dendrites."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Polysynaptic membranes are found in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axons",
            "b) Dendrites",
            "c) Myelin sheath",
            "d) Neuron cell bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neuropeptides is not a biogenic amine. It is a protein like molecules used by neurons to communicate with each other. They are neuronal signaling molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "During salutatory conduction, a nerve impulse jumps from one ___________ to another.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axon",
            "b) Synapse",
            "c) Myelin sheath",
            "d) Node of Ranvier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polysynaptic membranes are found in dendrites.  It shows slow depolarization."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Neurons that carry impulses away from the central nervous system are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sensory nerves",
            "b) Extensors",
            "c) Afferent nerves",
            "d) Efferent nerves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Salutatory conduction is a transmission of nerve impulses along myelinated fibers. During salutatory conduction a nerve impulse jumps from one Node of Ranvier to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "A nerve impulse is first received by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axon",
            "b) Soma",
            "c) Synapse",
            "d) Dendrite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Efferent nerves are the neurons that send an impulse from CNS to limbs and organs. Neurons that receives information from sensory organs and transmit input to CNS is called afferent neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "The supporting and nutritive cells found in brains are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oligodendrocytes",
            "b) Astrocytes",
            "c) Microglia",
            "d) Ependymal cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Astrocytes are star shaped glial cells of the central nervous system. They are supporting and nutritive cells found in brains."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not act as a neurotransmitter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetylcholine",
            "b) Epinephrine",
            "c) Norepinephrine",
            "d) Cortisone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cortisone is a pregnane steroid hormone. It is released by the adrenal gland in response to the stress. Cortisone is not a neurotransmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "________ is a quick response to the stimuli that passes the brain.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflex action",
            "b) Voluntary action",
            "c) Knee jerk",
            "d) Receptors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reflex action is an involuntary and instantaneous movement in response to the stimulus. A reflex is made possible by neural pathways called reflex arcs which can act on an impulse before that impulse reaches the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "The cerebellum is located between the cerebrum and the brain stem in the back of the head. It helps in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Breathing and controlling blood pressure",
            "b) Balance and coordination",
            "c) Voluntary movement",
            "d) Speech and hearing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cerebellum receives information from the sensory systems. It helps in balance and coordination."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "The outer covering of the brain is covered with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Axons",
            "b) Nerve cells",
            "c) Pons",
            "d) Dendrites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The outer covering of the brain is called the cerebral cortex. It is covered with nerve cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The brain stem is composed of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brain buds and flowers",
            "b) Spinal cord",
            "c) Axon and vertebra",
            "d) Medulla pons and middle brain tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The brainstem is the posterior part of the brain, adjoin and structurally continuous with the spinal cord. It consists of medulla oblongata pons and midbrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "What connects two hemispheres of the brain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pons",
            "b) Pia matter",
            "c) Corpus callosum",
            "d) Diencephalon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Corpus callosum is a thick band of nerve fibers that divides the cerebral cortex lobes into left and right hemisphere. It connects the left and right sides of the brain for communication between both hemispheres."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "Fluid filled cavity in the brain is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Matter",
            "b) Cavity",
            "c) Meninges",
            "d) Ventricles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fluid filled cavity in the brain is called as ventricles. It contains cerebrospinal fluid. Within each ventricle is a region of choroid plexus."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain controls higher mental activities like reasoning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temporal lobe",
            "b) Frontal lobe",
            "c) Medulla oblongata",
            "d) Cerebellum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frontal lobe is a part of the brain that controls important cognitive skills in humans. It is the largest of four major lobes and is located at the front of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain controls emotion experiences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pia matter",
            "b) Hypothalamus",
            "c) Limbic system",
            "d) Medulla oblongata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Limbic system includes amygdale, hippocampus, thalamus, hypothalamus, basal ganglia and cingulated gyrus. The amygdale is the emotion center of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "The midbrain is also called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medulla",
            "b) Diencephalon",
            "c) Mesencephalon",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mesencephalon is known as midbrain, it is a part of brain stem. It is associated with vision, hearing, motor control, temperature regulation and arousal."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "Mid brain is formed of ___________ parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Midbrain is made up of 2 parts. They are optic lobes and cerebral peduncles. "
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "How many pairs of optic lobes are present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Optic lobes are present on dorsal side. 1 pair of an optic lobe is present. Each divided transversely into upper and larger superior coliculus and lower and smaller inferior colicus."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "The optic lobes in human are represented by the corpora ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bigemina",
            "b) Arenacea",
            "c) Striata",
            "d) Quadrigemina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Optic lobes control visual reflexes. It controls and coordinates the movement of head and eyes. It controls auditory refluxes also."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The 3rd ventricle of brain is situated in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roof of diencephalon",
            "b) Base of telencephalon",
            "c) Roof of metencephalon",
            "d) Base of myelencephalon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corpora Quadrigemina are reflex centers involving vision and hearing. Corpora Quadrigemina are the four colliculi- two inferior and two superior."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which foramen is paired in mammalian brain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foramen of Luschka",
            "b) Foramen of Monro",
            "c) Foramen of Magendie",
            "d) Inter ventricular foramen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ventricles are filled with cerebrospinal fluid. It protects the brain from injury and transport nutrients and waste.  The third ventricle is a narrow cavity that is located between the two halves of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the reduced part of the brain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fore brain",
            "b) Mid brain",
            "c) Hind brain",
            "d) Cerebral cortex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Foramen of Luschka is two of the foramen in ventricular system and link the fourth ventricle to the cerebellopontine cistern."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Brain is situated in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benign",
            "b) Polonium",
            "c) Meninges",
            "d) Cranium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mid brain is a reduced part of the brain. It is composed of tectum and tegmentum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "How much does a normal brain weigh?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.4 kg",
            "b) 85g",
            "c) 3kg",
            "d) 3 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The skull is composed of 2 part.: The cranium and the mandible. Brain is situated in cranium and it protects the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain is concerned with the regulation of body temperatures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medulla oblongata",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Cerebrum",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hypothalamus contains small nuclei with a variety of functions. It links nervous system to the endocrine system via pituitary gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Comprehension of written and spoken words takes place in the region of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wernicke’s area",
            "b) Broca’s area",
            "c) Motor area",
            "d) Association area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wernicke’s area is a region of brain that is important for language development. It is located in the temporal lobe on the left side of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The decoding and interpretation of visual information are carried by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parietal lobe",
            "b) Frontal lobe",
            "c) Occipital lobe",
            "d) Temporal lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Occipital lobe is a visual processing centre of brain containing most of the anatomical region of the visual cortex. It is one of the most major lobes in cerebral cortex."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Arbor vitae are a part of____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cerebrum",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Midbrain",
            "d) Fore brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Arbor vitae serves crucial function in the brain. It is white in appearance and serves to bring sensory and motor information to the cerebellum."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Hind brain contains __________ major parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hind brain contains three major parts. They are Pons, cerebellum and medulla oblongata."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Which function is associated with pons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleep, arousal and the relay of the information",
            "b) Emotion memory and audition",
            "c) Color perception, depth perception",
            "d) Pain perception vision and audition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pons is the major part of the brain. It is involved in the control of breathing and communication between different parts of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which is the largest part of the brain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thalamus",
            "b) Cerebellum",
            "c) Cerebrum",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cerebrum is the largest part of the brain. It consists of cerebral cortex and subcortical structures. It is the uppermost region of the central nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which part of the brain is present on the top portion of medulla in hindbrain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pons",
            "b) Cortex",
            "c) Frontal lobe",
            "d) Parietal lobe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pons is present on the top portion of medulla in the hindbrain. It helps in breathing control."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "In peripheral nervous system the nerves that arise from spinal cord and brain are called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spinal nerves",
            "b) Cranial nerves",
            "c) Temporal nerves",
            "d) Frontal nerves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cranial nerve arises from brain and not from the spinal cord and it pass through a separate aperture in the skill. They are named according to their structure and functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Peripheral nervous system of human as ___________ pairs of spinal nerves.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 31",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Peripheral nervous system of human as 31 pairs of spinal nerves. They have different structure and functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "Preganglionic neurons lie within _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CNS",
            "b) Parasympathetic nervous system",
            "c) Peripheral nervous system",
            "d) Sympathetic nervous system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Preganglionic neurons originate from brain stem or in the spinal cord. Preganglionic neurons lie within central nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Spinal cord and brain are wrapped in protective membranes known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nodes of Ranvier",
            "b) Meninges",
            "c) Axomembranes",
            "d) Mylein sheath"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Meninges are three protective layer of tissues. The Meninges of the brain and spinal cord are continuous being linked through the magnum foramen."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of peripheral nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cranial nerve",
            "b) Ganglion",
            "c) Spinal nerve",
            "d) Spinal cord"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Peripheral nervous system lies outside the brain and spinal cord. Spinal cord is not a part of peripheral nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following cells is found in peripheral nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Schwann cells",
            "b) Microglia",
            "c) Astrocytes",
            "d) Oligodendrocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Schwann cells are found in peripheral nervous system. It is also called as neurilemma cell. It produced myelin sheath."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Bipolar neurons have ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two axons",
            "b) One axon and one dendrite",
            "c) One axon and one presynaptic terminal",
            "d) Two presynaptic terminals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bipolar neurons as two extensions, it is a specialized sensory neurons for the transmission of special senses."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "White matter consists of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuron cell bodies",
            "b) Unmyelinated axons and neuron cell bodies",
            "c) Myelinated axons",
            "d) Unmyelinated dendrites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: White matter consists of Myelinated axons. It is tissue present in the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which one of the following cranial nerves is carrying the nerve fibers originating from the Edinger Westphal nucleus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oculomotor",
            "b) Trochlear",
            "c) Vagus",
            "d) Abducens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oculomotor nerve is the 3rd cranial nerve, it enable most movement of eye and that raise the eyelid."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "The tract of nerve fibers which connects the cerebral hemispheres is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corpus luteum",
            "b) Corpus callosum",
            "c) Corpora quadrigemina",
            "d) Cerebral aqueduct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Corpus callosum allows communication between two hemispheres of the brain.  It is located near the centre of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "5th cranial nerve of frog is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vagus",
            "b) Trigeminal",
            "c) Olfactory",
            "d) Facial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trigeminal nerve is the 5th cranial nerve. It is located within Meckel’s cave and contains cell bodies of incoming sensory nerve fibers."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "In CNS myelinated fibers form the __________ while non myelinated fibers cells form the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grey matter, white matter",
            "b) Ependymal cells, neurosecretory cells",
            "c) White matter, grey matter",
            "d) Neurosecretory cells, Ependymal cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CNS has two kinds of tissues: grey matter and white matter.  White matter is made of axons and grey matter contains cell bodies, dendrites and axons terminals of neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "How many pairs of cranial nerves originate from the brain of a rat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 11",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 12 pairs of cranial nerves originate from the brain of rat. It has specialized functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Injury to the vagus nerve in human is not likely to affect _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Movement of tongue",
            "b) Pancreatic secretion",
            "c) Cardiac movements",
            "d) Gastrointestinal movements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vagus nerve is the 10th cranial nerve. It is the longest cranial nerve. It contains motor and sensory fibers."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which of the following cranial nerve is present in rabbit but absent in frog?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Olfactory",
            "b) Optic",
            "c) Hypoglossal",
            "d) Glossopharyngeal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hypoglossal nerve is the 12th cranial nerve. It innervates all the extrinsic and intrinsic muscles of the tongues."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of the following nerve is purely motor nerve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trigeminal",
            "b) Vagus",
            "c) Facial",
            "d) Abducens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Abducens nerve is a nerve that controls movements of the lateral rectus muscle in humans. it is a 6th cranial nerve."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Skeletal muscles are controlled by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Somatic nerves",
            "b) Autonomic nerves",
            "c) Parasympathetic nerves",
            "d) Sympathetic nerves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Somatic nerves are a part of the peripheral nervous system. It is associated with voluntary movement of the body via skeletal muscles."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "The thin and convoluted outer layer of gray matter that covers the cerebral hemisphere is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meninges",
            "b) Thalamus",
            "c) Medulla oblongata",
            "d) Cerebral cortex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cerebral cortex is the largest region of the cerebrum. It plays a key role in memory, attention, perception, awareness, thoughts, language etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which part of the nervous system controls reflex actions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vermis",
            "b) Pons",
            "c) Spinal cord",
            "d) Corpus callosum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corpus callosum is present in the cerebral cortex. It is about 10cm long. Reflex actions are controlled by Corpus callosum."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "The electrical potential difference between outside and inside of a nerve axon before excitation is known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resting potential",
            "b) Action potential",
            "c) Spike potential",
            "d) Reaction potential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resting potential of a neuron is about -70 Milli volts. At rest, there are relatively more sodium ions outside the neurons and more potassium ions inside the neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which set of ions are necessary for the nerve impulse conduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium and potassium ions",
            "b) Sodium and calcium ions",
            "c) Calcium and potassium ions",
            "d) Sodium and magnesium ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sodium and potassium ions are necessary for nerve impulse conduction. The process of moving sodium and potassium ions across the cell membrane is an active transport process involving the hydrolysis of ATP to provide the necessary energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Reflex arc consists of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motor nerve",
            "b) Sensory nerve",
            "c) Both motor and sensory nerve",
            "d) Mixed nerve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reflex arc is a neural pathway that controls the reflux. It includes sensory nerve and a motor nerve with a synapse between."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Dorsal root of spinal nerves contains  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effectors neurons",
            "b) Stimulators",
            "c) Detector neurons",
            "d) Receptor neurons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dorsal root of spinal nerve emerges from the spinal cord. Dorsal root of spinal nerves contains receptor neurons. Receptors neurons receive the stimuli and send the signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Reflex action is simplest form of response in  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple animals",
            "b) Higher animals",
            "c) Smaller animals",
            "d) Lowest animals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Reflex action is an involuntary response to the stimulus. Reflex action is the simplest form of response in higher animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not involved in voluntary actions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Math neuron",
            "b) Relay neuron",
            "c) Sensory neuron",
            "d) Synapse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sensory neuron is nerve cells within the nervous system responsible for converting external stimuli into internal electrical impulses. It is also known as afferent neurons."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Nerve impulse is conducted toward the cell body through ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motor neurons",
            "b) Nerve fibers",
            "c) Axon",
            "d) Dendrons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nerve impulse is conducted towards the cell body through dendrons. Dendron is a postsynaptic branch of neuron that carries postsynaptic potentials towards the cell body."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Stimuli are also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receptors",
            "b) Nerve impulse",
            "c) Biosensors",
            "d) Detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stimuli is something that can elicit or evoke a physiological response in a cell, tissue or an organism. It can be internal or external. Stimuli are also known as Receptors."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Blinking of an eye is an example of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spinal reflux",
            "b) Cranial refluxes",
            "c) Relay neurons",
            "d) Spinal refluxes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cranial refluxes are mediated by pathways in the cranial nerves and brain. Blinking and swallowing are cranial refluxes."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Autonomic nervous system affects ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflex actions",
            "b) Sensory organs",
            "c) Visceral organs",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Autonomic nervous system is a control system that acts largely unconsciously and regulates bodily function. It affects Visceral organs."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of the autonomic nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peristalsis of intestine",
            "b) Swallowing",
            "c) Movement of eyes",
            "d) Knee jerk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peristalsis of intestine is an example of the autonomic nervous system. Movement in the intestine so that the food can move forward is known as peristalsis."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which of the following ganglia is not a collateral ganglion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Celiac",
            "b) Superior mesenteric",
            "c) Inferior mesenteric",
            "d) Cervical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cervical ganglia is a paravertebral ganglia. It has three paravertebral ganglia. Collateral ganglion is ganglia which lie between paravertebral ganglia and target organ."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Catecholamine is derived from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetylcholine",
            "b) Tyrosine",
            "c) Tryptophan",
            "d) Epinephrine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Catecholamine is derived from tyrosine. Catecholamine is an organic compound that has a catechol and a side chain amine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "The brain area that most directly controls the activity of the autonomic nervous system is the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary gland",
            "b) Medulla oblongata",
            "c) Cerebellum",
            "d) Hypothalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Medulla oblongata is located in the brain stem. It controls the activity of the autonomic nervous system.  It is the lowest part of the brain."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Targets of the autonomic nervous system include all of the following except __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cardiac muscle",
            "b) Endocrine glands",
            "c) Skeletal muscle",
            "d) Exocrine glands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Skeletal muscle is formed of striated muscle tissue. It is under voluntary control of the somatic nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "Nurilenma provides nourishment for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nerve fibers",
            "b) Nerve impulse",
            "c) Effectors",
            "d) Receptors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nurilenma provides nourishment for nerve fibers. These are benign, encapsulated tumors of the nerve sheath. They are derived from the neural crest."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Parasympathetic nerve arises from which region of the nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cranio sacral",
            "b) Lumbar",
            "c) Cervical",
            "d) Thoracolumbar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parasympathetic nerve arises from Cranio sacral region of the nervous system. Parasympathetic nervous system nerves arise from the central nervous system."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which of the following is released by Parasympathetic nervous system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serotonin",
            "b) Acetylcholine",
            "c) Epinephrine",
            "d) Nor epinephrine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Acetylcholine is released by Parasympathetic nervous system. Acetylcholine is a neurotransmitter. It is released by nerve cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about parasympathetic neurons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The nerve fibers are contained in spinal nerves",
            "b) The synapse in terminal ganglia either next to or within the organs innervated",
            "c) They originate in thoracic and lumbar regions of the spinal cord",
            "d) Postganglionic fibers are usually longer than those of sympathetic neurons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ganglions is a structure containing a number of nerve cell bodies typically linked by synapse and often forming a swelling on a nerve fiber."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Which of the following cranial nerves does not contain preganglionic parasympathetic fibers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optic II",
            "b) Glossopharyngeal IX",
            "c) Facial VII",
            "d) Oculomotor III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Optic II nerve does not contain preganglionic parasympathetic fibers. Optic II nerve is the second cranial nerve. It transmits all visual information."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Which system is not regulated by a centre in the medulla oblongata?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cardiovascular system",
            "b) The respiratory system",
            "c) The immune system",
            "d) The digestive system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The organs and the processes of the body that provide resistance to infection and toxins. The immune system is not regulated by a centre in the medulla oblongata. Thymus, bone marrow and lymph nodes include an immune system."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Nerve fibers are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nuclear processes",
            "b) Protoplasmic processes",
            "c) Endoplasmic process",
            "d) Cytoplasmic processes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nerve provides a common pathway for the electrochemical nerve impulses that are transmitted along each of the axons to peripheral organs."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "The inner most layer of human eye is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sclera",
            "b) Cornea",
            "c) Choroid",
            "d) Retina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Retina is the inner most layer of human eye. It is light sensitive layer. The retina converts the light rays into impulses that travel through the optic nerve to brain where they are interpreted as the image we see."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Color blindness is due to defect in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cones",
            "b) Rods",
            "c) Rods and cons",
            "d) Rhodopsin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Color blindness is a reduced ability to distinguish between certain colors. It is a very common defect. Color blindness is due to defect in cones."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "The purplish red pigment rhodopsin contained in rods type of photoreceptor cell is a derivative of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin B1",
            "b) Vitamin C",
            "c) Vitamin D",
            "d) Vitamin A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rhodopsin is derivative of vitamin A. Vitamin A includes retinol, retinal and carotenoids. Rhodopsin is a light sensitive receptor protein involved in visual photo transduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Color perception in man is due to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodopsin present in rod cells",
            "b) Iodopsin present in cone cells",
            "c) Rhodopsin present in cone cells",
            "d) Iodopsin present in rod cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iodopsin is present in cone cells. Iodopsin consists of the protein component and a bound chromophore, retinal."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Organ of Corti helps in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Balancing",
            "b) Maintaining equilibrium",
            "c) Hearing",
            "d) Formation of wax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Organ of Corti helps in hearing. It is a spiral organ and receptor organ for hearing and is located in cochlea."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which is thickened to form organ of Corti?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basilar membrane",
            "b) Reissner’s membrane",
            "c) Tectorail membrane",
            "d) Epithelial cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basilar membrane within cochlea of inner ear is a stiff structural element that separates two liquid filled tubes that run along the coil of cochlea. Basilar membrane is thickened to form the organ of Corti."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "A person goes to ophthalmologist. He has a problem of reading books because he is not able to contract his ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iris",
            "b) Suspensory ligament",
            "c) Pupil",
            "d) Ciliary muscles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ciliary muscles are a ring of smooth muscle in the eyes. It controls accommodation for viewing objects at varying distances and regulates a flow of aqueous humour into Sclemm’s canal."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "Eustachian tube connects ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pharynx with middle ear",
            "b) Middle ear with external ear",
            "c) Middle ear with external ear",
            "d) External ear with internal ear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eustachian tube connects Pharynx with the middle ear. It controls pressure within the middle ear, making it equal with the air pressure outside the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "Which of the following animal produces high frequency sound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monkey",
            "b) Bat",
            "c) Butterfly",
            "d) Squirrel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bat produces high frequency sound. The frequency of bat sound is much higher than humans so humans can’t hear it. Bats are echolocation producing animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Aqueous and vitreous humours are divided by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lens",
            "b) Iris",
            "c) Retina",
            "d) Optic nerve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aqueous humours fill both anterior and posterior chambers of the eye. Vitreous humours are a clear gelatinous mass found in rear part of eyeball. Aqueous and vitreous humours are divided by lens."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Organ of Ruffini is sensitive to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cold",
            "b) Heat",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Touch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Organ of Ruffini is sensitive to heat. It is also referred as bulbus or ruffini corpuscles."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Which of the following prevents internal reflection of light inside the eye?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cornea",
            "b) Sclera",
            "c) Choroid",
            "d) Retina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Choroid is a vascular layer of the eye containing connective tissue and lying between retina and sclera. Choroid prevents internal reflection of light inside the eye."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "In which of the following only cone cells are found?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fovea centralis",
            "b) Retina",
            "c) Fossa ovalis",
            "d) Blind spot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Fovea centralis is a small central it composed of closely packed cones in the eye. It is located in the centre of the macula lutea of the retina."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Ora serrata is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present in ear",
            "b) Oral cavity of protochordates",
            "c) Gland present in oral cavity",
            "d) A part of third wall in retina of eye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ora serrata is the serrated junction between the retina and the ciliary body. Ora serrata is part of third wall in retina of eye."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Sense of smell is perceived by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary",
            "b) Hypothalamus",
            "c) Olfactory lobe",
            "d) Cerebrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sense of smell is perceived by Olfactory lobe. It is seen in the cerebrum. It contains the ending of olfactory nerves."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "FSH and LH are collectively known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neurohomones",
            "b) Antistress hormones",
            "c) Gonadotrophic hormone",
            "d) Emergency hormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FSH and LH are collectively known as gonadotrophic hormone. It is secreted by the anterior pituitary gland. It acts on gonads controlling gamete and sex hormone production."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a heredity disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hemophilia",
            "b) Cretinism",
            "c) Cystic fibrosis",
            "d) Thalassemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cretinism is a condition of severely stunted physical and mental growth owing to untreated deficiency of thyroid hormone. Cretinism is not a heredity disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is responsible for ovulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LH",
            "b) FSH",
            "c) Progesterone",
            "d) Testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LH is a hormone produced by gonadotrophic cells in the anterior pituitary gland. In females, an acute rise in LH triggers ovulation and development of corpus luteum."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a part of endocrine gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pars radiata",
            "b) Brunner’s gland",
            "c) Juxtaglomerulus",
            "d) Crypts of Lieberkuhn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Juxtaglomerulus is a part of endocrine gland. It consists of three types of cells. They are present in kidneys."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Who is the father of endocrinology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R H Whittakar",
            "b) Pasteur",
            "c) Thomas Addison",
            "d) Einthoven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thomas Addison is the father of endocrinology. In 1921 insulin was discovered and endocrinology became popular."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Stress hormone is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxytocin",
            "b) Adrenaline",
            "c) Vasopressin",
            "d) Sex hormone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adrenaline is a stress hormone. It is produced by adrenal glands and certain neurons. It is also known as epinephrine."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for sleep cycle movements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melatonin",
            "b) Dopamine",
            "c) Serotin",
            "d) Adrenaline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Melatonin is produced by a pineal gland and it regulates sleep and wakefulness."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Which part of the ovary of mammals acts as endocrine gland after copulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stroma",
            "b) Graaffian follicle",
            "c) Vitelline membrane",
            "d) Germinal epithelium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Graaffian follicle acts as endocrine gland after copulation. It contains a liquid filled cavity and ruptures during ovulation to release an egg."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is a modified amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progesterone",
            "b) Estrogen",
            "c) Prostaglandins",
            "d) Epinephrine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Epinephrine is a modified amino acid. It is a neurotransmitter. It increases cardiac output and raises glucose level in blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Ecdysone is secreted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insects",
            "b) Nematodes’",
            "c) Polychaetes",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ecdysone is secreted by insects. It is a steroid hormone that controls moulting in insects and in arthropods."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "Which hormone produces a calorigenic effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) Thyroxine",
            "c) Insulin",
            "d) Adrenaline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FSH hormone produces a calorigenic effect. FSH is produced by an anterior pituitary gland and regulates development, growth, pubertal maturation and reproductive process of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is a steroid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epinephrine",
            "b) Thyroxine",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Prostaglandins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Steroid is an organic compound with four rings arranged in a specific molecular configuration. Steroid included sex hormones, dietary lipid etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Deficiency of vasopressin causes ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Goitre",
            "b) Diabetes mellitus",
            "c) Myxoedema",
            "d) Diabetes insipidus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vasopressin is an antidiuretic hormone. It is synthesized by the hypothalamus. Deficiency of vasopressin causes Diabetes insipidus."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "Which of the following diseases not related to thyroid glands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myxoedema",
            "b) Cretinism",
            "c) Acromegaly",
            "d) Goitre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acromegaly is a disorder in adults in which the pituitary gland produces too much growth hormone. It requires a medical diagnosis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Grave’s disease is due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperactivity of thyroid gland",
            "b) Hyperactivity of adrenal medulla",
            "c) Hyperactivity of adrenal cortex",
            "d) Hyperactivity of islets of langerhans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Grave’s disease is also called as basedows disease. It results in the overproduction of thyroid hormones. It requires a medical diagnosis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Hypothyroidism causes in an adult ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Obesity",
            "b) Diabetes",
            "c) Cretinism",
            "d) Myxoedema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hypothyroidism is also called as underactive thyroid. A condition in which the thyroid gland does not produce enough thyroid hormone.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Endostyle of Amphioxus is similar to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parathyroid",
            "b) Thymus",
            "c) Thyroid",
            "d) Thalamus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thyroid gland is an endocrine gland. It is found at the front of the neck below Adam’s apple. "
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the symptom of hypothyroiditis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accumulation of urea in blood",
            "b) Edema",
            "c) Mental retardation",
            "d) Lethargy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hypothyroiditis symptoms include delayed puberty, hair loss, constipation, enlarged thyroid, high cholesterol. It does not include accumulation of urea in the blood. "
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Which type of epithelium is present in thyroid follicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Squamous",
            "b) Cuboidal",
            "c) Columnar",
            "d) Transitional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cuboidal epithelium is present in thyroid follicles. Follicular cells are responsible for the reduction and secretion of thyroid hormones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Metamorphosis in frog is controlled by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Growth hormone",
            "b) Insulin",
            "c) Vasopressin",
            "d) Thyroxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Metamorphosis is a biological process by which an animal physically develops after birth involving abrupt change in animals’ body structure through cell growth and differentiation. Metamorphosis in frog is controlled by thyroxin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "Endemic goiter is a state of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased thyroid function",
            "b) Decreased thyroid function",
            "c) Moderate thyroid function",
            "d) Normal thyroid function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Endemic goiter is associated with dietary iodine deficiency. It is due to decreased thyroid function. "
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "How many lobes are present in the thyroid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are two lobes present in the thyroid. Thyroid is a butterfly shaped gland. "
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Which cells produce calcitonin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C cells",
            "b) B cells",
            "c) A cells",
            "d) T cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C cells are also known as parafollicular cells. These cells are large and have a pale stain. C cells produce calcitonin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Development of thyroid gland occurs in which week of intrauterine life?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12th week",
            "b) 15th week",
            "c) 4th week",
            "d) 7th week"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Development of thyroid gland occurs in 4th week of intrauterine life. It is derived from ectoderm. "
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "The left and right lobes are joined by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Levator",
            "b) Isthmus",
            "c) Pyramidal lobe",
            "d) Valve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Papillary carcinoma is thyroid cancer. It appears as an irregular solid or cystic mass or nodule in a normal thyroid parenchyma. "
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "Enlargement of the thyroid is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diabetes",
            "b) Goitre",
            "c) Cretinism",
            "d) Myxoedema"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The left and right lobes are joined by Isthmus. Isthmus is made up of tissue. "
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "The four small glands in the thyroid gland are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parathyroid gland",
            "b) Adrenal gland",
            "c) Pineal gland",
            "d) Endocrine and exocrine gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enlargement of the thyroid is called as Goitre. It is a noncancerous enlargement. It is caused due to iodine deficiency. "
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Adrenaline and non adrenaline are hormones and act as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neurotransmitters",
            "b) Energy storing substance",
            "c) Food storage material",
            "d) Energy producing agents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adrenaline and non adrenaline are hormones and act as Neurotransmitters. They are secreted by adrenaline glands. They are also chemical messengers."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Glomerular area of adrenal cortex is responsible for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water and electrolyte balance",
            "b) Steroid hormone secretion",
            "c) Blood pressure",
            "d) Carbohydrate metabolism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adrenal cortex is the outer part of the gland. It produces hormones. Glomerular area of adrenal cortex is responsible for water and electrolyte balance."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is known as flight and fight hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thyroxin",
            "b) Adrenaline",
            "c) ADH",
            "d) Oxytocin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adrenaline is known as flight and fight hormone. It is produced by adrenal glands, during stressful conditions adrenaline is released into the blood sending impulses to organs to create a specific response."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "ADH acts on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loop of Henle",
            "b) Collecting ducts of testes",
            "c) Collecting tubules of kidneys",
            "d) PCT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ADH is also known as vasopressin. It is a peptide prohormone.it acts on collecting tubules of kidneys."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Adrenal gland is derived from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endoderm",
            "b) Mesoderm",
            "c) Ectoderm",
            "d) Ectoderm and mesoderm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adrenal gland is derived from Ectoderm and mesoderm. They are endocrine glands. They are found above the kidneys."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Adrenaline hormone increases ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blood pressure",
            "b) Blood glucose level",
            "c) Arteriosclerosis",
            "d) Oxygen uptake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adrenaline hormone increases blood pressure. It sends a message in the form of an impulse to different parts of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "ADH deficiency shows ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polydipsia",
            "b) Polyuria",
            "c) Glycosuria",
            "d) Polydipsia and Polyuria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ADH deficiency shows Polydipsia and Polyuria. Polydipsia is intense thirst despite drinking plenty of fluids. Polyuria is passing abnormally large amounts of urine."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "The adrenal gland is located ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the peritoneal cavity",
            "b) On the kidneys",
            "c) Lateral to the liver",
            "d) In the abdominal cavity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The adrenal gland is located on top of each kidney. Each adrenal gland is comprised of two distinct structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "What is the name of the cells producing the hormone in adrenal medulla?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F cells",
            "b) Chief cells",
            "c) Principal cells",
            "d) Chromaffin cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chromaffin cells are present in the adrenal medulla; they are innervated by the splanchnic nerve and secret adrenaline."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Which is not the function of cortisol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases glucose uptake by muscles",
            "b) Convert amino acids to glucose",
            "c) Converts fat to fatty acids",
            "d) Increases blood sugar level in response to stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cortisol is a steroid hormone, it is called a stress hormone.it helps in metabolism and immune response."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Low level of adrenal cortex hormones results in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addison diseases",
            "b) Cushing syndrome",
            "c) Goiters",
            "d) Tetany"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: Addison disease is also called as hypocortisolism. It is a disorder in which adrenal gland doesn’t produce enough hormones. Insufficient amount of cortisol and aldosterone is produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Adrenal gland consists of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ACTH and BCTH",
            "b) Inner and outer layer of kidney",
            "c) Inner medulla and outer cortex",
            "d) Lower adrenal and upper adrenal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adrenal gland consists of Inner and outer layer of the kidney. The outer part is called adrenal cortex and inner region is known as adrenal medulla."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "The adrenal ___________ secretes small amount of both sex hormones.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medulla",
            "b) Cortex",
            "c) Accessory gland",
            "d) Cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adrenal cortex is an outer part of the gland. It produces vital hormones like cortisol and aldosterone. It also secretes a small amount of sex hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "ACTH controls the secretion of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cortisol",
            "b) Aldosterone",
            "c) Epinephrine",
            "d) Testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ACTH is adrenocorticitropic hormone. It is a polypeptide hormone produced and secreted by pituitary gland. ACTH controls the secretion of cortisol."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "Low level of adrenal cortex hormones result in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Goitre",
            "b) Diabetes",
            "c) Addison disease",
            "d) Cushing syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Low level of adrenal cortex hormones result in Addison disease. It is fewer than 1 million cases per year in India. "
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "What connects hypothalamus to the pituitary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infundibulam",
            "b) Corpus callosum",
            "c) Anterior",
            "d) Cerebral cortex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Infundibulam is a funnel shaped structure. It is the connection between hypothalamus and posterior pituitary."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Hypothalamus is a part of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Midbrain",
            "b) Forebrain",
            "c) Hind brain",
            "d) Future brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hypothalamus is the part of the brain that contains a number of small nuclei with a variety of function. It links the nervous system to endocrine system."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Displacement of the set point in the hypothalamus is due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pathogens",
            "b) Effectors",
            "c) Receptors",
            "d) Pyrogens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Displacement of the set point in the hypothalamus is due to Pyrogens. Pyrogens are a low molecular weight protein produced in response to stimulation by exogenous pyrogens and released into the circulation system."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Hormones produced in hypothalamus are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxytocin and estrogen",
            "b) Oxytocin and testosterone",
            "c) Oxytocin and Antidiuretic hormone",
            "d) Oxytocin and thyroxine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hormones produced in hypothalamus are Oxytocin and Antidiuretic hormone. They have their specific function and specific target site."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "Which of the following events could be a result of damage to hypothalamus portal system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreased secretion of ADH",
            "b) Decreased secretion oxytocin",
            "c) Decreased secretion TSH",
            "d) Decreased secretion PTH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Secretion of Thyroid stimulation hormone will be decreased if there is any damage in hypothalamus region."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Secretion of many anterior pituitary hormones are controlled by other hormones from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pancreatic lobes",
            "b) Adrenal gland",
            "c) Hypothalamus",
            "d) Thyroid gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hypothalamus controls the secretion of anterior pituitary hormones. It is present in the forebrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Which of the following consists of nerve tissue and down growth from hypothalamus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Posterior pituitary",
            "b) Anterior pituitary",
            "c) Thymus",
            "d) Adrenal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Posterior pituitary is the posterior lobe of pituitary gland. It is a collection of axonal projections from hypothalamus that terminate behind anterior pituitary."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "If hypothalamus fails to secrete GnRH the effect would be _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypersecretion of oxytocin",
            "b) Hypersecretion of prolactin",
            "c) Hypersecretion of pituitary gonadotropins",
            "d) Hyposecretion of pituitary gonadotropins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GnRH is gonadotropin releasing hormone. They are released in gonads. If hypothalamus fails to secrete GnRH the effect would be Hyposecretion of pituitary gonadotropins."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Osmoreceptors in hypothalamus are involved in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secretion of GH",
            "b) Secretion of ADH",
            "c) Secretion of ACTH",
            "d) Secretion of Aldosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Osmoreceptors are sensory receptor found in hypothalamus. It detects changes in osmotic pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "GnRH directly stimulates release of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) Progesterone",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Thyrocalcitonin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GnRH directly stimulates the release of FSH.  It regulates the development, growth, pubertal maturation, and reproductive processes of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "FSH is produced by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thyroid gland",
            "b) Anterior pituitary gland",
            "c) Posterior pituitary gland",
            "d) Gonads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FSH is produced by anterior pituitary gland. FSH is Follicle stimulating hormone. Anterior pituitary gland secretes 6 hormones. It releases hormones into blood stream."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is produced by a pituitary gland in both males and females but functional only in a female?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relaxin",
            "b) Prolactin",
            "c) Vasopressin",
            "d) Somatotrophic hormones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prolactin is produced by a pituitary gland in both males and females but functional only in a female. It is also known as luteotropic hormone. It enables females to produce milk."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an accumulation and releasing centre of neurohormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypothalamus",
            "b) Anterior lobe of pituitary gland",
            "c) Posterior pituitary gland",
            "d) Intermediate lobe of pituitary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Posterior pituitary gland is a part of the endocrine system. Hormones secreted by Posterior pituitary gland include oxytocin and ADH."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "MSH is produced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anterior lobe of pituitary gland",
            "b) Posterior pituitary gland",
            "c) Parathyroid",
            "d) Pars intermedia of pituitary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MSH is produced by Pars intermedia of the pituitary. MSH is melanocyte stimulating hormone. It is a peptide hormones and neuropeptides."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Sertoli cells are regulated by pituitary hormone known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) LH",
            "c) GH",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sertoli cells are regulated by pituitary hormone known as FSH. Sertoli cells are found in gonads of male. "
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Trophic hormones are formed by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anterior pituitary",
            "b) Middle pituitary",
            "c) Thyroid",
            "d) Posterior pituitary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trophic hormones are a hormone that stimulates an endocrine gland to grow and secrete its hormones, in humans tropic hormones are secreted by the Anterior pituitary."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Gigantism and acromegaly are due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperthyroidism",
            "b) Hyperpituitarism",
            "c) Hypopituitarism",
            "d) Hypothyroidism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gigantism and acromegaly are due to Hyperpituitarism. Hyperpituitarism is a condition due to primary hypersecretion of pituitary hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which of the following gland is regarded as a master gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adrenal gland",
            "b) Hypothalamus",
            "c) Pituitary gland",
            "d) Thyroid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pituitary gland is regarded as the master gland. It is found at the base of the brain. It produces many hormones that travel throughout the body directing certain processes or stimulating other glands to produce other hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "What is Wermer’s syndrome known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Men type 1",
            "b) Men type 2",
            "c) Men type 3",
            "d) Men type 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wermer’s syndrome known as Men type 1. It is part of disorders the multiple endocrine neoplasias that affect the endocrine system through the development of neoplastic lesions in the pituitary, parathyroid gland and pancreas."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "Which hormone causes the contraction of labor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prolactin",
            "b) Estrogen",
            "c) Progesterone",
            "d) Oxytocin"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Pars distalis, Pars tuberalis, Pars intermedia belongs to the anterior pituitary. It secretes 6 hormones. anterior pituitary is also known as adenohypophysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "What is Sheeshan’s syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pituitary adenoma is hemorrhagic and necrotic",
            "b) Pituitary gland is infected with virus",
            "c) Pituitary gland is infected with Bacteria",
            "d) It is the malignancy of the pituitary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oxytocin is a peptide hormone and neuropeptide. It is produced by paraventricular nucleus of hypothalamus and released by the posterior pituitary."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not released by anterior pituitary gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prolactin",
            "b) ADH",
            "c) FSH",
            "d) TSH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sheeshan’s syndrome is also known as postpartum pituitary gland necrosis. It is caused by ischemic necrosis due to blood loss and hypovolemic shock during and after childbirth."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "What is Carney complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sex linked disorder",
            "b) Autosomal recessive disorder",
            "c) Autosomal dominant disorder",
            "d) Disorder kidney"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ADH is not released by the anterior pituitary gland. Hormones released by anterior pituitary gland are GH, PRL, FSH, LH, ACTH and TSH."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "What is the treatment of GH-oma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Growth hormone analogues",
            "b) Somatostatin analogues",
            "c) Somatostatin inhibitors",
            "d) Surgery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Carney syndrome is an Autosomal dominant disorder. It is associated with spotty pigmentation of the skin, endocrine and non endocrine tumors."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "Hassall’s corpuscles are found in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adrenalin gland",
            "b) Spleen",
            "c) Thymus",
            "d) Parathyroid gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hassall’s corpuscles are found in the medulla of thymus. It is formed from eosinophillic type IV epithelial reticular cells arranged concentrically."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "Damage to thymus in a child may lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loss of cell mediated immunity",
            "b) Loss of antibody mediated immunity",
            "c) Reduction in stem cell production",
            "d) Reduction in hemoglobin content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell mediated immunity is an immune response that does not involve antibodies but involves activation of phagocytes, antigen-specific cytotoxic T-lymphocytes and releases various cytokines in response to antigen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "Mammalian thymus is mainly associated with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secretion of thyrotrophin",
            "b) Regulation of body growth",
            "c) Regulation of body temperature",
            "d) Immunological functions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thymus is located in the neck. It produces T Lymphocytes for the immune system. Mammalian thymus is mainly associated with Immunological functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Thymus aids differentiation of ___________ cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red blood",
            "b) B",
            "c) T",
            "d) Cancerous"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer:  b\nExplanation: Thymus size decreases with aging. Human thymus becomes much smaller at the approach of puberty."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Thymus, spleen, tonsils and adenoids produces _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phagocytes",
            "b) Lymphocytes",
            "c) Erythrocytes",
            "d) Rhombocytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thymus aids differentiation of T cells. T cells are the type of lymphocyte that plays a central role in cell mediated immunity. T cells have a receptor on the cell surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a primary lymphoid tissue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymus",
            "b) Spleen",
            "c) Bone marrow",
            "d) Foetal liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lymphocytes are type of white blood cells. They work to fight illness and disease. There are two types of Lymphocytes and they are B Lymphocytes and T Lymphocytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "Which of these cell surface markers is unique to T cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CD3",
            "b) CD15",
            "c) CD45",
            "d) CD83"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spleen acts as a filter for blood as a part of immune system. Spleen is not a primary lymphoid tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "The pineal gland secretes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSH",
            "b) Melatonin",
            "c) Melanin",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CD3 T cell co receptor helps to activate cytotoxic T cell and also T helper cell. CD3 is unique to T cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an effect of pineal body secretion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inhibition of GnRH",
            "b) Inhibition of reproductive functions",
            "c) Help regulation of sleep cycle",
            "d) Stimulation of appetite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pineal gland secretes Melatonin. It regulates sleep and wakefulness. "
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about melanin secretion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More melatonin is secreted at night and day.",
            "b) More melatonin is secreted at day",
            "c) Melatonin can help regulate sleep cycles",
            "d) Melatonin is secreted at noon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pineal body secretion does not show any effect of appetite. Mainly it secretes Melatonin."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an endocrine gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pituitary gland",
            "b) Pineal gland",
            "c) Sebaceous gland",
            "d) Adrenal gland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Melatonin is produced by various tissues in the body, although the major source is the pineal gland. The production and release of Melatonin occur with a clear daily rhythm with peak levels occurring at night."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "Which is the common problem with the endocrine system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bad gas",
            "b) Diabetes",
            "c) Hemophilia",
            "d) Lung cancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sebaceous gland is a small gland that secretes a lubricating oily matter into hair follicles to lubricate skin and hair. Sebaceous gland is not an endocrine gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Gonadotropic hormone is released by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gonads",
            "b) Germ layers",
            "c) Neurohypophysis",
            "d) Adenohypophysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adenohypophysis is also known as anterior pituitary.  Adenohypophysis secretes gonadotropic hormone and it is released in gonads."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Which of the following hormone is responsible for the secretion of milk after parturition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ICSH",
            "b) ACTH",
            "c) LH",
            "d) Prolactin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Prolactin is responsible for the secretion of milk after parturition. It is also known as the luteotropic hormone. It is a protein substance."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Menstruation is due to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction of FSH",
            "b) Increase of LH",
            "c) Reduction is Estrogen and progesterone",
            "d) Decrease in LH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Menstruation is a regular discharge of blood and mucosal tissue from the inner lining of the uterus through vagina. Menstruation is due to Reduction is Estrogen and progesterone."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": " Estrogens and testosterone are steroid hormones and most likely bind to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytoplasmic receptors",
            "b) Membrane ion channels",
            "c) Enzyme linked membrane receptors",
            "d) G protein coupled receptor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steroids hormone receptors are found in the nucleus, cytosol, and on the plasma membrane of target cells. They are generally intracellular receptors."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Which of the following controls the functions of sertoli cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) ACTH",
            "c) Estrogen",
            "d) Testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sertoli cells are somatic cells of the testis. They facilitate the progression of germ cells to spermatozoa. FSH controls the functions of sertoli cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Testosterone is secreted by  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sertoli cells",
            "b) Leydig cells",
            "c) Thyroid",
            "d) Spermatogenic cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Testosterone is the key male sex hormone that regulates fertility. Testosterone is secreted by Leydig cells. Leydig cells are found in seminiferous tubules in the testicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "Corpus luteum secretes _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) LH",
            "b) Progesterone",
            "c) Progesterone and LH",
            "d) Progesterone and estrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corpus luteum develops from an ovarian follicle during the luteal phase of menstrual cycle. Corpus luteum secretes Progesterone and estrogen."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Aldosterone is secreted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zona glomerulosa",
            "b) Zona fasciculata",
            "c) Zona reticularis",
            "d) Zona pellucida"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aldosterone is secreted by Zona glomerulosa.  Zona glomerulosa is the most superficial layer of adrenal cortex. Its cells are ovoid and arranged in clusters."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "____________ is a male sex hormone.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estrogen",
            "b) Androgen",
            "c) Insulin",
            "d) Pheromones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Androgen is a male sex hormone. It primarily influences the growth and development of the male reproductive system."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Anabolic steroids are __________ forms of testosterone.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ineffective",
            "b) Natural",
            "c) Synthetic",
            "d) Super active"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anabolic steroids are synthetic substances related to make sex hormone. They promote the growth of skeletal muscle and the development of male sexual characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "In male reproductive system, testicles are inside a sac called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scrotum",
            "b) Bladder",
            "c) Rectum",
            "d) Glands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scrotum is the anatomical male reproductive structure. Testicles are inside a sac called as Scrotum."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "What is the function of LH hormone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stimulates oxidative respiration",
            "b) Stimulates muscle growth",
            "c) Causes color change in skin",
            "d) Stimulates production of testosterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LH hormone is luteinizing hormone.  It is produced in pituitary gland. In female acute rise in LH triggers ovulation. It stimulates the production of testosterone in males. "
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "What are the female gonads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ovary",
            "b) Ova",
            "c) Testis",
            "d) Testicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ovaries are part of the female reproductive system. They produce eggs and hormones. "
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Portion of placenta contributed by the embryo is the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chorion",
            "b) Yolk sac",
            "c) Amnion",
            "d) Allantois"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chorion is one of the membranes that surround the fetus while it is still being form. Chorion is contributed by the embryo."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "Which vessel transports blood rich in oxygen and nutrients to the fetus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ductus arteriosus",
            "b) Ductus venosus",
            "c) Umbilical vein",
            "d) Umbilical artery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Umbilical vein is the vein present during fetal development that carries oxygenated blood from the placenta into the growing fetus."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "The period immediately after birth to four weeks of age is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Senescent",
            "b) Adolescent",
            "c) Infancy",
            "d) Neonatal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Neonatal is pertaining to the newborn period, especially the first 4 weeks after birth."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "In which menstrual cycle phase does implantation occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Menses",
            "b) Ovulation",
            "c) Secretory",
            "d) Proliferative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Secretory phase is the 2nd half of the menstrual cycle after ovulation. During the Secretory phase implantation occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "Which extra embryonic membrane encloses the embryo in a fluid filled cavity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allantois",
            "b) Chorion",
            "c) Amnion",
            "d) Yolk sac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amnion is a membrane that closely covers the embryo when first formed. It fills with the amniotic fluid which causes the amnion to expand and become amniotic sac."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "Which hormone prevents the second pregnancy during gestation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FSH",
            "b) LH",
            "c) HCG",
            "d) Progesterone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Progesterone level raises during 2nd half of the menstrual cycle. Its role is to thicken the lining of uterus each month. Progesterone prevents the second pregnancy during gestation."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "When is it first possible to distinguish the sex of the fetus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st month",
            "b) 2nd month",
            "c) 3rd month",
            "d) 4th month"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the 3rd month of pregnancy is it first possible to distinguish the sex of the fetus. XX leads to a baby girl and XY leads to baby boy."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Within which extra embryonic membrane are blood cells formed in the early stage of development?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yolk sac",
            "b) Allantois",
            "c) Chorion",
            "d) Allantois"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yolk sac provides nourishment. It produces blood cells until the placenta fully forms later in the pregnancy. Towards the end of first trimester the yolk sac shrinks and can no longer be seen on the sonogram."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "The structure which implants in the endometrium is termed as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Embryo",
            "b) Zygote",
            "c) Morula",
            "d) Blastocyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fertilized egg begins to develop into a hollow ball of cells called Blastocyst. The Blastocyst implants in the wall of the uterus."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "Which membrane plays the greatest role in nutrient and waste exchange?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amnion",
            "b) Chorion",
            "c) Allantois",
            "d) Yolk sac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chorion is the outermost membrane surrounding an embryo. Chorion is the double layered membrane formed by the trophoblast. It plays the greatest role in nutrient and waste exchange."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "Human placenta is classified as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mesoeliochorial",
            "b) Epitheliochoria",
            "c) Haemochorial",
            "d) Endotheliochorial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Decidual reaction is the set of changes in the endometrium of the uterus that prepares it for implantation. These changes are observed in each menstrual cycle and enhanced after implantation."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "Diabetes insipidus is due to insufficient release of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulin",
            "b) ADH",
            "c) Thyroxine",
            "d) Glucagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diabetes insipidus is a disorder of salt and water metabolism marked by intense thirst and heavy urination. Diabetes insipidus is due to insufficient release of ADH."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "Which of the following gastrointestinal hormone stimulates insulin secretion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GIP",
            "b) CCK",
            "c) Gastrin",
            "d) Secretin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GIP is gastroinhibitory peptide. It is also known as glucose dependent insulinotroic peptide. It is a weak inhibitor of gastric acid secretion; its main role is to stimulate insulin secretion."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "Which of the following element is needed for insulin to exert its maximal effect in glucose uptake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vanadium",
            "b) Molybdenum",
            "c) Selenium",
            "d) Chromium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chromium is an essential mineral that appears to have a beneficial role in the regulation of insulin action and its effects on carbohydrate, protein and lipid metabolism.  Chromium is an important factor for enhancing insulin activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "Insulin promotes _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucosuria",
            "b) Glycogenesis",
            "c) Glycogenolysis",
            "d) Gluconeogenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glycogenesis is a process of glycogen synthesis from sugar. Insulin promotes Glycogenesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "Humulin is being commercially produced from a transgenic species of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhizobium",
            "b) Saccharomyces",
            "c) Escherichia",
            "d) Mycobacterim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Humulin is being commercially produced from a transgenic species of Escherichia. Humulin is a man-made form of hormone that is produced from the body. It was first done by Eli Lily company."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "Insulin receptors are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extrinsic protein",
            "b) Intrinsic protein",
            "c) G protein",
            "d) Trimeric protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Insulin receptors are extrinsic protein. Insulin binds to r4ecetors on the cell surface. This activates the cell’s glucose transporter molecules to form a doorway in the cell membrane so that glucose can enter the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "What do endocrine cells of the pancreas secrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omega growth hormone",
            "b) Beta somatostatin",
            "c) Delta insulin",
            "d) Alpha glucagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alpha glucagon is secreted by endocrine cells of the pancreas. They make up to 20% of human islet cells synthesizing and secreting glucagon."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "Where does synthesis of insulin begin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rRER",
            "b) sRER",
            "c) Nucleolus",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nucleolus is a part of eukaryote cell where ribosomes are made. It is the largest structure in the nucleus.  Synthesis of insulin begins in Nucleolus."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "How many intermolecular and interamolecular disulfide bond is present in insulin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 Intermolecular, 2 intramolecular",
            "b) 2 Intermolecular, 2 intramolecular",
            "c) 2 Intermolecular, 1 intramolecular",
            "d) 1 Intermolecular, 3 intramolecular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 2 Intermolecular and 1 intramolecular disulfide bond is present in insulin."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "Which of the following order is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulin > Proinsulin > Preproinsulin",
            "b) Preproinsulin > Insulin > Proinsulin",
            "c) Proinsulin > Preproinsulin > Insulin",
            "d) Preproinsulin > Proinsulin > Insulin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Insulin is made up of two peptide chains referred to as A chain and B chain. A and B chains are linked together by disulfide bonds and an additional disulfide bond is formed within A chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "What is the beta subunit of the insulin receptor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protein kinase",
            "b) Tyrosine kinase",
            "c) Tryptophan kinase",
            "d) Taurine kinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tyrosine kinase is an enzyme that can transfer a phosphate group from ATP to a protein in the cell. It functions as an on or off switch in many cellular functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "What do delta cells secrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cortisol",
            "b) Glucose",
            "c) Pancreatic enzyme",
            "d) Somatostatin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Somatostatin is also known as growth hormone. It is a peptide hormone. Somatostatin is secreted by delta cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "What is the function of GLUT 4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose transport",
            "b) Glycogen transport",
            "c) Insulin transport",
            "d) Glucagon transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GLUT 4 is the insulin regulated glucose transporter found primarily in adipose tissues and striated muscle. "
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "Division of human egg is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Holoblastic and unequal",
            "b) Meroblastic",
            "c) Holoblastic and equal",
            "d) Isoblastic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Division of human egg is Holoblastic and unequal. Holoblastic cleavage is seen in the eggs containing moderate to sparse amount of yolk. Holoblastic cleavage is the complete division of an isolecithal or microlecithal egg into blastomeres."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "The lytic enzyme released y sperm is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ligase",
            "b) Acrosome",
            "c) Androgamone",
            "d) Hyaluronidase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The lytic enzyme released y sperm is Hyaluronidase. It catalyzes the degradation of hyaluronic acid. "
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Number of autosomes in human primary spermatocyte is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 46",
            "b) 44",
            "c) 23",
            "d) 22"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An autosome is a chromosome that is not a sex chromosome. The DNA in autosomes is collectively known as atDNA or auDNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "Ovum receives the sperm in the region of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Animal pole",
            "b) Equator",
            "c) Vegetal pole",
            "d) Pigmented area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An embryo is divided into two hemispheres: the animal ole and vegetal pole within a blastula. The animal pole consists of small cells that divide rapidly in contrast with the vegetal pole below it. Ovum receives the sperm in the region of Vegetal pole."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Which of the following organ is devoid of gland?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vulva",
            "b) Oviduct",
            "c) Uterus",
            "d) Vagina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oviduct is a simple ciliated tube, lined with tissues. It is devoid of a gland."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "In the absence of acrosome the sperm _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cannot penetrate the egg",
            "b) Cannot get energy",
            "c) Cannot get food",
            "d) Cannot swim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acrosome contains digestive enzymes. These enzymes break the outer membrane of an ovum. In the absence of acrosome the sperm cannot penetrate the egg."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "Among the following stem cells which are found in the umbilical cord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Embryonic stem cells",
            "b) Adult stem cells",
            "c) Cord blood stem cells",
            "d) Blood stem cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cord blood cells are the blood left over in the placenta and in the umbilical cord after the birth of the baby. The cord blood is composed of RBCs, WBCs, plasma, platelets and is also rich in hematopoietic stem cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "Human sperm moves with the help of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cilia",
            "b) Flagellum",
            "c) Basal body",
            "d) Nucleosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Human sperm is haploid. Human sperm moves with the help of Flagellum. It is found in the tail region of the sperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "Cryptorchidism is a condition in which _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male hormones are not reactive",
            "b) Ovaries are removed",
            "c) Sperms are not formed",
            "d) Testes fail to descend in scrotal sacs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cryptorchidism is also known as undescended testicle. It is a condition in which the testicles haven’t moved into the bag of skin below the penis before birth."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "Bidder’s canal is meant for the passage of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sperms",
            "b) Urine",
            "c) Ova",
            "d) Saline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bidder’s canal is a spherical, brownish organ. It is present in the kidney. Bidder’s canal is meant for the passage of Sperms. It is found in frogs."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "Spermatogonia are formed by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meiosis",
            "b) Mitosis",
            "c) Amitosis",
            "d) Meiosis II"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Mitosis is a type of cell division that results in two daughter cells each having same number and kind of chromosome as in the parent nucleus. Spermatogonia are formed by Mitosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "Wolffian duct forms _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oviduct",
            "b) Urethra",
            "c) Epididymis",
            "d) Ejaculatory duct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wolffian duct is the mesonephric embryonic duct that leads to the development of male gonads. Wolffian duct develops into Epididymis."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "Type of placenta found in human is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discoidal",
            "b) Cotyledonary",
            "c) Zonary",
            "d) Diffuse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Placenta found in human is called Discoidal. It is a placenta in which the chorionic villi are arranged in a circular plate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "Acrosome is made up of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Mitochondria",
            "c) Centrioles",
            "d) Golgi bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acrosome is made up of Golgi bodies. It contains digestive enzymes. It is present in sperm."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "Which of the following groups includes all STD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hepatitis-B, Hemophilia, AIDS",
            "b) AIDS, Syphilis, Cholera",
            "c) Gonorrhea,   Hepatitis-B, Chlamydiasis",
            "d) HIV, Malaria, Trichomoniasis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: STD is sexually transmitted diseases. It is a disease that is transmitted through sexual contact and caused by bacteria, viruses or parasites. Gonorrhea, Hepatitis-B, Chlamydiasis are STDS."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "MTP is considered safe up to how many weeks of pregnancy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 18",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MTP is Medical termination of pregnancy. It is a medical way of getting rid of unwanted pregnancy. It is also called an induced abortion. MTP is considered safe up to12 weeks of pregnancy."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the widely accepted method of contraception in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IUDs",
            "b) Tubectomy",
            "c) Cervical caps",
            "d) Diaphragms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IUDs are intrauterine device. It is a birth control device that is inserted into woman’s uterus to recent pregnancy. IUDs is the widely accepted method of contraception in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "The interferons are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antibiotics",
            "b) Antibacterial proteins",
            "c) Immunosuppressive drugs",
            "d) Antiviral proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The interferons are a group of signaling protein made and released by host cells in response to the presence of several pathogens like viruses, bacteria, parasites and also tumor cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "Which of the following test is used to detect AIDS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Western blot and ELISA",
            "b) Northern blot and ELISA",
            "c) ELISA and Southern blot",
            "d) ELISA and Immunoblot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ELISA is enzyme linked immunosorbent assay. It is a test that uses antibodies and color change to identify a substance. Western blot is used to detect specific proteins in a sample of tissue homogenate or extract."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "Growth curve is normally _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) J shaped",
            "b) S shaped",
            "c) C shaped",
            "d) V shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Growth curve is an empirical model of the evolution of a quantity over time. It is S shaped curve. It has lag phase, log phase, stationary phase and death phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "Causative agent of syphilis is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HIV",
            "b) Neisseria",
            "c) Treponema pallidum",
            "d) Trichomonas vaginalis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Syphilis is a bacterial infection usually spread by sexual contact that starts as a painless sore. Causative agent of syphilis is Treponema pallidum."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "World population day falls on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11TH July",
            "b) 11th may",
            "c) 10th July",
            "d) 10th may"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: World population day falls on11TH July. It is to raise awareness of global population issues."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "Study of the human population is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anthropology",
            "b) Demography",
            "c) Geography",
            "d) Ethnology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Demography is the study of statistics such as births, deaths, income, or the incidence of diseases that illustrate changing structure of the human population."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "What is the function of copper-T?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stops cleavage",
            "b) Checks mutation",
            "c) Stops gastrulation",
            "d) Stops fertilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Copper-T is a type of IUDs. It contains copper. It is used for birth control and emergency contraception.  Copper-T Stops fertilization and inhibits pregnancy."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "Amniocentesis is a process of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Know about brain disease",
            "b) Grow cells on culture media",
            "c) Determine disease of the embryo",
            "d) Determine mutations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amniocentesis is a process in which amniotic fluid is sampled sing a hollow needle inserted into the uterus to screen for abnormalities in the developing fetus."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "Saheli is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An oral contraceptive for females",
            "b) A diaphragm used by males",
            "c) A surgical sterilation method",
            "d) A diaphragm used by females"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Saheli is world’s first and only oral non steroid contraceptive pill. It is also known as Centchroman. It has zero side effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "Test tube baby employs which of the following technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ICSI",
            "b) ZIFT",
            "c) GIFT",
            "d) IUI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ZIFT is zygote intrafallopian transfer. It is used to treat infertility. Egg cells are removed from woman’s ovary and in vitro fertilized. The resulting zygote is placed into fallopian tube by use of laparoscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "Histamine is secreted by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mast cells",
            "b) Liver cells",
            "c) Kidneys",
            "d) Nerve cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Histamine is secreted by Mast cells. It increases the permeability of the capillaries to WBCs and some proteins to allow them to engage pathogens in the infected tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "AIDS is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in number of killer T cells",
            "b) Reduction in number of Helper T cells",
            "c) Autoimmune disease",
            "d) Inability to produce interferons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: AIDS is acquired immune deficiency syndrome. It is caused by HIV. In this condition, there is a reduction in the number of Helper T cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "Synthesis of RNA and proteins take place in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) M phase",
            "b) S phase",
            "c) G1 Phase",
            "d) G2 phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: G1 Phase is the first phase of the cell cycle. It is a part of Interphase. Synthesis of RNA and proteins take place in G1 Phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "When does synapsis occur during meiosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zygotene",
            "b) Leptotene",
            "c) Diplotene",
            "d) Pachytene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zygotene is the 2nd stage of the prophase of meiosis. Formation of synaptonemal complexes is seen to form bivalents."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "Spindle fibers are made up of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spindles",
            "b) Tubulin",
            "c) Flagella",
            "d) Humulin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tubulin is a protein of globular protein. It forms microtubules. It helps in cell division."
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "Chromosomes are separated during?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase",
            "b) Anaphase",
            "c) Metaphase",
            "d) Telophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Anaphase is the 3rd stage of cell division. During this stage chromosomes move away from one another to opposite poles of the spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "Crossing over occurs between _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two daughter nuclei",
            "b) Two different bivalents",
            "c) Non sister chromatids of bivalents",
            "d) Sister chromatids of bivalents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Crossing over occurs between Non sisters chromatids of bivalents. Chromosomal crossing over is exchange of genetic material between homologous chromosomes that r4esults in recombinant chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "Replication of centriole occurs in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interphase",
            "b) Prophase",
            "c) Metaphase",
            "d) Anaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interphase is a phase of cell cycle in which typical cell sends most of its life. During this phase cell copies its DNA in preparation for mitosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "Colchicine arrests which of the following stages of cell division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anaphase",
            "b) Telophase",
            "c) Interphase",
            "d) Metaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Colchicine is an alkaloid. It is used to treat acute attacks of gout. Colchicine arrests Metaphase stage of cell division. "
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "Cell plate is laid during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytokinesis",
            "b) Karyokinesis",
            "c) Interphase",
            "d) Metaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cytokinesis is a process of cell division which divides cytoplasm of a parental cell into two daughter cells. It occurs with mitosis and meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "DNA replicates during ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1 phase",
            "b) G2 phase",
            "c) S phase",
            "d) Prophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: S phase is a part of the cell cycle in which DNA is replicated. Accurate DNA replication is necessary to prevent genetic abnormalities."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "Crossing over occurs during _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diplotene",
            "b) Pachytene",
            "c) Leptotene",
            "d) Zygotene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Crossing over occurs during Pachytene. Pachytene is a 3rd stage of the prophase of meiosis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "Polyploidy can be artificially induced by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Self pollination",
            "b) Line breeding",
            "c) Inbreeding",
            "d) Colchicine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyploidy s condition in which normally diploid cell acquires one or more additional sets of chromosomes. Polyploidy can be artificially induced by Colchicine."
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "Chromosomes are arranged along equator during ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase",
            "b) Metaphase",
            "c) Anaphase",
            "d) Telophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Metaphase is the 2nd stage of cell division. During metaphase chromosome arrange themselves in the middle of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Question": "Which phase comes between G1 and G2 phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Go",
            "b) M",
            "c) S",
            "d) I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: S phase comes between G1 and G2 phase. It is an important phase.DNA replicates in S Phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 901,
        "Question": "Chiasmata formation takes place during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase I",
            "b) Metaphase I",
            "c) Anaphase I",
            "d) Telophase I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chiasmata formation takes place during Prophase I. During this stage chromosomes are duplicated. Chiasmata is a point where paired chromosomes remain in contact during the first metaphase of meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 902,
        "Question": "Amitosis is shown by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Euglena",
            "b) Syllis",
            "c) Hydra",
            "d) Bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Amitosis is shown by Bacteria. Amitosis is a simple method of cell division which occurs without the formation of spindles and the appearance of chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 903,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simplest amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycine",
            "b) Alanine",
            "c) Aspergine",
            "d) Tyrosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glycine is the simplest amino acid. It has a single hydrogen atom as its side chain. It is a proteinogenic amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 904,
        "Question": "The animal cells are interconnected by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell wall",
            "b) Desmosomes",
            "c) Plasma membrane",
            "d) Plasmodesmata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Desmosomes are structure by which adjacent cells are attached, formed from protein plagues in cell membranes linked by filaments."
    },
    {
        "id": 905,
        "Question": "Polythene chromosomes are found due to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitosis",
            "b) Endomixes",
            "c) Endomitosis",
            "d) Meiosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Endomitosis is a replication of chromosomes in the absence of cell or nuclear division, resulting in numerous copies within each cell, it occurs in salivary glands of Drosophila."
    },
    {
        "id": 906,
        "Question": "r-RNA is synthesized by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytoplasm",
            "b) Golgi body",
            "c) Nucleolus",
            "d) Nucleus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nucleolus is a small dense spherical structure in the nucleus of the cell. r-RNA is synthesized by  Nucleolus."
    },
    {
        "id": 907,
        "Question": "Cristae are associated with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria",
            "b) Cytoplasm",
            "c) Vacuole",
            "d) Ribosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cristae are associated with Mitochondria. It is a fold in the inner membrane of mitochondrion. It provides a large area for chemical reactions to occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 908,
        "Question": "Glycocalyx is associated with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell wall",
            "b) Plasma membrane",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) Ribosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glycocalyx is associated with Plasma membrane. It is a glycoprotein and glycolipid covering the membrane. It is also known as a peculiar matrix."
    },
    {
        "id": 909,
        "Question": "Histone octamer contains ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 types of histones",
            "b) 5 types of histones",
            "c) 6 types of histones",
            "d) 8 histones of four different types"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Histone octamer is an 8 protein complex found at the centre of nucleosome core particles. It consists of 2 copies of 4 core histone proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 910,
        "Question": "Detoxification of lipid drugs and other harmful compounds in ER is carried out by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytochrome P450",
            "b) Cytochrome bf",
            "c) Cytochrome D",
            "d) Cytochrome F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cytochrome P450 enzymes function to metabolize potentially toxic compounds. There are 57 human genes coding for various cytochrome450."
    },
    {
        "id": 911,
        "Question": "Sodium and potassium pumps are examples of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passive transport",
            "b) Plasmolysis",
            "c) Active transport",
            "d) Osmosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Active transport is the movement of ions or molecules across a cell membrane into a region of higher concentration assisted by enzymes and requiring energy. Sodium and potassium pumps are examples of Active transport."
    },
    {
        "id": 912,
        "Question": "Cell theory is not applicable to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virus",
            "b) Micro organisms",
            "c) Fungi",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell theory is not applicable to a virus as a virus is considered living and nonliving."
    },
    {
        "id": 913,
        "Question": "Digestive enzymes are present in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liposomes",
            "b) Lysosomes",
            "c) Ribosome",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lysosomes is an organelle in cytoplasm containing enzymes enclosed in the membrane. It contains hydrolytic enzymes that can breakdown biomolecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 914,
        "Question": "Which among the following is known as mitoplast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondria without outer membrane",
            "b) Mitochondria without inner membrane",
            "c) Mitochondria without membranes",
            "d) Another name for mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mitoplast is a mitochondrion that has been stripped of its outer membrane leaving inner membrane intact."
    },
    {
        "id": 915,
        "Question": "Cell drinking is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exocytosis",
            "b) Endocytosis",
            "c) Pinocytosis",
            "d) Phagocytosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: Cell drinking is Pinocytosis.  It is ingestion of liquid into cell by the budding of small vesicles from the cell membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 916,
        "Question": "Amyloplasts are articles storing _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fats",
            "b) Proteins",
            "c) Lipids",
            "d) Starch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Amyloplasts are articles storing starch. They are non pigmented organelles. They also convert starch back into sugar to release energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 917,
        "Question": "Centrioles take part in the formation of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell plate",
            "b) Spindle",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) To start cell division"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Centrioles are a cylindrical structure composed of tubulin. Centrioles take part in the formation of Spindle."
    },
    {
        "id": 918,
        "Question": "Formation of antibodies within our body is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passive immunity",
            "b) Active immunity",
            "c) Innate Immunity",
            "d) Acquired immunity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Active immunity is a long lasting immunity developed by antibodies produced by an individual’s own cells. It can be developed in three ways."
    },
    {
        "id": 919,
        "Question": "Metastasis is associated with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Malignant tumor",
            "b) Benign tumor",
            "c) Gall Tumor",
            "d) Crown gall tumor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metastasis is associated with a malignant tumor. Metastasis is spreading of cancer cells from the place where they first formed to another part of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 920,
        "Question": "Leukemia is due to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excess of RBCs",
            "b) Excess of Platelets",
            "c) Excess of WBCs",
            "d) Excess of antibodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Leukemia is due to an excess of WBCs. It is also known as blood cancer i.e., blood-forming tissues hindering body’s ability to fight infection."
    },
    {
        "id": 921,
        "Question": "Tunnel vision is associated with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcoholism",
            "b) Smoking",
            "c) Drug addiction",
            "d) Mental health"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tunnel vision is a peripheral loss of vision. It is caused due to severe addiction of alcohol."
    },
    {
        "id": 922,
        "Question": "The organism which carries a disease from one organism to another is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agent",
            "b) Host",
            "c) Parasite",
            "d) Vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An organism that transmits a disease or parasite from one animal or plant to another is known as a vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 923,
        "Question": "Which immunoglobulin is the largest in size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ig A",
            "b) Ig D",
            "c) Ig E",
            "d) Ig M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ig M is the largest immunoglobulin in size. It is the first antibody to appear in the response to initial exposure to an antigen."
    },
    {
        "id": 924,
        "Question": "Antigens are present ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) On cell surface",
            "b) On n nuclear membrane",
            "c) Inside cytoplasm",
            "d) Inside nucleus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Antigens are a toxic or foreign substance which induces an immune response in the body especially the production of antibody. Antigens are present on the surface of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 925,
        "Question": "BCG vaccine is to prevent ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AIDS",
            "b) TB",
            "c) Cholera",
            "d) Typhoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: BCG vaccine is to prevent tuberculosis. BCG stands for Bacillus Calamitte Guerin. "
    },
    {
        "id": 926,
        "Question": "Passive immunity can be obtained by injecting _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antibodies",
            "b) Antigen",
            "c) Vaccination",
            "d) Antibiotics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Passive immunity is the transfer of active humoral immunity in the form of readymade antibodies. Passive immunity can occur naturally when maternal antibodies are transferred to the fetus through placenta and it can also be induced artificially."
    },
    {
        "id": 927,
        "Question": "Aflatoxins are produced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacteria",
            "b) Virus",
            "c) Fungus",
            "d) Nematode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aflatoxins are produced by a fungus. Aflatoxins are poisonous carcinogens that are produced by some molds which grow in soil, decaying vegetation, hay and grains."
    },
    {
        "id": 928,
        "Question": "Aedes mosquito is a vector for transmitting  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Malaria",
            "b) Cholera",
            "c) Dengue",
            "d) Fever"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dengue is a mosquito borne disease. It is caused by Aedes mosquito. It is a viral disease. "
    },
    {
        "id": 929,
        "Question": "Virus envelope is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Core",
            "b) Capsid",
            "c) Virion",
            "d) Nucleoprotein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Virus envelope is known as the capsid. It is a protein shell of a virus. It consists of several oligomeric structural subunits made of proteins called protomers."
    },
    {
        "id": 930,
        "Question": "Dipsomania is a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depression",
            "b) Alcohol addiction",
            "c) Tendency to take much water",
            "d) Insanity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dipsomania is alcohol addiction. It is characterized by intermittent bouts of craving for alcohol."
    },
    {
        "id": 931,
        "Question": "Widal test is carried out to test _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) HIV",
            "b) Typhoid",
            "c) Malaria",
            "d) Diabetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Widal test is carried out to test Typhoid. It is a common agglutination test employed in the serological diagnosis of enteric fever."
    },
    {
        "id": 932,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is caused by a virus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cholera",
            "b) Measles",
            "c) Diphtheria",
            "d) Whooping cough"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Measles is caused by a virus. It is also called as rubella. It is a highly contagious infectious disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 933,
        "Question": "Which of the following are cancer cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hela cells",
            "b) CD4",
            "c) Plasma cells",
            "d) Memory cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hela cells are a type of immortal cell line used in scientific research. It was derived from cervical cancer cells taken from Henrietta Lacks."
    },
    {
        "id": 934,
        "Question": "Which cell secretes antibody?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monocytes",
            "b) Lymphocytes",
            "c) Neutrophils",
            "d) Eosinphils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lymphocytes secretes antibody. It is a type of WBC with a single round nucleus occurring in the lymphatic system."
    },
    {
        "id": 935,
        "Question": "To confirm AIDS using ELISA we use ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Northern blotting",
            "b) Western blotting",
            "c) Southern blotting",
            "d) Eastern blotting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Western blotting is often used to separate and identify proteins. It is a widely used analytical technique in molecular biology. Western blotting is done in ELISA."
    },
    {
        "id": 936,
        "Question": "Which antibody initiates allergic reactions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ig A",
            "b) Ig D",
            "c) Ig E",
            "d) Ig M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ig E is a type of immunoglobulin. It is synthesized by plasma cells. It consists of 2 heavy chain and 2 light chains. Ig E antibody initiates allergic reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 937,
        "Question": "Monoclonal antibodies are produced by ___________ type of cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uninucleate",
            "b) Multinucleate",
            "c) Hybridoma",
            "d) Prokaryotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Monoclonal antibodies are antibodies that are made by identical immune cells that are all clones of a unique parent cell. They bind to the same epitope. Monoclonal antibodies are produced by the Hybridoma type of cells."
    }
]